<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="MCELLBI" name="Molecular And Cell Biology">
    <course name="Of Molecules and Man:  A View for the Layman" number="11" units="3">
        Examination of molecular mechanisms that underlie normal functions of living organisms and ways in which those functions are disrupted by medical disorders and environmental agents. Designed to provide non-biologists with an understanding of modern biochemistry and the ways we control and alter the biology of our life and environment.
    </course>
    <course name="Current Topics in the Biological Sciences" number="15" units="2">
        Students in this course will critically examine modern methods of biological investigations and their social implications. Relevant literature will be used to present basic biological concepts that address the cultural, technological and health aspects of current topics in the biological sciences. Designing and evaluating scientific questions will be stressed.
    </course>
    <course name="Genes, Cells, and Creatures" number="31" units="3">
        An introduction for non-majors to some important concepts of modern biology, ranging from biological molecules to organisms and the environment. Some possible topics are: 1) What is DNA and how does it serve as genetic material? 2) How does the immune system cope with exposure to disease-causing bacteria? 3) How do embryos develop? 4) Can we determine the size of human population that the earth can sustain?
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Human Physiology" number="32" units="3">
        A comprehensive introduction to human cell biology. The course will concentrate on basic mechanisms underlying human life processes, including cells and membranes; nerve and muscle function; cardiovascular, respiratory, renal, and gastrointestinal physiology; metabolism, endocrinology, and reproduction.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Human Physiology Laboratory" number="32L" units="2">
        Experiments and demonstrations are designed to amplify and reinforce information presented in 32. Exercises include investigations into the structure and function of muscle, nerve, cardiovascular, renal, respiratory, endocrine, and blood systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Genetics and Society" number="41" units="3">
        Basic communication of inheritance; gene mapping; gene expression and genetic disease in animals and humans; social inheritance of genetics.
    </course>
    <course name="The Immune System and Disease" number="50" units="3">
        Course will discuss how the immune system resolves, prevents, or causes disease. A general overview of the immune system will be covered in the first five weeks followed by five weeks discussing infectious diseases including anthrax, mad cow, herpes, malaria, tuberculosis, and HIV. In addition, other lectures will focus on current immunology topics including vaccines, autoimmunity, allergy, transplantation, and cancer.
    </course>
    <course name="Plagues and Pandemics" number="55" units="3">
        Discussion of how infectious agents cause disease and impact society at large. We will examine historical and current examples of plagues and pandemics and consider the question of what we should do to ameliorate the impact of infectious disease in the future. The course is intended for non-majors and will begin by briefly providing necessary background in microbiology and immunology. The primary focus in each subsequent week, however, will be on discussing a particular infectious disease. The course will be broad in scope covering biological, historical, ethical and social implications of each disease.
    </course>
    <course name="Brain, Mind, and Behavior" number="61" units="3">
        Introduction to human brain mechanisms of sensation, movement, perception, thinking, learning, memory, and emotion in terms of anatomy, physiology, and chemistry of the nervous system in health and disease. Intended for students in the humanities and social sciences and others not majoring in the biological sciences.
    </course>
    <course name="Drugs and the Brain" number="C62" units="3">
        The history, chemical nature, botanical origins, and effects on the human brain and behavior of drugs such as stimulants, depressants, psychedelics, analgesics, antidepressants, antipsychotics, steroids, and other psychoactive substances of both natural and synthetic origin. The necessary biological, chemical, and psychological background material for understanding the content of this course will be contained within the course itself. Also listed as Letters and Science C30T.
    </course>
    <course name="Exploring the Brain: Introduction to Neuroscience" number="64" units="3">
        This course will introduce lower division undergraduates to the fundamentals of neuroscience. The first part of the course covers basic membrane properties, synapses, action potentials, chemical and electrical synaptic interactions, receptor potentials, and receptor proteins. The second part of the course covers networks in invertebrates, memory and learning behavior, modulation, vertebrate brain and spinal cord, retina, visual cortex architecture, hierarchy, development, and higher cortical centers.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="84A" units="1,2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="84B" units="1,2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="84C" units="1,2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="84D" units="1,2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="84E" units="1,2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Biochemistry and Molecular Biology" number="90A" units="1">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Cell and Developmental Biology" number="90B" units="1">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Genetics and Development" number="90C" units="1">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Immunology" number="90D" units="1">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Neurobiology" number="90E" units="1">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Biochemistry and Molecular Biology" number="91A" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Cell and Developmental Biology" number="91B" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Genetics and Development" number="91C" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Immunology" number="91D" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Neurobiology" number="91E" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Studying the Biological Sciences" number="C96" units="1">
        Freshmen will be introduced to the &quot;culture&quot; of the biological sciences, along with an in-depth orientation to the academic life and the culture of the university as they relate to majoring in biology. Students will learn concepts, skills, and information that they can use in their major course, and as future science professionals. Restricted to freshmen in the biology scholars program. Also listed as Plant and Microbial Biology C96 and Integrative Biology C96.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study" number="98" units="1-4">
        Lectures and small group discussions focusing on topics of interest, varying from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study" number="99" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Biophysical Chemistry: Physical Principles and the Molecules of Life" number="C100A" units="4">
        Thermodynamic and kinetic concepts applied to understanding the chemistry and structure of biomolecules (proteins, DNA, and RNA). Molecular distributions, reaction kinetics, enzyme kinetics. Bioenergetics, energy transduction, and motor proteins. Electrochemical potential, membranes, and ion channels. Also listed as Chemistry C130.
    </course>
    <course name="Biochemistry: Pathways, Mechanisms, and Regulation" number="100B" units="3">
        Bioenergetics, metabolic pathways, and regulation of metabolism; the chemistry, structure, function, synthesis, and degradation of the constituent molecules (amino acids, fatty acids, sugars, nucleotides) and cofactors of the major biological macromolecules. Diseases that are linked to metabolic disorders. Designed for majors in the biochemistry and molecular biology, genetics and development, or immunology emphases.
    </course>
    <course name="Survey of the Principles of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology" number="102" units="4">
        A comprehensive survey of the fundamentals of biological chemistry, including the properties of intermediary metabolites, the structure and function of biological macromolecules, the logic of metabolic pathways (both degradative and biosynthetic) and the molecular basis of genetics and gene expression.
    </course>
    <course name="Bacterial Pathogenesis" number="C103" units="3">
        This course for upper division and graduate students will explore the molecular and cellular basis of microbial pathogenesis. The course will focus on model microbial systems which illustrate mechanisms of pathogenesis. Most of the emphasis will be on bacterial pathogens of mammals, but there will be some discussion of viral and protozoan pathogens. There will be an emphasis on experimental approaches. The course will also include some aspects of bacterial genetics and physiology, immune response to infection, and the cell biology of host-parasite interactions. Also listed as Public Health C102 and Plant and Microbial Biology C103.
    </course>
    <course name="General Biochemistry and Molecular Biology" number="110" units="4">
        Molecular biology of prokaryotic and eukaryotic cells and their viruses. Mechanisms of DNA replication, transcription, translation. Structure of genes and chromosomes. Regulation of gene expression. Biochemical processes and principles in membrane structure and function, intracellular trafficking and subcellular compartmentation, cytoskeletal architecture, nucleocytoplasmic transport, signal transduction mechanisms, and cell cycle control.
    </course>
    <course name="General Biochemistry and Molecular Biology Laboratory" number="110L" units="4">
        Experimental techniques of biochemistry and molecular biology, designed to accompany the lectures in 100B and 110.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Structural Biology" number="111" units="3">
        This course for upper division majors will teach principles of protein and nucleic acid structures and outline basic experimental methods for conformational studies. The classical problems of structural biology, as well as new approaches and methods, will be emphasized.
    </course>
    <course name="General Microbiology" number="C112" units="4">
        This course will explore the molecular bases for physiological and biochemical diversity among members of the two major domains, Bacteria and Archaea. The ecological significance and evolutionary origins of this diversity will be discussed. Molecular, genetic, and structure-function analyses of microbial cell cycles, adaptive responses, metabolic capability, and macromolecular syntheses will be emphasized. Also listed as Plant and Microbial Biology C112.
    </course>
    <course name="General Microbiology Laboratory" number="C112L" units="2">
        Experimental techniques of microbiology designed to accompany the lecture in C112 and C148. The primary emphasis in the laboratory will be on the cultivation and physiological and genetic characterization of bacteria. Laboratory exercises will include the observation, enrichment, and isolation of bacteria from selected environments. Also listed as Plant and Microbial Biology C112L.
    </course>
    <course name="Applied Microbiology and Biochemistry" number="113" units="2">
        A survey of modern developments emphasizing the application of the knowledge of fundamental microbiology to industrial processes. Topics include production of metabolites, enzymes, and single-cell proteins; genetic manipulation of microorganisms; recovery of minerals; and energy production.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Comparative Virology" number="C114" units="4">
        Viruses will be considered as infectious agents of bacteria, plants, and animals (vertebrates and invertebrates). Several families of viruses will be compared with respect to biochemical, structural and morphological properties, and strategies of infection and replication. Also listed as Environ Sci, Policy, and Management C138 and Plant and Microbial Biology C114.
    </course>
    <course name="Molecular Biology of Animal Viruses" number="115" units="2">
        Structure, reproduction, mutations, and host cell interactions (including pathogenesis) of animal viruses. This upper division and graduate course will broadly survey the strategies that viruses use to propagate in eukaryote cells, with an emphasis on vertebrate systems and disease-causing viruses. We will also discuss host mechanisms of defense against viruses. Graduate students should additionally enroll in 215. 115/215 are taught concurrently.
    </course>
    <course name="Microbial Diversity" number="C116" units="3">
        This course for upper-division and graduate students will broadly survey myriad types of microbial organisms, both procaryote and eucaryote, using a phylogenetic framework to organize the concept of &quot;biodiversity.&quot; Emphasis will be on the evolutionary development of the many biochemical themes, how they mold our biosphere, and the organisms that affect the global biochemistry. Molecular mechanisms that occur in different lineages will be compared and contrasted to illustrate fundamental biological strategies. Graduate students additionally should enroll in C216, Microbial Diversity Workshop. Also listed as Plant and Microbial Biology C116.
    </course>
    <course name="Cell Biology" number="130" units="4">
        An introductory survey of cell and developmental biology. The assembly of supramolecular structures; membrane structure and function; the cell surface; cytoplasmic membranes; the cytoskeleton and cell motility; the eukaryotic genome, chromatin, and gene expression; the cell cycle; organelle biogenesis, differentiation, and morphogenesis.
    </course>
    <course name="Cell and Developmental Biology Laboratory" number="130L" units="4">
        Experimental analyses of central problems in cell biology using modern techniques, including biochemical analysis of DNA and proteins, fluorescence microscopy of the cytoskeleton and organelles, DNA transfection of cultured mammalian cells, analysis of organelle functions, reporter assays of signal transduction pathways, and analysis of cell cycle progression and apoptosis.
    </course>
    <course name="Biology of Human Cancer" number="132" units="4">
        The course is designed for students interested in learning about the molecular and cell biology of cancer and how this knowledge is being applied to the prevention, diagnosis and therapy of cancer. Topics covered include tumor pathology and epidemiology; tumor viruses and oncogenes; intracellular signaling; tumor suppressors; multi-step carcinogenesis and tumor progression; genetic instability in cancer; tumor-host interactions; invasion and metastasis; tumor immunology; cancer therapy.
    </course>
    <course name="Chromosome Biology/Cytogenetics" number="C134" units="3">
        Survey of behavior, structure, and function of chromosomes with emphasis on behavior in model organisms. Topics include mitosis, meiosis, chromosome aberrations, genome function, dosage compensation, transposons, repetitive DNA, and modern cytological imaging. Also listed as Plant and Microbial Biology C134.
    </course>
    <course name="Molecular Endocrinology" number="135A" units="3">
        Molecular mechanisms by which hormones elicit specific responses and regulate gene expression; hormone-receptor interaction; synthesis, transport and targeting of hormones, growth factors and receptors.
    </course>
    <course name="Physiology of Human Development" number="135E" units="3">
        The developing human body from prenatal life to maturity; fertilization, embryology and fetal physiology, birth and neonatal adjustment, functional maturation in infant, child and adolescent; neuroendocrine control of puberty; factors influencing growth and development.
    </course>
    <course name="Physiology of the Aging Process" number="135K" units="3">
        The aging human body; structural and functional changes at organismic, cellular sub-cellular and molecular levels. Comparative epidemiological and environmental aspects. Theories of aging modification and life extension.
    </course>
    <course name="Physiology" number="136" units="4">
        Principles of mammalian (primarily human) physiology emphasizing physical, chemical, molecular and cellular bases of functional biology. The following topics will be covered: cellular and membrane ion and nonelectrolyte transport; cell and endocrine regulation; autonomic nervous system regulation; skeletal, smooth and cardiac muscle; cardiovascular physiology; respiration; renal physiology; gastrointestinal physiology. Discussion section led by Graduate Student Instructor will review material covered in lecture.
    </course>
    <course name="Computer Simulation in Biology" number="137" units="3">
        Modeling and computer simulation of dynamic biological processes using special graphical interfaces requiring very little mathematical or computer experience. Models are drawn from the current literature to teach concepts and technique. The later part of the course is a workshop for student-selected individual projects. Computer work may be done at home or in the university laboratory.
    </course>
    <course name="General Genetics" number="140" units="4">
        In-depth introduction to genetics, including mechanisms of inheritance; gene transmission and recombination; transposable DNA elements; gene structure, function, and regulation; and developmental genetics. Some exams may be given in the evening.
    </course>
    <course name="Genetics Laboratory" number="140L" units="4">
        Experimental techniques in classical and molecular genetics.
    </course>
    <course name="Developmental Biology" number="141" units="3">
        An introduction to principles and processes of embryonic and post-embryonic development, stressing mechanisms of cell and tissue interactions, morphogenesis and regulation of gene expression.
    </course>
    <course name="Survey of General Genetics" number="C142" units="4">
        A survey of genetics with primary emphasis upon mechanisms of heredity and molecular genetics. Includes some treatment of evolutionary genetics. Also listed as Integrative Biology C163.
    </course>
    <course name="Genomics" number="C145" units="4">
        In-depth introduction to genomics, including genome sequencing; bioinformatics; sequence annotation and analysis; complex trait mapping; DNA microarrays and their uses; proteomics; structural genomics. Also listed as Plant and Microbial Biology C145.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Computational Biology and Genomics" number="C146" units="4">
        Instruction and discussion of topics in genomics and computational biology. Working from evolutionary concepts, the course will cover principles and application of molecular sequence comparison, genome sequencing and functional annotation, and phylogenetic analysis. Also listed as Bioengineering C146 and Plant and Microbial Biology C146.
    </course>
    <course name="Microbial Genomics and Genetics" number="C148" units="4">
        Course emphasizes bacterial and archaeal genetics and comparative genomics. Genetics and genomic methods used to dissect metabolic and development processes in bacteria, archaea, and selected microbial eukaryotes. Genetic mechanisms integrated with genomic information to address integration and diversity of microbial processes. Introduction to the use of computational tools for a comparative analysis of microbial genomes and determining relationships among bacteria, archaea, and microbial eukaryotes. Also listed as Plant and Microbial Biology C148.
    </course>
    <course name="Molecular Immunology" number="150" units="4">
        Fundamentals of immunology with emphasis on biochemical and molecular approaches to study of the immune system and its application in medicine and biotechnology. Topics covered include description of the immune system, antibody and T-cell receptor structure and function, genes of the immunoglobulin superfamily, cells and molecular mediators that regulate the immune response, allergy, autoimmunity, immunodeficiency, tissue and organ transplants, and tumor immunology.
    </course>
    <course name="Immunology Laboratory" number="150L" units="4">
        Experimental techniques in mammalian molecular biology and cellular immunology. Molecular techniques covered include PCR and recombinant DNA procedures such as gene cloning, gene transfer, DNA sequencing, Southern blot, and restriction mapping. Immunological techniques covered include cell culture and monoclonal antibody production, flow cytometry, ELISA, immunoprecipitation, and western blot.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Neurobiology" number="C160" units="4">
        An introductory course designed to provide a general understanding of the nervous system including how it functions, how it develops, and how it changes with learning and memory. Analysis from the level of molecules to cells to simple circuits to complex networks to higher brain functions. Also listed as Neuroscience C160.
    </course>
    <course name="Neurobiology Laboratory" number="160L" units="4">
        Experimental analyses of properties and interactions of nerve cells and systems, illustrating principal features and current methods. Techniques employed include computer simulation of neuron properties, electrophysiological recording and stimulation of nerves and cells, digitally enhanced video imaging of outgrowth, fluorescence immunocytochemistry, analysis of sensory: CNS mapping, human-evoked potential recording, sensory psychophysics.
    </course>
    <course name="Mammalian Neuroanatomy" number="163" units="4">
        Development, structure (gross and microscopic), and functional relationships of the mammalian nervous system.
    </course>
    <course name="Molecular Neurobiology" number="165" units="3">
        The molecular and biochemical aspects of the structure and function of the nervous system, including ion channels, neurotransmitters and their receptors, second messenger systems, and molecular mechanisms of development and plasticity.
    </course>
    <course name="Biophysical Neurobiology" number="166" units="3">
        Biophysical properties of ion channels and excitability, ion selectivity, membrane transport phenomena. Sensory transduction, optical measurements and microscopy. Cellular networks as computational devices, information processing and transfer.
    </course>
    <course name="Undergraduate Teaching of Biology 1A" number="180" units="1,2">
        Course consists of a weekly three-hour training session that focuses on laboratory techniques, instructional aids, and problem solving, plus an additional three hour weekly laboratory where the UGSI is required to assist a GSI in the instruction of laboratory (answering questions, providing demonstrations, etc.).
    </course>
    <course name="Honors Research" number="H196A" units="1-4">
        Individual research and thesis preparation under the supervision of a faculty member. Acceptance to the Molecular and Cell Biology Honors Program is required. Contact the MCB Undergraduate Affairs Office, 2083 Valley Life Sciences Building, for application and details.
    </course>
    <course name="Honors Research" number="H196B" units="1-4">
        Individual research and completion of thesis under the supervision of a faculty member. This course satisfies the thesis requirement for the Molecular and Cell Biology Department Honors Program. Contact the MCB Undergraduate Affairs Office, 2083 Valley Life Sciences Building, for program details and an application.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study" number="198" units="1-4">
        Lectures and small group discussions focusing on topics of interest, varying from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study and Research" number="199" units="1-4">
        Enrollment restrictions apply; see the Introduction to Courses and Curricula section of this catalog.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Biochemistry and Molecular Biology" number="200" units="4">
        General course for first-year graduate students. Recent advances in the study of structural, functional, and genetic characteristics of prokaryotic and eukaryotic cells and their viruses, macromolecular syntheses, regulation of gene expression, chromosome organization, cell signaling, proliferation, and differentiation. Admission to the course requires formal consent of the instructors, except for MCB graduate students and graduate students in the laboratories of MCB faculty. Enrollment is restricted to 45. Auditors are not permitted in the discussion sessions.
    </course>
    <course name="Physical Biochemistry" number="206" units="3">
        Application of modern physical concepts and experimental methods to the analysis of the structure, function, and interaction of large molecules of biological interest.
    </course>
    <course name="Dietary Determinants of Cancer, Heart Disease, and Aging" number="C209" units="3">
        The influence of diet on DNA damage, cancer, and aging will be discussed with an emphasis on micronutrient deficiencies as a major contributor to DNA damage, cancer, and aging. The influence of diet on atherosclerotic heart disease will be covered with an emphasis on the role of dietary constituents proposed to have either toxic or preventive effects in the artery wall. Readings will consist of papers from the literature. Also listed as Nutritional Sciences and Toxicology C210.
    </course>
    <course name="Foundations of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology" number="210X" units="1">
        General course for first-year graduate students (except those in MCB laboratories). Prokaryotic and eukaryotic molecular biology; biological macromolecules; DNA replication, recombination, and repair; chromosome organization and mechanics; transcription, gene regulation; protein synthesis, intracellular protein trafficking; molecular basis of cellular ultrastructure; hormone action, signal transduction mechanisms, cell cycle control; modern methods.
    </course>
    <course name="An Introduction to Structural Biology and Physical Biochemistry" number="211" units="4">
        This course is for Molecular and Cell Biology graduate students. It will teach principles of protein and nucleic acid structure and outline basic experimental methods for conformation studies. The classical problems of structural biology, as well as new approaches and methods, will be emphasized. Courses 111 and 211 are taught concurrently. Students enrolled in 211 will also be required to attend a weekly discussion section and to prepare a mini-grant proposal.
    </course>
    <course name="Chemical Biology I - Structure, Synthesis and Function of Biomolecules" number="C212A" units="1">
        This course will present the structure of proteins, nucleic acids, and oligosaccharides from the perspective of organic chemistry. Modern methods for the synthesis and purification of these molecules will also be presented. Also listed as Chemistry C271A.
    </course>
    <course name="Chemical Biology II - Enzyme Reaction Mechanisms" number="C212B" units="1">
        This course will focus on the principles of enzyme catalysis. The course will begin with an introduction of the general concepts of enzyme catalysis which will be followed by detailed examples that will examine the chemistry behind the reactions and the three-dimensional structures that carry out the transformations. Also listed as Chemistry C271B.
    </course>
    <course name="Chemical Biology III - Contemporary Topics in Chemical Biology" number="C212C" units="1">
        This course will build on the principles discussed in Chemical Biology I and II. The focus will consist of case studies where rigorous chemical approaches have been brought to bear on biological questions. Potential subject areas will include signal transduction, photosynthesis, immunology, virology, and cancer. For each topic, the appropriate bioanalytical techniques will be emphasized. Also listed as Chemistry C271C.
    </course>
    <course name="Protein Chemistry, Enzymology, and Bio-organic Chemistry" number="C214" units="2">
        The topics covered will be chosen from the following: protein structure; protein-protein interactions; enzyme kinetics and mechanism; enzyme design. Intended for graduate students in chemistry, biochemistry, and molecular and cell biology. Also listed as Chemistry C230.
    </course>
    <course name="Molecular Biology of Animal Viruses Workshop" number="215" units="1">
        This workshop for graduate students will parallel 115 which should be taken concurrently. Emphasis in the workshop will be on the review of a current research topic as presented in the recent professional literature. A formulation of a seminar and/or paper relevant to this topic will be required.
    </course>
    <course name="Microbial Diversity Workshop" number="C216" units="1">
        This workshop for graduate students will parallel C116, Microbial Diversity, which should be taken concurrently. Emphasis in the workshop will be on review of research literature and formulation of paper pertinent to research in microbial diversity. Also listed as Plant and Microbial Biology C216.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in Biochemistry and Molecular Biology" number="217A" units="1">
        Recent advances. Topics changed each year. 217A, 217B, 217C are three sections of five weeks each. The sections are taught in tandem and may be taken individually.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in Biochemistry and Molecular Biology" number="217B" units="1">
        Recent advances. Topics changed each year. 217A, 217B, 217C are three sections of five weeks each. The sections are taught in tandem and may be taken individually.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in Biochemistry and Molecular Biology" number="217C" units="1">
        Recent advances. Topics changed each year. 217A, 217B, 217C are three sections of five weeks each. The sections are taught in tandem and may be taken individually.
    </course>
    <course name="Bacterial Viruses" number="218A" units="2">
        Initiation of DNA replication, the regulation of transcription at the initiation and termination stages, DNA packaging, interference between viruses, molecular cloning, and the heat shock response.
    </course>
    <course name="Viruses as Models for Eukaryote Gene Expression and Replication" number="218E" units="2">
        Recent developments in eukaryote viral and cellular regulation. New concepts in transcription and RNA replication, with particular emphasis on virus-cell interactions.
    </course>
    <course name="Myxobacterial Development" number="218G" units="2">
        Review of current literature and discussion of original research.
    </course>
    <course name="Protein Synthesis in Bacteria and Mammals" number="218H" units="2">
        The mechanism of protein synthesis in bacteria and human cells. Specific areas of interest include the structure and function of the ribosome and the regulation of protein synthesis.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced 20th Century Perspectives on Cancer Cell Genetics" number="218J" units="2">
        Transduction of cellular sequences and genetic regulation of transformation by oncogenic retroviruses as models for natural carcinogenesis, including a critical review of the current research.
    </course>
    <course name="Channel-Forming Membrane Proteins" number="218K" units="2">
        Structure, functional properties, and assembly of proteins that form nonspecific and specific passive diffusion channels, as well as active transport apparatus, in bacterial membranes.
    </course>
    <course name="Chemical Biology and Enzymology" number="218M" units="2">
        Topics at the interface of chemistry and biology with a particular focus on mechanisms of enzyme catalysis.
    </course>
    <course name="Eukaryotic Transcriptional Control" number="218N" units="2">
        Nucleic acid and protein components involved in regulating gene expression from eukaryotic chromosomes.
    </course>
    <course name="The Protein Folding Problem" number="218R" units="2">
        Protein structure, stability, design, and the pathway of protein folding.
    </course>
    <course name="Cryo-Electron Microscopy of Macromolecules" number="218S" units="2">
        Structure-function studies of the cytoskeleton and large molecular machines by cryo-electron microscopy and image reconstruction.
    </course>
    <course name="Post-transcriptional Control in Saccharomyces Cerevisiae" number="218T" units="2">
        Poly (A) tail recognition by translation and degradation enzymes in the yeast cell.
    </course>
    <course name="Protein Folding and Stability" number="218U" units="2">
        The connection between the sequence of a protein and its three-dimensional structure.
    </course>
    <course name="Biophysics of Macromolecule Transport Across Membranes" number="218V" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Enzyme Catalysis" number="218W" units="2">
        Fundamental aspects of enzyme catalysis, as probed by kinetic, spectroscopic, and molecular biological approaches.
    </course>
    <course name="DNA Enzymology" number="219D" units="2">
        Enzymology of DNA repair, replication, restriction, recombination, and methylation.
    </course>
    <course name="Eukaryotic Gene Expression" number="219F" units="2">
        Protein-DNA interactions and the control of gene expression in eukaryotes.
    </course>
    <course name="Molecular and Cell Biology of Listeria monocytogenes Pathogenesis" number="219H" units="2">
        Discussion of recent research on the genetics, cell biology, and immunology of the model facultative intracellular bacterical pathogen, Listeria monocytogenes.
    </course>
    <course name="Structure and Function of RNA" number="219J" units="2">
        RNA structure, folding, and function. Specific topics include ribozyme mechanisms, RNA-mediated translation initiation, and protein targeting and secretion.
    </course>
    <course name="Structural Biology of Molecular Machines" number="219Q" units="2">
        Crystallographic and biochemical studies of protein machines, focused on protein-nucleic acid interactions; analysis of chemomechanical function within multiprotein complexes will be covered in research reports and reviews of the current literature and in discussion of current experiments in the field.
    </course>
    <course name="Structural Biology of Signaling and Replication" number="219S" units="2">
        Mechanisms and structure in DNA replication and eukaryotic cell signaling.
    </course>
    <course name="Signal Transduction Mechanisms" number="219T" units="2">
        Discussion of recent research on various aspects of signal transduction mechanisms in eukaryotic cells, including G protein-coupled receptors, protein kinase cascades, synthesis and mobilization of lipid mediators, calcium sensing and response pathways, activation and inhibition of gene expression, and the biochemical basis of signal desensitization and physiological adaptation, with strong emphasis on genetic and molecular analysis of these systems, especially in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae.
    </course>
    <course name="Single Molecule Biophysics" number="219U" units="2">
        Methods of single molecule manipulation and visualization that are used to characterize the structure and mechanochemical properties of translocating DNA binding protein such as RNA polymerase and to investigate the mechanical denaturation of single protein molecules will be covered in research reports and reviews of the current literature and in discussion of current experiments in the field.
    </course>
    <course name="Biochemistry of Autophagy" number="219V" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Cell Surface Glycoconjugate Interactions" number="219X" units="2">
        Investigations of cell surface glycoproteins as mediators of cell-cell interactions. Development of new methods for engineering cell surface structures.
    </course>
    <course name="Regulation of HIV Gene Expression" number="219Y" units="2">
        Regulation of HIV gene expression by viral proteins and cellular cofactors will be covered in research reports and reviews of the current literature and in discussion of current experiments in the field.
    </course>
    <course name="Telomere Synthesis and Dynamics" number="219Z" units="2">
        Emphasizes a study of the replication of eukaryotic telomeric DNA. Special focus on techniques in protein biochemistry and molecular biology.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Cell Biology" number="230" units="4">
        Advanced treatment of topics in cell biology.
    </course>
    <course name="Foundations in Cell Biology" number="230X" units="1">
        General course for first-year graduate students (except those in molecular and cell biology laboratories). The assembly of supramolecular structures; membrane structure and function; the cell surface; cytoplasmic membranes; the cytoskeleton and cell motility; the eukaryotic genome, chromatin, and gene expression; the cell cycle; organelle biogenesis differentiation; and morphogenesis.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Stem Cell and Developmental Biology" number="231" units="4">
        Principles of animal development will be set forth from the classical and recent experimental analysis of induction, localization, patterning mutants, axis formation, regional gene expression, and cell interactions. Early development of selected vertebrates and invertebrates will be described. Basic experimental methods and new approaches will be presented. A weekly discussion section with readings from the research literature is required. Students will prepare a mini grant proposal.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Mammalian Physiology" number="236" units="5">
        Principles of mammalian (primarily human) physiology emphasizing physical, chemical, molecular, and cellular bases of functional biology. The following topics will be covered: cellular and membrane ion and nonelectrolyte transport; cell and endocrine regulation; autonomic nervous system regulation; skeletal, smooth, and cardiac muscle; cardiovascular physiology; respiration; renal physiology; gastrointestinal physiology. Discussion section will study advanced physiological topics, including: presentations by the faculty; problem sets; discussion of the primary literature and of reviews; two presentations by each student on topics in current physiological research.
    </course>
    <course name="Stem Cells and Directed Organogenesis" number="C237" units="3">
        This course will provide an overview of basic and applied embryonic stem cell (ESC) biology. Topics will include early embryonic development, ESC laboratory methods, biomaterials for directed differentiation and other stem cell manipulations, and clinical uses of stem cells. Also listed as Bioengineering C218.
    </course>
    <course name="Current Ethical, Legal, and Social Issues in Stem Cell Research" number="237SC" units="1">
        The course will cover key topics in the ethical, social, and legal aspects of stem cell research and medicine, including informed consent, egg and tissue donation, access to medical care, intellectual property, governmental and institutional regulations, and international perspectives on stem cell research. Required for CIRM scholars. Molecular and Cell Biology graduate students and trainees cannot substitute this course for 293C.
    </course>
    <course name="Regulation of the Cell Cycle" number="239B" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Vertebrate Development" number="239C" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Epithelial Function, Structure, and Regulations" number="239D" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Tumor Biology" number="239E" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Cell Morphogenesis" number="239EE" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Nucleocytoplasmic Transport" number="239F" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Signal Transduction and Tumor Suppressor Genes" number="239FF" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Photoreceptor Motility and Morphogenesis" number="239G" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="239GG" units="2">
        Mouse neuronal stem cell differentiation.
    </course>
    <course name="Cell Division" number="239H" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Mechanisms of Control of Growth and Cell Proliferation" number="239HH" units="2">
        Identifying pathways that restrict growth and cell proliferation in vivo.
    </course>
    <course name="Cytoskeleton and Cell Motility" number="239I" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Steroid Hormone and Growth Factor Action" number="239J" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Secretion and Cell Membrane Assembly" number="239K" units="2">
        Cell surface growth with emphasis on the unicellular eukaryote S. cerevisiae.
    </course>
    <course name="Assembly and Subcellular Organization of Bacterial Organelles" number="239KK" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="MicroRNA Functions in Cancer Development, Mouse Tumor Models" number="239M" units="2">
        Malignant transformation represents the endpoint of successive genetic lesions that confer uncontrolled proliferation and survival, unlimited replicative potential, and invasive growth.
    </course>
    <course name="Biophysics of Cell Motility and Morphogenesis" number="239N" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Cancer Biology" number="239O" units="2">
        Inheritance, chromatin structure, gene expression, and the organization of chromosomes in the nucleus.
    </course>
    <course name="Development and Aging" number="239P" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Regulation of Cell Polarity in Drosophila" number="239Q" units="2">
        Mechanisms underlying the establishment and maintenance of cellular organization in epithelia and other cell types.
    </course>
    <course name="Cellular Transport Processes" number="239S" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="The Cytoskeleton and Morphogenesis" number="239U" units="2">
        Review of current literature and discussion of current research.
    </course>
    <course name="Molecular Mechanisms of Transduction in Touch and Pain Receptors" number="239V" units="2">
        Review of current literature and discussion of current research. Current research focuses on elucidating the molecular mechanisms of somatosensory mechanotransduction.
    </course>
    <course name="Leech Embryology and Development" number="239W" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Malignant Transformation" number="239X" units="2">
        Malignant transformation by retroviruses and the role of protein phosphorylation in growth regulation.
    </course>
    <course name="Determination and Differentiation in Development" number="239Y" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Chromosome Remodeling and Reorganization During Meiosis" number="239Z" units="2">
        How chromosomes are reorganized during melosis to accomplish the pairing, recombinatin, and segregation leading up to successful gamete production.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Genetic Analysis" number="240" units="4">
        Principles and practice of classical and modern genetic analysis as applied to eukaryotic organisms, including yeast, nematodes, Drosophila, mice and humans; isolation and analysis of mutations; gene mapping; suppressor analysis; chromosome structure; control of gene expression; and developmental genetics.
    </course>
    <course name="General Genetics Workshop" number="241" units="4">
        This course is for Molecular and Cell Biology graduate students. It will teach in-depth introduction to genetics, including mechanisms of inheritance; gene transmission and recombination; transposable DNA elements; gene structure, function, and regulation; and developmental genetics. Some exams may be given in the evening. Courses 140 and 241 are taught concurrently. Students enrolled in 241 will also be required to participate in a one-hour specialized discussion section per week, led by the course instructor. This section will cover methodological background and will be based on the primary literature of the field.
    </course>
    <course name="Mechanisms of Developmental Evolution" number="C245" units="3">
        Synthesis of modern research on the molecular genetics of developmental evolution. Topics include the origin of animals, the evolution of body plan, the role of transcriptional regulation in morphological evolution, and genome evolution. Also listed as Integrative Biology C266.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Computational Biology and Genomics" number="C246" units="4">
        Instruction and discussion of topics in genomics and computational biology. Working from evolutionary concepts, the course will cover principles and application of molecular sequence comparison, genome sequencing and functional annotation, and phylogenetic analysis. Also listed as Bioengineering C246 and Plant and Microbial Biology C246.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Genetics, Genomics, and Development" number="248" units="4">
        Three five-week sections covering the principles and practice of i) modern genetic analysis as applied to eukaryotic organisms, ii) animal developmental biology, and iii) genome sequence analysis. The course will focus on the essential concepts and intellectual underpinnings of these areas, with a particular emphasis on their intersection.
    </course>
    <course name="Genetics of Regulatory Variation" number="249A" units="2">
        Work in my group will focus on transcriptional regulatory networks and their variation between members of a species.
    </course>
    <course name="Metazoan Sex Determination" number="249B" units="2">
        Molecular and genetic aspects of Metazoan sex determination, with emphasis on Drosophila melanogaster.
    </course>
    <course name="Nucleic Acid-Protein Interactions and Control of Gene Expression" number="249C" units="2">
        Biochemical and molecular genetic aspects of eukaryotic messenger RNA splicing and transposition, with an emphasis on Drosophila melanogaster as an experimental system.
    </course>
    <course name="Mechanisms of Genetic Regulation in Yeast" number="249D" units="2">
        Genes, gene products and molecular mechanisms that control cell types in the unicellular eukaryote Saccharomyces cerevisiae.
    </course>
    <course name="Molecular Genetics of Drosophila" number="249E" units="2">
        Gene regulation and developmental neurobiology.
    </course>
    <course name="Neuronal Development" number="249F" units="2">
        Molecular and genetic approaches to the problem of how neurons develop, with emphasis on Drosophila melanogaster and Caenorhabditis elegans.
    </course>
    <course name="Gene Expression in Drosophila" number="249H" units="2">
        Presentation and discussion of current research on gene regulation in Drosophila and other eukaryotes.
    </course>
    <course name="Developmental and Molecular Genetics of C. elegans" number="249J" units="2">
        Molecular and genetical analysis of sex determination and dosage compensation in the nematode C. elegans.
    </course>
    <course name="Animal Origins" number="249K" units="2">
        Evaluation of current research in human genetics, especially problems in human gene mapping. Intended to complement ongoing research for graduate students.
    </course>
    <course name="Saccharomyces Cerevisiae Microtubule Cytoskeleton" number="249M" units="2">
        Review of current literature and discussion of current research.
    </course>
    <course name="Gene Regulation" number="249N" units="2">
        Current literature and research in gene regulation will be covered in research reports and reviews of the current literature and in discussion of current experiments in the field.
    </course>
    <course name="Genome Sequences" number="249O" units="2">
        Biochemistry, cancer biology and virology, cell biology, computational biology, genetics, microbiology, molecular and cell physiology.
    </course>
    <course name="Mesodermal Patterning and Segmentation" number="249P" units="2">
        Genetic, molecular, and embryological aspects of mesodermal patterning and segmentation, with emphasis on the vertebrate, zebrafish.
    </course>
    <course name="Computational Genomics" number="249Q" units="2">
        Recent developments in computational methods for genomics and their application for understanding the structure and function of genes encoded in completely sequenced genomes.
    </course>
    <course name="Evolution of Development Mechanisms" number="249S" units="2">
        Evolution of development mechanisms with a focus on the genes that regulate segmentation and regionalization of the body plan.
    </course>
    <course name="Theoretical Modeling of Complex Biological Systems; Bioinformatics" number="249T" units="2">
        Theoretical modeling of complex biological systems; bioinformatics in genetics and development.
    </course>
    <course name="Mechanisms of Gene Control in Vertebrate Animals" number="249Y" units="2">
        This course will focus on mechanisms of gene control in vertebrate animals, particularly in the area of vertebrate development. Amphibian egg formation, mesoderm induction, neural induction, and patterning of the nervous system at the molecular level. Control of transcription, post-transcriptional control of gene expression (including control of RNA turnover and RNA localization).
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Immunology" number="250" units="4">
        Molecular and cellular analysis of the immune response. Structure and function of antibodies and antibody genes including antibody-antigen reactions, principles of molecular recognition, recombination and regulation of antibody genes, and the immunoglobulin class switch; B cell differentiation, activation, and tolerance. Structure and function of T cell receptors and T cell receptor genes; antigen processing and presentation, and role of MHC molecules in guiding T cell recognition; T cell activation, development, positive selection, and tolerance. Analysis of T cells, natural killer cells, and tumor surveillance.
    </course>
    <course name="The Regulation of Immune System Development and Function" number="251" units="1">
        This is an advanced seminar course which will consider current research questions and experimental approaches in molecular and cellular immunology. Each registrant will present a 30-minute research talk describing the problems they are studying, the approach they are taking, their preliminary data, and technical problems. Other course participants (including basic immunology faculty) will provide criticism and suggestions.
    </course>
    <course name="Cancer and Immunology" number="254" units="2">
        Emphasis will be on the treatment or prevention of cancer based on rational approaches derived from recent advances in tumor immunology. The course will examine the application of basic research in immune regulation to more applied studies in animal models and clinical trials. Introductory lectures by instructor followed by student presentations of original literature and lectures by invited speakers engaged in translational and clinical research in tumor immunotherapy.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in Immunology" number="257" units="1-3">
        Course will present varied topics in immunology including recent literature or special subjects in greater detail. The extensive reading list will vary with topics.
    </course>
    <course name="Specificity of T lymphocytes" number="259B" units="2">
        Molecular basis of antigen recognition function of T lymphocytes.
    </course>
    <course name="Regulation of T Cell Receptor Genes Expression" number="259E" units="2">
        Molecular biology of T cell receptor genes and their transcription controlling proteins/genes. Programmed cell death during thymocyte differentiation.
    </course>
    <course name="Antigen Receptor Repertoire of T Lymphocytes" number="259F" units="2">
        Molecular and biological basis for development of antigen/MHC repertoire.
    </course>
    <course name="T Cell Development" number="259G" units="2">
        Molecular and cellular aspects of thymocyte differentiation.
    </course>
    <course name="B Cell Differentiation" number="259H" units="2">
        Molecular basis of terminal B cell differentiation. Role of transcription factors in B cell activation.
    </course>
    <course name="Regulation of Lymphocyte Development" number="259I" units="2">
        Molecular mechanisms involved in the synergistic relationship between V(D)J recombination and lymphocyte development/function.
    </course>
    <course name="Immune Evasion by Viruses" number="259J" units="2">
        The mechanisms used by viruses to counteract the pressure of the immune system.
    </course>
    <course name="Innate Immunity and Innate Control of Adaptive Immunity" number="259M" units="2">
        Innate immunity and innate control of adaptive immunity.
    </course>
    <course name="Immunology, Microbiology, and Genetics of Bacterial Pathogenesis" number="259N" units="2">
        Role of innate host responses in defense against intracellular bacterial pathogens.
    </course>
    <course name="Principles of Neuroscience" number="260" units="4">
        Comprehensive survey of current state of knowledge in molecular, cellular, developmental, integrative and behavioral aspects of neurobiology.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Cellular Neurobiology" number="C261" units="3">
        Physical-chemical basis of membrane potentials, electrotonus, action potential generation and propagation, synaptic transmission, sensory receptor function, and volume conductor potentials. Also listed as Neuroscience C261.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Systems Neuroscience" number="C262" units="3">
        Advanced coverage of current research problems in systems-level neuroscience, and experimental and computational techniques used for these studies. Also listed as Neuroscience C262.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Developmental Neurobiology" number="C263" units="3">
        Advanced level coverage of current research problems in the embryonic and post-embryonic development of invertebrate and vertebrate nervous systems. Also listed as Neuroscience C263.
    </course>
    <course name="Vision A: Quantitative, Perceptual, and Physiological Aspects" number="C264A" units="2">
        The course will present basic material on the retina and visual pathways, psychophysical measurements, visual sensitivity, color vision, and the estimation of disparity and motion. Introduction to front-end visual processing in mammalian visual system. Basic optics, anatomy and physiology of retina, lateral geniculate nucleus, and primary visual cortex. Psychophysics of color, light and dark adaptation, spatial contrast sensitivity, spatial resolution, spatiotemporal contrast sensitivity, motion and disparity measurement. Connections between psychophysics and physiology. Relevant modeling techniques such as linear systems, signal detection theory, and information theory will be introduced and applied. There will be an accompanying laboratory which the students can register for separately. Also listed as Computer Science C293A and Vision Science C290A.
    </course>
    <course name="Vision B: Quantitative, Perceptual, and Physiological Aspects" number="C264B" units="2">
        The course will present basic material on inferring 3d from visual information. This will include disparity, motion, texture, shading, and occlusion. Introduction to the psychophysics and mathematical analysis underlying the inference of 3d scene properties from 2d retinal images. Psychophysics of various cues to 3d shape and spatial layout such as texture, contour, shading, stereopsis, and structure from motion. Geometrical analysis of these cues. Probabilitic theory for optimal combination of cues and estimation of scene properties. Relevant physiology of V1, V2, V4, and higher areas. Also listed as Computer Science C293B and Vision Science C290B.
    </course>
    <course name="Vision C: Perceptual Organization" number="C264C" units="2">
        This course will cover &quot;mid-level&quot; visual processing, including the perception of objects, their properties, and the determination of part-whole structure from optical images. The approach will be interdisciplinary, including material from psychophysics, classical perceptual psychology, computational modeling, and neuroscience. Specific topics include perception of color, grouping, figure-ground organization, modal and amodal completion, and part-whole structure. Also listed as Vision Science C290C, Psychology C215C, and Computer Science C293C.
    </course>
    <course name="Vision D: High-Level Vision" number="C264D" units="2">
        This course will cover &quot;high-level&quot; visual processing, including object recognition, visual attention, visual memory, visual imagery, and visual awarness. The approach will be interdisciplinary, including material from psychophysics, classical perceptual psychology, computational modeling and neurosciences. Also listed as Vision Science C290D, Psychology C215D, and Computer Science C293D.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Neuroplasticity" number="269A" units="2">
        Molecular and cellular studies of nerve growth, axon guidance, synaptic formation, and synaptic plasticity using electrophysiological and optical imaging techniques.
    </course>
    <course name="Synaptic Transmission and Neuromodulation" number="269B" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Signaling Within and Between Neurons" number="269D" units="2">
        Review of recent research in molecular mechanisms involved in intracellular and extracellular signaling in the nervous system.
    </course>
    <course name="Auditory Neuroscience" number="269E" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Retinal Signal Processing" number="269F" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Neural Systems" number="269G" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Recent Advances in Retinal Neurobiology" number="269H" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Taste Recognition in Drosophila" number="269J" units="2">
        The molecular and cellular basis of taste perception in the model organism Drosophila melanogaster.
    </course>
    <course name="Protein Trafficking and Synapses Formation" number="269K" units="2">
        Molecular mechanisms of polarized protein trafficking and synaptogenesis in neurons.
    </course>
    <course name="Insect Neurophysiology" number="269M" units="2">
        Drosophila mutants that have behavioral abnormalities to unravel new and basic features of nervous system structure and function.
    </course>
    <course name="Sensory Processing and Plasticity in Cerebral Cortex" number="269Q" units="2">
        How the cerebral cortex processes sensory input and stores information about the sensory world. We focus on the rat's primary somatosensory (S1) cortex.
    </course>
    <course name="Potassium Channels and Synaptic Plasticity" number="269R" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Molecular Mechanisms of  Olfaction" number="269S" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Processing of Visual Information in the Mammalian Brain" number="269T" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="269U" units="2">
        Evaluation of current research in molecular mechanisms underlying diseases of the retina.
    </course>
    <course name="Neural Activity Affecting the Assembly of Neural Circuits" number="269W" units="2">
        How neural activity affects the assembly of neural circuits.
    </course>
    <course name="Tumor Biology Seminar" number="282" units="1">
        Reviews and reports of current research in tumor biology.
    </course>
    <course name="Graduate Seminar" number="290" units="1">
        Graduate student presentations on selected research topics in molecular and cell biology. Several sections covering different topics offered each semester. Concurrent enrollment in more than one section is permitted. List of topics to be announced before each semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Research" number="291A" units="2-12">
        Closely supervised experimental work under the direction of an individual faculty member; an introduction to experimental methods and research approaches in particular areas of molecular and cell biology.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Research" number="291B" units="2-12">
        Closely supervised experimental work under the direction of an individual faculty member; an introduction to experimental methods and research approaches in particular areas of molecular and cell biology.
    </course>
    <course name="Research" number="292" units="3-12">
        Individual research under the supervision of a faculty member.
    </course>
    <course name="Research Seminar" number="293A" units="2">
        Seminar on presentation and evaluation of results in area of student's individual research interests.
    </course>
    <course name="Research Seminar" number="293B" units="2">
        Seminar on presentation and evaluation of results in area of student's individual research interests.
    </course>
    <course name="Responsible Conduct of Research" number="293C" units="1">
        This course will cover topics in responsible conduct in research drawing from case studies of the Association of American Medical Colleges and the NIH. Students will review case studies in preparation for class discussion. Required of all MCB graduate and post doctoral students funded on NIH training grants. One session will probably feature a guest lecturer on a topic relevant to the course.
    </course>
    <course name="Careers for Life Sciences Ph.D's" number="295" units="1">
        This course is designed to assist graduate students in the biological sciences with planning their postgraduate careers. Weekly guest speakers will present their experiences on a variety of topics. Postdoctoral students are invited. Topics may include academia;: job searches; setting up a laboratory; patent law/technology transfer; public policy/regulatory affairs; bioinformatics; science writing/technical support; forensic science; postdoctoral positions in industry; teaching, and other topics of interest.
    </course>
    <course name="Methods and Logic in Biology" number="297" units="3">
        The focus of this course will be some of the papers in the scientific literature that provide the discoveries and methods critical to modern molecular and cell biology. Students will learn how to dissect published literature to evaluate precisely what constitutes an important paper. The themes for the methods and logics course will be broadly applicable to all students interested in modern experimental biology. Students will meet and discuss the themes of a series of papers first by themselves (with assistance of a faculty member) and then participate in an in-depth dissection lead by the staff.
    </course>
    <course name="Teaching of Molecular and Cell Biology" number="380" units="1-2">
        Teaching laboratories and/or discussions for Molecular and Cell Biology courses: analysis of specific format and problems. Two units of credit for those with 50% teaching appointment; one unit of credit for those with 25% teaching appointment.
    </course>
    <course name="Transmission Electron Microscopy" number="481B" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Scanning Electron Microscopy" number="481C" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Principles and Operation of the Light Microscope" number="481E" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study for Master's Students" number="601" units="1-8">
        Individual study for the comprehensive or language examinations in consultation with the field adviser.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study for Doctoral Students" number="602" units="1-8">
        Individual study in consultation with the major field adviser. Intended to provide an opportunity for qualified students to prepare themselves for the various examinations required of candidates for the Ph.D.
    </course>
</department>
