<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="AST" name="Applied Science And Technology">
    <course name="Soft X-rays and Extreme Ultraviolet Radiation" number="C210" units="3">
        This course will explore modern developments in the physics and applications of soft x-rays. It begins with a review of electromagnetic radiation at short wavelengths including dipole radiation, scattering and refractive index, using a semi-classical atomic model. Subject matter will include the generation of x-rays with laboratory tubes, synchrotron radiation, laser-plasma sources, x-ray lasers, and black body radiation. Concepts of spatial and temporal coherence will be discussed. Also listed as Electrical Engineering C213.
    </course>
    <course name="Thin-Film Science and Technology" number="C225" units="3">
        Thin-film nucleation and growth, microstructural evolution and reactions. Comparison of thin-film deposition techniques. Characterization techniques. Processing of thin films by ion implantation and rapid annealing. Processing-microstructure-property-performance relationships in the context of applications in information storage, ICs, micro-electromechanical systems and optoelectronics. Also listed as Materials Science and Engineering C225.
    </course>
    <course name="Partially Ionized Plasmas" number="C239" units="3">
        Introduction to partially ionized, chemically reactive plasmas, including collisional processes, diffusion, sources, sheaths, boundaries, and diagnostics. DC, RF, and microwave discharges. Applications to plasma-assisted materials processing and to plasma wall interactions. Also listed as Electrical Engineering C239.
    </course>
    <course name="Applied Spectroscopy" number="C295R" units="3">
        After a brief review of quantum mechanics and semi-classical theories for the interaction of radiation with matter, this course will survey the various spectroscopies associated with the electromagnetic spectrum, from gamma rays to radio waves. Special emphasis is placed on application to research problems in applied and engineering sciences. Graduate researchers interested in systematic in situ process characterization, analysis, or discovery are best served by this course. Also listed as Chemical Engineering C295R.
    </course>
    <course name="Group Studies, Lectures, or Seminars" number="298A" units="1-6">
        Advanced group studies, lectures, or seminars in subjects which are interdisciplinary in the various fields of engineering or other sciences associated with engneering problems. Topics which form the basis of seminars will be annnounced at the beginning of each semester. May be cross-listed with other engineering group studies, lectures, or seminars.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study or Research" number="299" units="1-12">
        Investigations of advanced problems in applied science and technology. Sponsored by Engineering Interdisciplinary Studies Center.
    </course>
</department>
