<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="ENGLISH" name="English">
    <course name="Reading and Composition" number="R1A" units="4">
        Training in writing expository prose.
    </course>
    <course name="Reading and Composition" number="R1B" units="4">
        Training in writing expository prose.
    </course>
    <course name="Shakespeare" number="17" units="4">
        Lectures on Shakespeare and reading of his best works.
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman Seminars" number="24" units="1">
        The Berkeley Seminar Program has been designed to provide new students with the opportunity to explore an intellectual topic with a faculty member in a small-seminar setting. Berkeley Seminars are offered in all campus departments, and topics vary from department to department and semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="English as a Language" number="25" units="4">
        An introduction to the grammar of English, including phonology (sound structure), morphology (word structure), syntax (sentence structure), semantics (linguistic meaning), and pragmatics (contextual meaning), with consideration of different varieties of English in use within the United States and throughout the world, and comparison of English with other languages.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to the Study of Poetry" number="26" units="4">
        Lectures and discussion on poetry intended to develop the student's ability to understand and evaluate a poem. Designed primarily for students whose major is not English, but majors and prospective majors are welcome.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature of American Cultures" number="31AC" units="4">
        An introduction to the ethnic diversity of American literature. The course will take substantial account of the literature of three or more of the following groups: African Americans, Native Americans, Asian Americans, Chicanos/Latinos, and European Americans. Topics vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; well before the beginning of the semester for details.
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman Seminar" number="39" units="4">
        Topics vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for current offerings well before the start of the semester. (Sections limited to 15 students each.)
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to the Writing of Short Fiction" number="43A" units="4">
        A workshop course intended for students who have recently begun to write fiction or who have not previously taken a course in creative writing.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to the Writing of Verse" number="43B" units="4">
        A workshop course intended for students who have recently begun to write verse or who have not previously taken a course in creative writing.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature in English" number="45A" units="4">
        Historical survey of literature in English from Chaucer through the 20th century.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature in English" number="45B" units="4">
        Historical survey of literature in English from Chaucer through the 20th century.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature in English" number="45C" units="4">
        Historical survey of literature in English from Chaucer through the 20th century.
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman and Sophomore Studies" number="R50" units="4">
        Writing-intensive introduction to the study of literature; fulfills the second half of Reading and Composition requirement. Highly recommended for prospective English majors who have not yet taken R1B. Topics and readings vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for current offerings well before the beginning of the semester. Sections limited to 17 students.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Environmental Studies" number="C77" units="4">
        This innovative course taught by a scientist and a humanities professor surveys current global environmental issues; introduces students to the basic intellectual tools of environmental science; investigates ways the human relationship to nature has been imagined in literary and philosophical traditions; and examines how tools of scientific and literary analysis, scientific method, and imaginative thinking can clarify what is at stake in environmental issues and environmental citizenship. Also listed as Undergrad Interdisciplinary Studies C12 and Environ Sci, Policy, and Management C12.
    </course>
    <course name="Children's Literature" number="80K" units="4">
        The study of selected works written for children.
    </course>
    <course name="Sophomore Seminar" number="84" units="1,2">
        Sophomore seminars are small interactive courses offered by faculty members in departments all across the campus. Sophomore seminars offer opportunity for close, regular intellectual contact between faculty members and students in the crucial second year. The topics vary from department to department and semester to semester. Enrollment limited to 15 sophomores.
    </course>
    <course name="Other Voices: Multicultural Literary Perspectives" number="95" units="2">
        This course will introduce students to the literary study currently being undertaken by English Department faculty interested in issues of race and class, gender and ethnicity, and the formations of minority discourse. Each week a scholar or writer will lecture on literary study that reflects cultural and racial concerns. Upper division English majors will lead discussion groups focusing upon the methods advocated in the lecture and on various readings. This course does not satisfy major requirements.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study for Freshmen and Sophomores" number="98" units="1-4">
        Group study in a field that may not coincide with that of any regular course and must be specific enough to enable students to write essays based upon their studies.
    </course>
    <course name="Independent Study" number="99" units="1-4">
        Meetings to be arranged. Reading and regular conference with the instructor in a field that shall not coincide with that of any regular course and shall be specific enough to enable students to write essays based on their studies.
    </course>
    <course name="Junior Seminar" number="100" units="4">
        Intensive study of critical and methodological problems in the study of literature. Normally fulfills one or more of the area of concentration requirements. Designed for English majors. Topics vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for offerings well before the beginning of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="The History of the English Language" number="101" units="4">
        The history of the English language from its Indo-European roots, through its Old, Middle, and Early Modern periods, as preserved in the literary heritage, to its different forms in use throughout the world today.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in the English Language" number="102" units="4">
        Topics vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Anglo-Saxon England" number="105" units="4">
        Instruction in the basic elements of the Old English language with analysis of literary and cultural issues relating to the formative period of the English nation. (Undergraduates who pass 105 with a grade of B+ or higher, or with permission of the 205B instructor, are eligible to enroll in 205B, Beowulf.)
    </course>
    <course name="The English Bible As Literature" number="C107" units="4">
        Introduction to the English Bible treated as a literary work. Also listed as Religious Studies C119.
    </course>
    <course name="Medieval Literature" number="110" units="4">
        Development of literary form and idiom throughout the Christian West from the first to the fifteenth century.
    </course>
    <course name="Chaucer" number="111" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of Chaucer's major works.
    </course>
    <course name="Middle English Literature" number="112" units="4">
        Middle English literature exclusive of Chaucer studied in the original language.
    </course>
    <course name="English Drama" number="114A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="English Drama" number="114B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="The English Renaissance" number="115A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="The English Renaissance" number="115B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Shakespeare" number="117A" units="4">
        A chronological survey of Shakespeare's career.
    </course>
    <course name="Shakespeare" number="117B" units="4">
        A chronological survey of Shakespeare's career.
    </course>
    <course name="Shakespeare" number="117J" units="4">
        Study of selected plays, with practice in various critical approaches, e.g., establishing text, relation to source, changing concepts of comedy and tragedy, influence of theatrical conditions on technique.
    </course>
    <course name="Shakespeare" number="117S" units="4">
        Lectures on Shakespeare and reading of his best works.
    </course>
    <course name="Shakespeare in the Theatre" number="117T" units="4">
        The interrelation of Elizabethan plays and stage practices. Classroom exercises, written assignments, and a final examination. The course will usually culminate in the performance of a play.
    </course>
    <course name="Milton" number="118" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of Milton's major works.
    </course>
    <course name="The Augustan Age" number="119" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of Dryden, Swift, Pope, and some of their contemporaries.
    </course>
    <course name="The Age of Johnson" number="120" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of later eighteenth-century British literature.
    </course>
    <course name="Romantic Period" number="121" units="4">
        Blake, Wordsworth, Coleridge, Byron, Shelley, Keats, and contemporaries.
    </course>
    <course name="Victorian Period" number="122" units="4">
        Literature of the Victorian period with an emphasis on poetry and nonfiction prose.
    </course>
    <course name="The English Novel" number="125A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="The English Novel" number="125B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="The European Novel" number="125C" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of major European novels.
    </course>
    <course name="The 20th-Century Novel" number="125D" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of major novels of the twentieth century.
    </course>
    <course name="The Contemporary Novel" number="125E" units="4">
        Important contemporary novels, some of which may be read in translation.
    </course>
    <course name="British Literature: 1900-1945" number="126" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of British literature written between 1900 and 1945.
    </course>
    <course name="Modern Poetry" number="127" units="4">
        British and American poetry: 1900 to the present.
    </course>
    <course name="American Literature: Before 1800" number="130A" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of the major writers of the early American period.
    </course>
    <course name="American Literature: 1800-1865" number="130B" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of the major texts of the American Renaissance.
    </course>
    <course name="American Literature:  1865-1900" number="130C" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of American literature from the Civil War through 1900.
    </course>
    <course name="American Literature: 1900-1945" number="130D" units="4">
        A survey of modern American literature.
    </course>
    <course name="American Poetry" number="131" units="4">
        A historical survey of American poetry and its backgrounds.
    </course>
    <course name="American Novel" number="132" units="4">
        A survey of major American novels.
    </course>
    <course name="African American Literature and Culture Before 1917" number="133A" units="4">
        Major literary and cultural texts in the African American tradition from origins through World War I.
    </course>
    <course name="African American Literature and Culture Since 1917" number="133B" units="4">
        Major literary and cultural texts in the African American tradition from the Harlem Renaissance through the twentieth century.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in African American Literature and Culture" number="133T" units="4">
        Topics vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for offerings well before the beginning of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Contemporary Literature" number="134" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of selected works written since the Second World War.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature of American Cultures" number="135AC" units="4">
        Study of the ethnic diversity of American literature. The course will take substantial account of the literature of three or more of the following groups: African Americans, Native Americans, Asian Americans, Chicanos/Latinos, and European Americans. Topics vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; well before the beginning of the semester for details.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in American Studies" number="C136" units="4">
        A course on the intellectual, cultural, historical, and social backgrounds to American literature. Topics will vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for current offerings well before the start of the semester. Also listed as American Studies C111E.
    </course>
    <course name="Chicana/o Literature and Culture to 1910" number="137A" units="4">
        Major literary and cultural texts in the Chicana/o tradition from origins through the Mexican Revolution of 1910.
    </course>
    <course name="Chicana/o Literature and Culture Since 1910" number="137B" units="4">
        Major literary and cultural texts in the Chicana/o tradition from 1910 through the contemporary Chicana/o period.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Chicana/o Literature and Culture" number="137T" units="4">
        Topics in Chicana/o literature and culture.
    </course>
    <course name="Studies in World Literature in English" number="138" units="4">
        An examination of various aspects of the modern literature written in English in Africa, the Caribbean, India, and Southeast Asia. Topics will vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for current offerings well before the start of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="The Cultures of English" number="139" units="4">
        Literatures of various regions in which English is one of the spoken languages, such as Canada, the Caribbean, Australia, Africa, India; and the writings of specific groups or distinctive cultures in the English-speaking world, including the U.S. and the British Isles. Topics vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for current offerings well before the start of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Modes of Writing (Exposition, Fiction, Verse, Etc.)" number="141" units="4">
        Writing in connection with reading in recent English literature and its continental background.
    </course>
    <course name="Short Fiction" number="143A" units="4">
        A seminar in writing short stories.
    </course>
    <course name="Verse" number="143B" units="4">
        A seminar in writing poetry.
    </course>
    <course name="Playwriting" number="143E" units="4">
        A seminar in playwriting.
    </course>
    <course name="Prose Nonfiction" number="143N" units="4">
        A seminar in the writing of prose nonfiction as an art.
    </course>
    <course name="Poetry Translation Workshop" number="143T" units="4">
        Open to those who wish to assimilate foreign influences for writing poetry or to seek a fuller understanding of any foreign poetry by rendering it into English.
    </course>
    <course name="Visual Autobiography" number="C143V" units="4">
        Since visual and literary studies have historically been viewed as separate disciplines, we will use theories from both to study those forms of self-representation that defy disciplinary boundaries, or what we call &quot;visual autobiography.&quot; The course aims to help students become conversant with the elements of alphabetic literacy (reading and writing) and visual literacy (observing and making) in order to develop a third distinctive textual/visual literacy. Also listed as Visual Studies C185A, Undergrad Interdisciplinary Studies C135, and American Studies C174.
    </course>
    <course name="Senior Seminar" number="150" units="4">
        Designed primarily for senior English majors. Intensive study of a special topic or critical problem in literary study. Topics vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for offerings well before the beginning of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Women Writers" number="152" units="4">
        Topics will vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Methods and Materials of Literary Criticism" number="160" units="4">
        An introduction to issues in literary criticism with emphasis on application of principles and methods to selected literary texts.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Literary Theory" number="161" units="4">
        This class will focus on literary theory.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics" number="165" units="4">
        Designed primarily for English majors. Topics vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for offerings well before the beginning of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in American Cultures" number="165AC" units="4">
        Designed primarily for English majors. Study of a special topic related to the diversity of the United States. Topics vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for offerings well before the beginning of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics" number="166" units="4">
        Topics vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for offerings well before the beginning of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in American Cultures" number="166AC" units="4">
        Study of a special topic related to the diversity of the United States. Topics vary from semester to semester. Student's should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for offerings well before the beginning of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature and the Arts" number="170" units="4">
        Studies in the relationship of literature in English to the arts.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature and Sexual Identity" number="171" units="4">
        Sexual identity in literature in relation to thematics, literary convention, psychology, and the particular politics and sociology of individual cultures. The course may range broadly over Western literature or concentrate on one historical period.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature and Psychology" number="172" units="4">
        Studies in the relationship of literature in English to psychology.
    </course>
    <course name="The Language and Literature of Films" number="173" units="4">
        Studies in film as a mode of representing reality; cinematic techniques and the &quot;language&quot; of film. Lectures, class discussions, and film viewings.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature and History" number="174" units="4">
        Topics will vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature and Disability" number="175" units="4">
        Studies of the relationships among literature, culture, and &quot;disability.&quot; The course may range broadly or concentrate on one historical period, genre, or issue.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature and Popular Culture" number="176" units="4">
        Topics will vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature and Philosophy" number="177" units="4">
        Studies in the relationship of literature in English to philosophy.
    </course>
    <course name="British and American Folklore" number="178" units="4">
        Study of representative forms of folklore and oral literature among the English-speaking people of the British Isles and North America.
    </course>
    <course name="Literature and Linguistics" number="179" units="4">
        Study of the English language as a medium for literature. Topics may include rhyme, alliteration, meter, poetic syntax, metaphor, irony, the language of point of view, narrative tense, orality, literacy, etc.
    </course>
    <course name="Autobiography" number="180A" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of autobiographical forms.
    </course>
    <course name="The Epic" number="180E" units="4">
        Reading and discussion of epics, considering their cultural and historical contexts, the nature of their composition, and the development of the form.
    </course>
    <course name="Short Story" number="180H" units="4">
        Lectures on and discussion of the form of the short story.
    </course>
    <course name="Lyric Verse" number="180L" units="4">
        Study of lyric forms and techniques.
    </course>
    <course name="The Novel" number="180N" units="4">
        Study of the novel as a literary genre, its formal development and variations, its technical possibilities, its cultural functions. Topics may vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="The Romance" number="180R" units="4">
        Study of the romance as a literary genre. Topics may vary from semester to semester; focus may be historical or restricted to a particular period (e.g., medieval, modern).
    </course>
    <course name="Honors Course" number="H195A" units="4">
        This is a two-semester course, graded IP at the end of the first semester. During the second semester, each student will write an honors thesis. Completion of the thesis is required for a passing grade in the course.
    </course>
    <course name="Honors Course" number="H195B" units="4">
        This is a two-semester course, graded IP at the end of the first semester. During the second semester, each student will write an honors thesis. Completion of the thesis is required for a passing grade in the course.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study" number="198" units="1-4">
        Enrollment is restricted by university regulations. Group study in a field that shall not coincide with that of any regular course and shall be specific enough to enable students to write essays based upon their studies.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study for Advanced Undergraduates" number="199" units="1-4">
        Meetings to be arranged. Enrollment is restricted by university regulations. Reading and conference with the instructor in a field that shall not coincide with that of any regular course and shall be specific enough to enable students to write essays based upon their studies.
    </course>
    <course name="Problems in the Study of Literature" number="200" units="4">
        Approaches to literary study, including textual analysis, scholarly methodology and bibliography, critical theory and practice.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in the Structure of the English Language" number="201A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="History of Literary Criticism" number="202" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Graduate Readings" number="203" units="4">
        Graduate lecture courses surveying broad areas and periods of literary history, and directing students in wide reading. Offerings vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for offerings well before the beginning of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Old English" number="205A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Chaucer" number="211" units="4">
        Discussion of Chaucer's major works.
    </course>
    <course name="Readings in Middle English" number="212" units="4">
        Rapid reading of selections in Middle English, from the twelfth century through the fifteenth.
    </course>
    <course name="Shakespeare" number="217" units="4">
        Discussion of selected works of Shakespeare.
    </course>
    <course name="Milton" number="218" units="4">
        Discussion of Milton's major works.
    </course>
    <course name="Fiction Writing Workshop" number="243A" units="4">
        A writing workshop in fiction for graduate students.
    </course>
    <course name="Poetry Writing Workshop" number="243B" units="4">
        A writing workshop in poetry for graduate students.
    </course>
    <course name="Renaissance: Sixteenth century (excluding, or at least not prominently featuring, Skakespeare)" number="246C" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Renaissance: Seventeenth century through Milton" number="246D" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Restoration and early 18th century" number="246E" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Later 18th century" number="246F" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Romantic" number="246G" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Victorian" number="246H" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="American to 1855" number="246I" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="American 1855 to 1900" number="246J" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Literature in English 1900 to 1945" number="246K" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Literature in English 1945 to Present" number="246L" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Research Seminars" number="250" units="4">
        Required of all Ph.D. students. Advanced study in various fields, leading to a substantial piece of writing. Offerings vary from semester to semester. Students should consult the department's &quot;Announcement of Classes&quot; for offerings well before the beginning of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Studies" number="298" units="4-12">
        Normally reserved for students directly engaged upon the doctoral dissertation.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Study" number="299" units="1-8">
        Primarily for students engaged in preliminary exploration of a restricted field, involving research and the writing of a report. May not be substituted for available seminars.
    </course>
    <course name="The Teaching of Composition and Literature" number="302" units="3">
        Discussion of course aims, instructional methods, grading standards, and special problems in the teaching of composition and literature, with practice in handling sample essays. When given for graduate student instructors in the English R1A-R1B Program or the English 45 series, the course will include class visitation.
    </course>
    <course name="Field Studies in Tutoring Writing" number="310" units="1-3">
        Tutoring Berkeley undergraduates in College Writing R1A, R1A, R1B, and other writing and/or literature courses. Seminar topics: the writing process, responding to writing, composition theory, grammar, collaborative learning, tutoring methods. Tutors keep a weekly journal, read assigned articles, videotape their tutoring, and write a final paper. This course cannot be used toward fulfillment of the major requirements.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study for Doctoral Students" number="602" units="1-12">
        Individual study in consultation with the major field adviser, intended to provide an opportunity for qualified students to prepare themselves for the various examinations required of candidates for the Ph.D. May not be used for unit or residence requirements for the doctoral degree.
    </course>
</department>
