<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="EPS" name="Earth And Planetary Science">
    <course name="Gems and Gem Materials" number="2" units="1-3">
        The primary goal of the course is to present some introductory earth science and to provide students with a solid understanding of gemology. The course covers (1) processes leading to the formation of gems in the Earth, (2) how gems are identified, (3) factors that affect the appearance and value of gems, (4) processes used to enhance the appearance of gems, (5) materials used to simulate common gemstones, and (6) issues associated with the synthesis of gems. Information about each of the main gems groups is provided. Additional credits require a term paper and practical (laboratory) work.
    </course>
    <course name="The Water Planet" number="3" units="2">
        An overview of the processes that control water supply to natural ecosystems and human civilization. Hydrologic cycle, floods, droughts, groundwater. Patterns of water use, threats to water quality, effects of global climate change on future water supplies. Water issues facing California.
    </course>
    <course name="Geologic Record of Climate Change" number="8" units="3">
        This course will review the geologic record of climate change emphasizing how such knowledge can constrain present day thinking about (and predictive models of) future climate change. We will cover the entire spectrum of climate variations, from the formation of the Earth's early atmosophere 4.6 billion years ago to the ice ages to the development of instrumental records.
    </course>
    <course name="The Planets" number="C12" units="3">
        A tour of the mysteries and inner workings of our solar system. What are planets made of? Why do they orbit the sun the way they do? How do planets form, and what are they made of? Why do some bizarre moons have oceans, volcanoes, and ice floes? What makes the Earth hospitable for life? Is the Earth a common type of planet or some cosmic quirk? This course will introduce basic physics, chemistry, and math to understand planets, moons, rings, comets, asteroids, atmospheres, and oceans. Understanding other worlds will help us save our own planet and help us understand our place in the universe. Also listed as Letters and Science C70T and Astronomy C12.
    </course>
    <course name="Earthquakes in Your Backyard" number="20" units="3">
        Introduction to earthquakes, their causes and effects. General discussion of basic principles and methods of seismology and geological tectonics, distribution of earthquakes in space and time, effects of earthquakes, and earthquake hazard and risk, with particular emphasis on the situation in California.
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman Seminar in Earth and Planetary Sciences" number="24" units="1">
        The freshman seminar in earth and planetary science is designed to provide new students with an opportunity to explore a topic in geology or earth sciences with a faculty member in a small seminar setting. Topics will vary from semester to semester but will include such possible topics as great voyages of geologic discovery and the role of atmospheric sciences in geologic study.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39A" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Geology of National Parks" number="49A" units="3">
        This course introduces students to geology through an exploration of our national parks. Students will learn about the major processes of the earth - ranging from volcanism, continental drift, and mountain building, to river erosion, glaciers, and groundwater movement - through an exploration of the natural beauty of the various parks. The course will also touch upon environmental issues and early American history, both prehistoric and historic.
    </course>
    <course name="Geology of National Parks" number="49B" units="1">
        This course is the field component of 49A. Enrollment is limited to 30 students.
    </course>
    <course name="The Planet Earth" number="50" units="4">
        An introduction to the physical and chemical processes that have shaped the earth through time, with emphasis on the theory of plate tectonics. Laboratory work will involve the practical study of minerals, rocks, and geologic maps and exercises on geological processes.
    </course>
    <course name="Big History -- Cosmos, Earth, Life, and Humanity" number="51" units="4">
        This course explores all four major regimes of history -- cosmic history, Earth history, life history, and human history. Bringing together these normally unrelated topics, it seeks to understand the character of history by examining longterm trends and critical chance events, by looking for common causes underlying historical change in all four regimes, and by identifying the novelities that have made each regime unique. It offers a broad perspective for students interested in any one of the historical disciplines, helping them cross the barriers between fields of historical study.
    </course>
    <course name="Big History -- Cosmos, Earth, Life, and Humanity" number="C51" units="4">
        This course explores all four major regimes of history -- cosmic history, Earth history, life history, and human history. Bringing together these normally unrelated topics, it seeks to understand the character of history by examining longterm trends and critical chance events, by looking for common causes underlying historical change in all four regimes, and by identifying the novelities that have made each regime unique. It offers a broad perspective for students interested in any one of the historical disciplines, helping them cross the barriers between fields of historical study. Also listed as Letters and Science C70X.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantitative Analysis of Earth Sciences" number="60" units="4">
        Introduction to quantitative description of geological processes. Topics include rate processes, description of three dimensional geological fields like gravity, temperature, velocity; conservation equations; deformation; plate kinematics; geological time series; multiple chemical equilibria.
    </course>
    <course name="Environmental Earth Sciences" number="80" units="2">
        The course describes geologic processes active on and in the earth and man's interactions with them. Geologic aspects of use of the land and oceans based on an understanding of earth's environmental processes.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Oceans" number="C82" units="2">
        The geology, physics, chemistry, and biology of the world oceans. The application of oceanographic sciences to human problems will be explored through special topics such as energy from the sea, marine pollution, food from the sea, and climate change. Also listed as Integrative Biology C82.
    </course>
    <course name="Sophomore Seminar" number="84" units="1,2">
        Sophomore seminars are small interactive courses offered by faculty members in departments all across the campus. Sophomore seminars offer opportunity for close, regular intellectual contact between faculty members and students in the crucial second year. The topics vary from department to department and semester to semester. Enrollment limited to 15 sophomores.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study" number="98" units="1-4">
        Group studies of selected topics which vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Communicating Ocean Science" number="C100" units="4">
        For undergraduates interested in improving their ability to communicate their scientific knowledge by teaching ocean science in elementary schools or science centers/aquariums. The course will combine instruction in inquiry-based teaching methods and learning pedagogy with six weeks of supervised teaching experience in a local school classroom or the Lawrence Hall of Science with a partner. Thus, students will practice communicating scientific knowledge and receive mentoring on how to improve their presentations. Also listed as Integrative Biology C100.
    </course>
    <course name="Minerals: Their Constitution and Origin" number="100A" units="4">
        Introduction to structural, compositional, and physical properties of minerals, their analogs and related substances, their genesis in various geological and synthetic processes, and laboratory techniques to identify and investigate minerals. One field trip to selected mineral deposits and visits to laboratories.
    </course>
    <course name="Genesis and Interpretation of Rocks" number="100B" units="4">
        Introduction to the principal geologic environments where rocks are formed and displayed. Igneous, sedimentary, and metamorphic processes discussed in the context of global tectonics.
    </course>
    <course name="Field Geology and Digital Mapping" number="101" units="4">
        Geological mapping, field observation, and problem-solving in the Berkeley hills and environs leading to original interpretation of geological processes and history from stratigraphic, structural, and lithological investigations. Integration of the Berkeley hills geology into the Coast Ranges and California as a whole through field trips to key localities. Training in digital field mapping, global positioning systems, and laser surveying. Interdisciplinary focus encourages participation by nonmajors.
    </course>
    <course name="History and Evolution of Planet Earth" number="102" units="4">
        Formation and evolution of the earth. Nucleosynthesis; formation of the solar system; planetary accretion; dating the earth and solar system; formation of the core, mantle, oceans, and atmosphere; plate tectonics; heat transfer and internal dynamics; stratigraphic record of environment, and evolution; climate history and climate change.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Marine Geochemistry" number="103" units="3">
        Introduction to marine geochemistry: the global water cycle; major processes governing the distribution of chemical species within the hydrosphere; mass balances, fluxes, and reactions in the marine environment from global to submicron scales; relationships to physical, biological, and geological processes; geochemical tracers and tools.
    </course>
    <course name="Mathematical Methods in Geophysics" number="104" units="4">
        Linear systems. Linear inverse problems, least squares; generalized inverse, resolution; Fourier series, integral transforms; time series analysis, spherical harmonics; partial differntial equations of geophysics; functions of a complex variable; probability and significance tests, maximum likelihood methods. Intended for students in geophysics and other physical sciences.
    </course>
    <course name="Hydrogeology" number="105" units="3">
        An overview of the principles governing fluid flow in the earth's crust, interaction of geological processes and fluid flow, transport of energy and solutes, migration of hydrocarbons and contaminants, and waste isolation.
    </course>
    <course name="Geodynamics" number="108" units="4">
        Basic principles in studying the physical properties of earth materials and the dynamic processes of the earth. Examples are drawn from tectonics, mechanics of earthquakes, etc., to augment course material.
    </course>
    <course name="Computer Simulations in Earth and Planetary Sciences" number="109" units="3">
        Introduction to modern computer simulation methods and their application to selected Earth and Planetary Science problems. In hands-on computer laboratories, students will learn about numerical algorithms, modify provided programs, and display the solution graphically on their laptops. This is an introductory course and no programming experience is required. Examples include fractals in geophysics, properties of materials at high pressure, celestial mechanics, and diffusion processes in the Earth. Topics range from ordinary and partial differential equations to molecular dynamics and Monte Carlo simulations.
    </course>
    <course name="Stratigraphy and Earth History" number="115" units="4">
        Collecting, analyzing, and presenting stratigraphic data; dating and correlating sedimentary rocks; recognizing ancient environments and reconstructing Earth history; seismic and sequence stratigraphy; event stratigraphy and neocatastrophism; applications of stratigraphy to climate change, petroleum geology, and archaeology.
    </course>
    <course name="Structural Geology and Tectonics" number="116" units="3">
        Introduction to the geometry and mechanics of brittle and ductile geologic structures; their origins and genetic relation to stress fields and their use as kinematic indicators; case histories of selected regions to elucidate tectonic evolution in different plate tectonic settings. Laboratory exercises will focus on analysis of hand specimens and structural relations portrayed on geologic maps. Several trips to observe geologic structures in the field to supplement laboratory exercises.
    </course>
    <course name="Geomorphology" number="117" units="4">
        Quantitative examination of landforms, runoff generation, weathering, mechanics of soil erosion by water and wind, mass wasting, glacial and periglacial processes and hillslope evolution.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Field Course" number="118" units="4">
        Advanced geological mapping, intensive field observation, and problem solving in the field areas selected by instructors. Includes preparation of final reports.
    </course>
    <course name="Geologic Field Studies" number="119" units="2">
        Two to four weekend field trips to localities of geological interest.
    </course>
    <course name="Analysis of Environmental Data" number="C120" units="4">
        Fundamentals of exploratory data analysis and hypothesis testing for environmental scientists, with emphasis on characterizing and evaluating uncertainty. Introduction to selected topics relevant to environmental analysis, including error propagation, design of experiments, and Monte Carlo methods. Microcomputer laboratories, using real environmental data, explore concepts and techniques presented in lecture. Also listed as Energy and Resources Group C130.
    </course>
    <course name="Seismology" number="121" units="4">
        Elastic waves in the earth; forward and inverse problems for the velocity distribution; refraction and reflection methods of seismic exploration. Theory of the seismograph; interpretation of seismograms; causes, effects, and distribution of earthquakes; mechanics of earthquakes; earthquake hazard and risk.
    </course>
    <course name="Physics of the Earth and Planetary Interiors" number="122" units="3">
        Gravity field, density distribution, and internal structure of the Earth and planets. Constitution, composition, temperature distribution, and energetics of the Earth's interior. The geomagnetic field, paleomagnetism, the geodynamo, and concepts in geophysical fluid dynamics.
    </course>
    <course name="Isotopic Geochemistry" number="124" units="4">
        An overview of the use of natural isotopic variations to study earth, planetary, and environmental problems. Topics include geochronology, cosmogenic isotope studies of surficial processes, radiocarbon and the carbon cycle, water isotopes in the water cycle, and radiogenic and stable isotope studies of planetary evolution, mantle dynamics, volcanoes, groundwater, and geothermal systems. The course begins with a short introduction to nuclear processes and includes simple mathematical models used in isotope geochemistry.
    </course>
    <course name="Biometeorology" number="C129" units="3">
        This course describes how the physical environment (light, wind, temperature, humidity) of plants and soil affects the physiological status of plants and how plants affect their physical environment. Using experimental data and theory, it examines physical, biological, and chemical processes affecting transfer of momentum, energy, and material (water, CO2, atmospheric trace gases) between vegetation and the atmosphere. Plant biometeorology instrumentation and measurements are also discussed. Also listed as Environ Sci, Policy, and Management C129.
    </course>
    <course name="Strong Motion Seismology" number="130" units="3">
        Generation of seismic waves. Synthetic accelerograms. Instrumentation to measure strong ground motion. Estimation of seismic motion at a site. Ground motion spectra. Influence of soils and geologic structures. Seismic risk mapping.
    </course>
    <course name="Geochemistry" number="131" units="4">
        Chemical reactions in geological processes. Thermodynamic methods for predicting chemical equilibria in nature. Isotopic and chemical tracers of transport processes in the earth. Chemistry of the solid earth, oceans, and atmosphere.
    </course>
    <course name="Paleoclimatology" number="C141" units="4">
        Earth's climatic changes have been substantial throughout geologic history, and these changes constitute fascinating natural experiments that reveal much about the earth's climate systems and their capacity for change. In this course we will review important methods for past climate reconstruction and also current knowledge of past climate changes throughout earth's history, with an emphasis on those of the Quaternary. Methods to be explored include analyses of physical, geochemical, and paleontologic characteristics of marine sediments, coral reefs, coastal sediments, lake sediments, tree rings, and ice cores. Also listed as Geography C141.
    </course>
    <course name="Geological Oceanography" number="C146" units="4">
        The tectonics and morphology of the sea floor, the geologic processes in the deep and shelf seas, and the climatic record contained in deep-sea sediments. The course will cover sources and composition of marine sediments, sea-level change, ocean circulation, paleoenvironmental reconstruction using fossils, imprint of climatic zonation on marine sediments, marine stratigraphy, and ocean floor resources. Also listed as Geography C145.
    </course>
    <course name="The Origin and Evolution of the Solar System" number="C149" units="3">
        The story of the solar system. Topics include the solar nebula and modern observations of disks, the formation of the planets, planetary interiors and surfaces, planetary atmospheres and magnetospheres, and smaller bodies in the solar system. The physical processes at work are developed in some detail, and an evolutionary picture of each object is expounded. Some discussion of other (potential) planetary systems is also included.
    </course>
    <course name="Case Studies in Earth Systems" number="150" units="2">
        Analysis and discussion of three research problems on the interactions of solid earth, hydrologic, chemical, and atmospheric processes. Emphasis is on the synthesis and application of the student's disciplinary knowledge to a new integrative problem in the earth sciences.
    </course>
    <course name="Planetary Astrophysics" number="C162" units="4">
        Physics of planetary systems, both solar and extra-solar. Star and planet formation, radioactive dating, small-body dynamics and interaction of radiation with matter, tides, planetary interiors, atmospheres, and magnetospheres. High-quality oral presentations will be required in addition to problem sets. Also listed as Astronomy C162.
    </course>
    <course name="Crossroads of Earth Resources and Society" number="170AC" units="4">
        Intersection of geological processes with American cultures in the past, present, and future. Overview of ethnogeology including traditional knowledge of sources and uses of earth materials and their cultural influences today. Scientific approach to study of tectonic controls on the genesis and global distribution of energy fuels, metals, and industrial minerals. Evolution and diversity of opinion in attitudes about resource development, environmental management, and conservation on public, private, and tribal lands. Impending crisis in renewable energy and the imperative of resource literacy. Also listed as Letters and Science 170AC.
    </course>
    <course name="Geoarchaeological Science" number="C171" units="4">
        This survey and laboratory course will cover a broad range of current scientific techniques used in the field and in the analysis of geoarchaeological materials. The course includes field and laboratory studies in analytical chemistry, geology, petrology/petography and a survey of dating materials in archaeology, the historical development of geoarchaeological science and other aspects of archaeological science applied to geoarchaeological materials. Also listed as Anthropology C131.
    </course>
    <course name="Applied Geophysics" number="C178" units="3">
        The theory and practice of geophysical methods for determining the subsurface distribution of physical rock and soil properties. Measurements of gravity and magnetic fields, electrical and electromagnetic fields, and seismic velocity are interpreted to map the subsurface distribution of density, magnetic susceptibility, electrical conductivity, and mechanical properties. Also listed as Civil and Environmental Engineering C178.
    </course>
    <course name="Air Pollution" number="C180" units="3">
        An introduction to air pollution and the chemistry of earth's atmosphere. The fundamental natural processes controlling trace gas concentrations in the atmosphere, and how anthropogenic activity has affected those processes at the local, regional, and global scales. Specific topics include stratospheric ozone depletion, increasing concentrations of greenhouse gases, smog, and changes in the oxidation capacity of the troposphere. Also listed as Environ Sci, Policy, and Management C180.
    </course>
    <course name="Atmospheric Physics and Dynamics" number="181" units="3">
        This course examines the processes that determine the structure and circulation of the Earth's atmosphere. The approach is deductive rather than descriptive: to figure out the properties and behavior of the Earth's atmosphere based on the laws of physics and fluid dynamics. Topics will include interaction between radiation and atmospheric composition; the role of water in the energy and radiation balance; governing equations for atmospheric motion, mass conservation, and thermodynamic energy balance; geostrophic flow, quasigeostrophic motion, baroclinic instability and dynamics of extratropical cyclones.
    </course>
    <course name="Atmospheric Physics and Dynamics" number="C181" units="3">
        This course examines the processes that determine the structure and circulation of the Earth's atmosphere. The approach is deductive rather than descriptive: to figure out the properties and behavior of the Earth's atmosphere based on the laws of physics and fluid dynamics. Topics will include interaction between radiation and atmospheric composition; the role of water in the energy and radiation balance; governing equations for atmospheric motion, mass conservation, and thermodynamic energy balance; geostrophic flow, quasigeostrophic motion, baroclinic instability and dynamics of extratropical cyclones. Also listed as Geography C139.
    </course>
    <course name="Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics Laboratory" number="C182" units="3">
        Fluid dynamics, radiative transfer, and the kinetics, spectroscopy, and measurement of atmospherically relevant species are explored through laboratory experiments, numerical simulations, and field observations. The course is intended for Earth and Planetary Science majors and minors, and for chemistry, physics, astronomy, biology, and engineering majors whose interests may lie in science applied to the atmosphere of Earth and other planets. Also listed as Chemistry C182.
    </course>
    <course name="Marine Geobiology" number="185" units="2">
        Interrelationships between marine organisms and physical, chemical and geological processes in oceans.
    </course>
    <course name="Senior Honors Course" number="H195" units="3">
        Original research and preparation of an acceptable thesis. May be taken during two consecutive semesters of senior year and may be substituted for six units of the upper division requirement with consent of major adviser.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study" number="198" units="1-4">
        Group studies of selected topics which vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study and Research" number="199" units="1-4">
        Enrollment is restricted by regulations.
    </course>
    <course name="Problems in Hydrogeology" number="200" units="4">
        Current problems in fluid flow, heat flow, and solute transport in the earth. Pressure- and thermal-driven flow, instability, convection, interaction between fluid flow and chemical reactions. Pore pressure; faulting and earthquakes; diagenesis; hydrocarbon migration and trapping; flow-associated mineralization; contaminant problems.
    </course>
    <course name="Thermodynamic Analysis of Chemical Reactions in Natural Processes" number="202" units="3">
        Application of chemical thermodynamics and solution chemistry to prediction and interpretation of the consequences of both reversible and irreversible reactions in inorganic and organic processes.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Marine Geochemistry" number="203" units="3">
        The global water cycle; major processes governing the distribution of chemical species within the hydrosphere; mass balances, fluxes, and reactions in the marine environment from global to submicron scales; relationships to physical, biological, and geological processes; geochemical tracers and tools.
    </course>
    <course name="Elastic Wave Propagation" number="204" units="3">
        Wave propagation in elastic solids; effects of anelasticity and anistropy; representation theorems; reflection and refraction; propagation in layered media; finite-difference and finite-element methods.
    </course>
    <course name="Laboratory in Observational Seismology" number="207" units="3">
        Group problem solving of current seismological topics. Analysis, inversion, and numerical modeling of seismic waveform data to investigate questions regarding the physics of the earthquake source and seismic wave propagation. Application of current developments and techniques in seismological research.
    </course>
    <course name="Mineral Thermodynamics" number="209" units="3">
        Physical basis of the thermodynamic properties of minerals, including the use of elastic constants, spectroscopic, and related data. The emphasis is on high-temperature phenomena, including the nature of melting. Thermal defects and non-equilibrium processes, particularly diffusion and the theory of phase transformations, are also discussed.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Stratigraphy and Tectonics" number="212" units="3">
        Evolution of the earth in response to internal, surficial and extraterrestrial processes.
    </course>
    <course name="Field Geology and Digital Mapping" number="213" units="4">
        Geological mapping, field observation, and problem solving in the Berkeley hills and environs leading to original interpretation of geological processes and history from stratigraphic, structural, and lithological investigations. Integration of the Berkeley hills geology into the coast ranges and California as a whole through systematic field mapping in key localities. Training in digital field mapping and use of global positioning systems. Interdisciplinary focus encourages participation by non-majors.
    </course>
    <course name="Active Tectonics" number="216" units="3">
        This course is a graduate course designed to introduce students in the earth sciences to the geology of earthquakes, including tectonic geomorphology, paleoseismology and the analysis and interpretation of geodetic measurements of active deformation. While the focus will be primarily on seismically active faults, we will also discuss deformation associated with landslides, regional isostatic rebound, and volcanoes, as well as measurements of global plate motions. We will address methods and applications in paleoseismology, tectonic geomorphology, and geodesy. The course will address measurement techniques (e.g,. GPS, leveling, etc.), data analysis and inversion, and subsequent modeling and interpretation of the data. The integration of geodetic measurements with geologic and seismologic data allows an improved understanding of active processes.
    </course>
    <course name="Fluvial Geomorphology" number="217" units="4">
        Application of fluid mechanics to sediment transport and development of river morphology. Form and process in river meanders, the pool-riffle sequence, aggradation, grade, and baselevel.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Concepts in Mineral Physics" number="220" units="3">
        A combined seminar and lecture course covering advanced topics related to mineral physics. The interface between geophysics with the other physical sciences is emphasized. Topics vary each semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Isotopic Geochemistry" number="224" units="4">
        An overview of the use of natural isotopic variations to study earth, planetary, and environmental problems. Topics include geochronology, cosmogenic isotope studies of surficial processes, radiocarbon and the carbon cycle, water isotopes in the water cycle, and radiogenic and stable isotope studies of planetary evolution, mantle dynamics, volcanoes, groundwater, and geothermal systems. The course begins with a short introduction to nuclear processes and includes simple mathematical models used in isotope geochemistry.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in High-Pressure Research" number="225" units="2">
        Analysis of current developments and techniques in experimental and theoretical high-pressure research, with applications in the physical sciences. Topics vary each semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Characterization of Minerals and Rocks" number="235" units="3">
        Introduction to the main methods of characterization such as x-ray diffraction, x-ray fluorescence, electron microprobe, and electron microscopy. Interpretation of data in a geologic context. Advanced undergraduates are encouraged to attend.
    </course>
    <course name="Geological Fluid Mechanics" number="236" units="4">
        An advanced course in the application of fluid mechanics in the earth sciences, with emphasis on the design and scaling of laboratory and numerical models. Principals of inviscid and viscous fluid flow; dynamic similarity; boundary layers; convection; instabilities; gravity currents; mixing and chaos; porous flow. Applications to mantle convection, magma dynamics, atmosphere and ocean dynamics, sediment/debris flows, and hydrogeology. Topics may vary from year to year.
    </course>
    <course name="Isotope Biogeochemistry" number="C241" units="5">
        Use of isotopes in present and past terrestrial and aquatic research. Lectures cover the principles of isotope distribution on Earth (first 10 weeks). The second part of the course focuses on student presentations of case studies and research proposals. In the laboratory, students prepare samples of choice for isotopic analyses. Also listed as Environ Sci, Policy, and Management C220 and Integrative Biology C227.
    </course>
    <course name="Glaciology" number="C242" units="4">
        A review of the mechanics of glacial systems, including formation of ice masses, glacial flow mechanisms, subglacial hydrology, temperature and heat transport, global flow, and response of ice sheets and glaciers. We will use this knowledge to examine glaciers as geomorphologic agents and as participants in climate change. Also listed as Geography C241.
    </course>
    <course name="Geological Oceanography" number="C246" units="4">
        The tectonics and morphology of the sea floor, the geologic processes in the deep and shelf seas, and the climatic record contained in deep-sea sediments. The course will cover sources and composition of marine sediments, sea level change, ocean sediments, marine stratigraphy, and ocean floor resources. Also listed as Geography C247.
    </course>
    <course name="Solar System Astrophysics" number="C249" units="3">
        The physical foundations of planetary sciences. Topics include planetary interiors and surfaces, planetary atmospheres and magnetospheres, and smaller bodies in our solar system. The physical processes at work are developed in some detail, and an evolutionary picture for our solar system, and each class of objects, is developed. Some discussion of other (potential) planetary systems is also included. Also listed as Astronomy C249.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Earth and Environmental Sciences" number="250" units="3">
        Review of recent literature and discussion of ongoing research at the interface between earth science and environmental science.
    </course>
    <course name="Carbon Cycle Dynamics" number="251" units="3">
        In this course, we will focus on the (unsolved) puzzle of the contemporary carbon cycle. Why is the concentration of atmospheric CO2 changing at the rate observed? What are the terrestrial and oceanic processes that add and remove carbon from the atmosphere? What are the processes responsible for long-term storage of carbon on land and in the sea? Emphasis will be placed on the observations and modeling needed to evaluate hypotheses about carbon sources and sinks. Past records will be examined for clues about sensitivity of carbon processes to climate variations.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Seismology and Geophysics" number="254" units="1">
        Lectures on various topics representing current advances in seismology and geophysics, including local crustal and earthquake studies, regional tectonics, structure of the earth's mantle, and core and global dynamics.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Earth and Planetary Science" number="255" units="1">
        Lectures on various topics representing current advances in all aspects of earth and planetary science.
    </course>
    <course name="Earthquake of the Week" number="256" units="2">
        Each week, the seismicity of the previous week, in California and worldwide, is reviewed. Tectonics of the region as well as source parameters and waveforms of interest are discussed and placed in the context of ongoing research in seismology.
    </course>
    <course name="Research in Earth Science" number="260" units="2">
        Weekly presentations to introduce new graduate students and senior undergraduates to current research conducted in the Department of Earth and Planetary Science.
    </course>
    <course name="Field Geology and Digital Mapping" number="271" units="4">
        Geological mapping, field observation, and problem solving in the Berkeley hills and environs leading to original interpretation of geological processes and history from stratigraphic, structural, and lithological investigations. Integration of the Berkeley hills geology into the tectonic and paleo-climatic record of the Coast Ranges and California as a whole through systematic field mapping in key localities and reading of original literature. Training in digital field mapping, use of digital base maps, and use of global positioning systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Research" number="280" units="2-12">
        Individual conferences to be arranged. Provides supervision in the preparation of an original research paper or dissertation.
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290" units="2-6">
        Topics will be announced each semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study for Graduates" number="298" units="1-9">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Professional Preparation: Supervised Teaching of Geology and Geophysics" number="300" units="1-6">
        Discussion, curriculum, class observation, and practice teaching in geology, geophysics, and earth science.
    </course>
    <course name="Communicating Ocean Science" number="C301" units="4">
        For graduate students interested in improving their ability to communicate their scientific knowledge by teaching ocean science in elementary schools or science centers/aquariums. The course will combine instruction in inquiry-based teaching methods and learning pedagogy with six weeks of supervised teaching experience in a local school classroom or the Lawrence Hall of Science with a partner. Thus, students will practice communicating scientific knowledge and receive mentoring on how to improve their presentations. Also listed as Integrative Biology C215.
    </course>
</department>
