<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="POL SCI" name="Political Science">
    <course name="Introduction to American Politics" number="1" units="4">
        An introductory analysis of the structure and operations of the American political system, primarily at the national level.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to American Politics" number="1AC" units="4">
        Politics is the art and noise of collective governance under conditions of scarce resources, conflicting interests, diverse beliefs, uncertain outcomes, and unequal power. In 1AC, we learn about the institutions, ideologies, and processes that constitute politics in the U.S. In fulfilling the AC requirement, we further examine how power, equality, and diversity are configured and contested in our politics. The course emphasizes active research- and group-based learning.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Comparative Politics" number="2" units="4">
        This course deals with the basic problems and processes that all political systems face and examines their particular expression in Western, Communist, and Third World settings.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Empirical Analysis and Quantitative Methods" number="3" units="4">
        Analytical and methodological problems of political inquiry, with an emphasis on quantification and measurement.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Political Theory" number="4" units="4">
        An approach to the understanding of politics through the perspectives and language of the political theorist.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to International Relations" number="5" units="4">
        This course is designed to introduce students to the major theoretical approaches to international politics, to explore important historical and contemporary questions and debates in international affairs, and to teach students to think critically about international relations. It is a prerequisite for most upper division international relations courses in Political Science.
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman Seminars" number="24" units="1">
        The Berkeley Seminar Program has been designed to provide new students with the opportunity to explore an intellectual topic with a faculty member in a small-seminar setting. Berkeley Seminars are offered in all campus departments, and topics vary from department to department and semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39A" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39B" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39C" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39D" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39E" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39F" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39G" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39H" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39I" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39J" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39K" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39L" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39M" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39N" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39O" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39P" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39Q" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39R" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39S" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39T" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39U" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39V" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39W" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39X" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39Y" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39Z" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman Seminar" number="41" units="4">
        Topics, experimental in nature, will vary from year to year.
    </course>
    <course name="What Is Political Freedom?" number="60AC" units="4">
        Explores meanings and conundrums of political freedom. What is freedom, how does it relate to other political values (equality, security, community, cultural preservation), how is it won and lost? Canonical political thinkers (Socrates, Machiavelli, Rousseau, Marx, Mill, Arendt, Fanon, Foucault) are read along with novels, legal cases, and material on contemporary controversies. Issues include free speech and hate speech, capitalism, freedom and empire, violent and nonviolent emancipation, rights and identity, racial profiling.
    </course>
    <course name="Sophomore Seminar" number="84" units="1,2">
        Sophomore seminars are small interactive courses offered by faculty members in departments all across the campus. Sophomore seminars offer opportunity for close, regular intellectual contact between faculty members and students in the crucial second year. The topics vary from department to department and semester to semester. Enrollment limited to 15 sophomores.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study for Lower Division Students" number="98" units="1-3">
        Lectures and small group discussion focusing on topics of interest that vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study" number="99" units="1-4">
        Supervised Independent Study and Research for lower division students, pursuant to the Regulations of the Berkeley Division, Section A230.
    </course>
    <course name="The American Executive" number="102" units="4">
        Analysis of principal institutions, functions, and problems of the Presidency and the federal executive branch. Special attention will be given to topics of presidential leadership, staffing, executive-legislative relations, and policy formation. Comparative reference to executive processes in other political systems.
    </course>
    <course name="The American Executive" number="102W" units="3">
        Analysis of principal institutions, functions, and problems of the presidency and the federal executive branch. Special attention will be given to topics of presidential leadership, staffing, executive-legislative relations, and policy formation.
    </course>
    <course name="Congress" number="103" units="4">
        Nomination and election, constituent relations, the formal and informal structures of both houses, relations with the executive branch, policy formation, and lobbying.
    </course>
    <course name="Congress" number="103W" units="3">
        Nomination and election, constituent relations, the formal and informal structures of both houses, relations with the executive branch, policy formation, and lobbying. Sessions with Washington experts on Congress. Observation of congressional hearings and debates.
    </course>
    <course name="Political Parties" number="104" units="4">
        The institutional environment within which American politics takes place. Concept and history of parties in the American context: their nature and function, origin and development. Party organization and structure. State, national, and local party systems and their variations. Nominations and elections. One directed research paper will be required.
    </course>
    <course name="Political Parties" number="104W" units="3">
        The institutional environment within which American politics takes place. Concept and history of parties in the American context: their nature and function, origin and development, party organization and structure.
    </course>
    <course name="The Politician" number="105" units="4">
        The nature of politics, the education of politicians, the structure of ambition, and the ethical values of social behavior in the political world. Sessions with elected officials and party workers on their vocation. Directed field research.
    </course>
    <course name="The Politician" number="105W" units="3">
        The nature of politics, the education of politicians, the structure of ambition, and the ethical values of social behavior in the political world. Sessions with elected officials and party workers on their vocation.
    </course>
    <course name="American Politics: Campaign Strategy - Media" number="106A" units="4">
        An inside look at how political campaigns operate from the viewpoint of the media, taught by the people who run them. Class material will be directed towards students who are interested in direct involvement in campaign politics or who are looking for a greater understanding of the political process. Students will be required to develop a complete written campaign strategy document in order to fulfill class requirements. Students will be expected to follow political and campaign news via the media and be prepared to discuss those developments in class.
    </course>
    <course name="American Politics: Campaign Strategy - Management" number="106B" units="4">
        An inside look at how political campaigns operate from the viewpoint of campaign management, taught by the people who run them. Class material will be directed toward students who are interested in direct involvement in campaign politics or who are looking for a greater understanding of the political process. Students will be required to develop a complete written campaign strategy document in order to fulfill class requirements. Students will be expected to follow political and campaign news via the media and be prepared to discuss those developments in class.
    </course>
    <course name="Politics, Ethics, and Leadership" number="108A" units="4">
        Those who decide to participate in politics must inevitably make ethical choices. Too often, the moral bases of political decisions are unexamined. This course looks at the political choices of leaders and citizens as they relate to honesty and public rhetoric, corruption and public trust, influence and the appropriate exercise of power, fairness in process and policy outcome, political obligations and duties, and the nature of political calculation. The materials of this course will be drawn from case studies of political choices, relevant legal cases, comparative politics, guest speakers with political experience, and ethical theory.
    </course>
    <course name="Politics, Ethics, and Leadership" number="108AW" units="4">
        Those who decide to participate in politics must inevitably make ethical choices. Too often, the moral bases of political decisions are unexamined. This course looks at the political choices of leaders and citizens as they relate to honesty and public rhetoric, corruption and public trust, influence and the appropriate exercise of power, fairness in process and policy outcome, political obligations and duties, and the nature of political calculation. The materials of this course will be drawn from case studies of political choices, relevant legal cases, comparative politics, guest speakers with political experience, and ethical theory.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109C" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109D" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109E" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109F" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109G" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109H" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109I" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109J" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109K" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109L" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109M" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109N" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109O" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109P" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109Q" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109R" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109S" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109T" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109U" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109V" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in American Politics-UCDC" number="109W" units="3">
        Topics will vary.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109X" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109Y" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="109Z" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Cal-in-the-Capitol" number="110" units="2">
        The course is designed to provide prospective interns with the opportunity to gain an understanding of some important issues facing our national government and an appreciation of the way these issues are dealt with in Washington, D.C. The course simulates the internship experience by giving class members the opportunity to work with Berkeley experts who will make demands of the students' research skills.
    </course>
    <course name="Cal-in-Sacramento" number="110B" units="2">
        The purpose of this course is to provide Cal-in-Sacramento interns and other interested UC Berkeley students with a rudimentary understanding of our state government. We will focus on the state legislature and executive branch, exploring both the policy-making process and the politics in Sacramento, which we will learn are quite closely related to one another.
    </course>
    <course name="Politics and the News Media" number="111A" units="4">
        This course's objective is to describe and analyze the ways in which the news media have become a part of the political system. In order to understand the manner in which news organizations interact with officials, organized groups, and the public focus will be on media influences in areas such as who gets to make policy and the outcome of policy making.
    </course>
    <course name="The Politics of Displacement" number="111AC" units="4">
        Antebellum American political history generally follows a routine script in which the purpose of the Revolution was to liberate Americans for self-government and economic and social development. Slavery is viewed as an anomaly still needing explanation, and Native American relocation as the consequence of natural forces of immigration and pre-modern social values. In this class, the revolution against traditional political authority embodied in Jefferson's and Thomas Paine's attack on the British crown, the rise of slavery, and the conflict with Native America are seen as coherent parts of a cultural and social development that emerges in the 18th- and 19th-century America. Using both original antebellum materials, including biographies, history, and literature, and contemporary images from American popular culture such as film, news and magazine articles, and music, we will compare and contrast the experiences of antebellum Native Americans, Euopean imiiigrants, and African slaves as a connection between the past and the present emerges.
    </course>
    <course name="Politics and the News Media" number="111W" units="4">
        This course's objective is to describe and analyze the ways in which the news media have become a part of the political system. In order to understand the manner in which news organizations interact with officials, organized groups, and the public focus will be on media influences in areas such as who gets to make policy and the outcome of policy making.
    </course>
    <course name="History of Political Theory" number="112A" units="4">
        Major theories from the ancient Greeks to the modern period. Ancient and medieval political thought, including Plato, Aristotle, and St. Augustine.
    </course>
    <course name="History of Political Theory" number="112B" units="4">
        Early modern political thought up to the French Revolution, including Machiavelli, Hobbes, Locke, and Rousseau.
    </course>
    <course name="History of Political Theory" number="112C" units="4">
        Nineteenth and twentieth century political thought, including Burke, Utilitarianism, Marx, and contemporary theory.
    </course>
    <course name="History of European Political Theory: The 20th Century" number="112D" units="4">
        This is a survey course that will examine developments in 20th-century European Political Theory. It will focus on theorists' contributions and reactions to various major political and intellectual shifts, including Marxism (as &quot;Western Marxism&quot; and Critical Theory, as well as institutionalized Soviet communism in its heyday); psychoanalysis; and facism.
    </course>
    <course name="American Political Theory" number="113A" units="4">
        Basic problems of political theory as viewed within the context of American history and institutions.
    </course>
    <course name="American Political Theory" number="113B" units="4">
        Basic problems of political theory as viewed within the context of American history and institutions.
    </course>
    <course name="Theories of Governance: Late 20th Century" number="114A" units="4">
        What is governance? How should we explain its emergence? What are its implications for public policy and democracy? This course uses debates about contemporary governance to examine four approaches to political science and political theory. The approaches are rational choice theory, institutionalism, Marxism, and poststructuralism. The course looks at the narrative that each approach provides of the origins and workings of governance since 1979, and at the way these narratives embody theoretical commitments about rationality and power, structure and agency, and democracy. It thus promotes an awareness of the way questions about contemporary governance are inextricably linked to philosophical and normative commitments. This course has a required discussion section.
    </course>
    <course name="Marxism and Culture" number="115C" units="4">
        The purpose of this course is to trace the development of Marxism as an idea system and political ideology since its inception, focusing particularly on developments in &quot;Communist&quot; or &quot;State Socialist&quot; systems, but also including a brief look at Eurocommunist thought.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116C" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116D" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116E" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116F" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116G" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116H" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116I" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116J" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116K" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116L" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116M" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116N" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116O" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116P" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116Q" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116R" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116S" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116T" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116U" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116V" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116W" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116X" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116Y" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="116Z" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Three American Cultures" number="118AC" units="4">
        The course will examine three American cultural forms. The focus of the course is to be comparative; readings will center around first-person accounts, written by members of the ethnic groups most immediately involved in each of the cultural forms. The theme is that of identity, seen politically as well as culturally: examining how the various ethnic groups involved came to forge a collective identity for themselves. The three groups studied will vary by instructor. See departmental listings for more specific information.
    </course>
    <course name="International Relations" number="120A" units="4">
        Comparative foreign policy.
    </course>
    <course name="Politics of European Integration" number="122A" units="4">
        The European Union is the world's most advanced experiment in governance beyond the level of the traditional nation-state. Through the European Union, the main members countries have pooled their national sovereignty and created new ways political authority, economic competition, social cohesion, and cultural identity. While specialists in comparative politics focus on the separate countries, scholars in international relations emphasize the construction of supranational institutions and transnational identities. This course seeks to synthesize the comparative and international approaches by examining the economic, political, and cultural aspects of integration. Readings are drawn from international relations, comparative politics, public policy, sociology, and some anthropological debates. Course requirements include careful preparation of the readings, discussion sections, participation in a group report on one of the major domains mentioned above, and a closed-book final.
    </course>
    <course name="Politics of European Integration" number="122AW" units="4">
        The European Union is the world's most advanced experiment in governance beyond the level of the traditional nation-state. As France, Britan, Germany, Spain, Poland, and the other main member states have pooled their sovereignty, they have created new ways of organizing the realities of economic competition, political authority, social cohesion, and cultural identity. Not surprisingly, there are several divisions among social scientists who study Europe. Specialists in comparative politics focus primarily on workings of national political economies, while scholars in international relations devote most of their attention to the construction of supranational institutions. Economists are especially interested in Europe's internal trade regime and currency arrangements. Sociologists and anthropologists have meanwhile focused growing attention to transnational interest groups, religion, and identity. The course seeks to bridge the intellectual divide between these different approaches by examining economic, political, and cultural aspects of integration. Readings are drawn primarily from the fields of international relations, comparative politics, and public policy.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123C" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123D" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123E" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123F" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123G" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123H" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123I" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123J" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123K" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123L" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123M" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123N" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123O" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123P" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123Q" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123R" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123S" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123T" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123U" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123V" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123W" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123X" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123Y" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="123Z" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="War!" number="124A" units="4">
        The nature and causes of war; the relationship of politics to war in history; historical varieties of strategic doctrine; the implementing of strategy; the endings of war.
    </course>
    <course name="Ethics and Justice in International Affairs" number="124C" units="4">
        Should nations intervene in other countries to prevent human rights abuses or famine? On what principles should immigration be based? Should wealthy states aid poorer states, and if so, how much? Who should pay for global environmental damage? Answers to these moral questions depend to a great degree on who we believe we have an obligation to: Ourselves? Nationals of our country? Residents of our country? Everyone in the world equally? We will examine different traditions of moral thought including skeptics, communitarians, cosmopolitans, and use these traditions as tools to make reasoned judgments about difficult moral problems in world politics.
    </course>
    <course name="International Political Economy" number="126A" units="4">
        Economic concepts in the study of international political behavior. Political concepts influencing the choice of economic policies.
    </course>
    <course name="International Law" number="127A" units="4">
        This course is an introduction to public international law for students of international relations. The primary purpose of this course is to enhance students' understanding of the ways in which international law orders international politics. How and to what extent has it been used in resolving conflicts between nations? How and to what extent has it facilitated the achievement of common goals? What is the relationship between international law and states' foreign policies? Emphasis throughout the course is on the substantive rules of the law, the relationship between law and politics, and on historical episodes that illustrate the issues. Substantive areas include international human rights, international trade law, and international law and the use of force.
    </course>
    <course name="Chinese Foreign Policy" number="128" units="4">
        This course covers the history and analysis of Chinese foreign policy since the inception of the People's Republic of China 1949. Some attention is devoted to pre-1949 Far Eastern international relations, but only as a background to the study of the contemporary period. Emphasis is placed on Sino-American and Sino-Soviet relations, on the domestic determinants of Chinese foreign policy, on the changing nature of China's relations with her Asian neighbors, and on important substantive issues.
    </course>
    <course name="Chinese Foreign Policy" number="128A" units="4">
        Chinese foreign policy from the inception of the People's Republic of China in 1949 to the present. This course aims at providing the student with a sufficient factual base, alternative theoretical approaches and some of the methodological tools useful in studying Chinese foreign policy.
    </course>
    <course name="Russia after Communism" number="129B" units="4">
        This course presents a broad introduction to contemporary politics and society in Russia. Other countries of the former Soviet Union and Eastern Europe will receive secondary attention. What was Soviet-type socialism and how is its legacy shaping post-Soviet Russia? Where is Russia headed - toward democracy as it is known in the West, a new form of authoritarianism, reversion to the old system, or something else? The social movements and political transformations of the Gorbachev period will be explored. Most of the course is devoted to the post-commmunist period and current problems of political change and upheaval. Topics to be investigated include the movement from a command economy to capitaliam, struggles among emerging social interests, the changing role of the military in society, crime and social disintegration, the rise of nationalism and the search for national identity, civil war, and the transformation of political institutions. The course is recommended for juniors and seniors but is open to all students.
    </course>
    <course name="Applied Econometrics and Public Policy" number="C131A" units="4">
        This course focuses on the sensible application of econometric methods to empirical problems in economics and public policy analysis. It provides background on issues that arise when analyzing non-experimental social science data and a guide for tools that are useful for empirical research. By the end of the course, students will have an understanding of the types of research designs that can lead to convincing analysis and be comfortable working with large scale data sets. Also listed as Public Policy C142 and Economics C142.
    </course>
    <course name="Game Theory in the Social Sciences" number="C135" units="4">
        A non-technical introduction to game theory. Basic principle, and models of interaction among players, with a strong emphasis on applications to political science, economics, and other social sciences. Also listed as Economics C110.
    </course>
    <course name="Theory in Comparative Analysis" number="136A" units="4">
        Major themes in comparative analysis. Political systems, culture, authority and other themes in the study of macro-politics. Subject matter will vary with instructor. For details consult departmental announcements.
    </course>
    <course name="Method in Comparative Analysis" number="136B" units="4">
        Application of the comparative method in the field of comparative politics. Use of comparison in description, hypothesis-testing, and theory construction. Methodological issues that arise in comparing national units and in making comparisons across different cultures.
    </course>
    <course name="Revolutionary Change" number="137A" units="4">
        Theories of revolutionary violence, rebellion, and revolution. Strategies of revolution, terrorism, sources of revolutionary action.
    </course>
    <course name="Revolutionary Movements" number="137B" units="4">
        Ideas as instruments of political action. A comparison of radical movements from the Middle Ages to the present day, emphasizing reactions to the rise of modern capitalism, industrial society and the post-industrial age.
    </course>
    <course name="Democracy and Its Alternatives in The Developing World" number="137C" units="4">
        This course offers a comparative study of the wave of democratization that swept much of Latin America, Southern Europe, East Asia, Africa, Eastern Europe, and the former Soviet Union during the past three decades. The course will analyze the theoretical literatures on regime change and compare experiences of countries emerging from bureaucratic authoritarianism, military rule, personalistic dictatorships, and state socialism. In addition to dealing with democratization, the course will address the reverse phenomenon, meaning movement from more democratic to more authoritarian regimes, a tendency that has been increasingly evident during the past decade. We will investigate, among other topics: the meaning of democracy and authoritarianism, the factors that facilitate or hinder democratization, the roles of mass movements, the significance of constitutional arrangements, problems of nationalism and ethnic conflict, and the relationship between economic transformation and political regime change.
    </course>
    <course name="Democracy, Democracies" number="138A" units="4">
        The course deals with issues in normative as well as empirical democratic theory. The first part deals with justifications for democracy as rule of the people versus other political systems. The second part deals with empirical theories about why some countries are democracies and others are not. The third part looks at whether institutional choices make a difference in the consolidation and performance of democracies.
    </course>
    <course name="Governance of the E-conomy" number="138D" units="4">
        New digital technologies, changing market structures, and innovative business organizations are transforming the economic and social landscape of the advanced industrial countries. The policy issues associated with this transformation pose fundamental philosophical and political questions of how to organize our markets, polity, and society. The means of making and implementing these choices is politics. The necessarily global scope of the E-conomy extends the political and policy challenges to the international arena. This course will explore the literature on the political economy of the Internet to determine what policy choices - and hence which political debates - are and will be most important. We also will examine our conceptual understanding of the burgeoning digital economy and its impact on politics, law, and socio-economic relations.
    </course>
    <course name="The Varieties of Capitalism: Political Economic Systems of the World" number="138E" units="4">
        This course examines the interaction between politics and markets, both in theory and in practice, explicitly linking classic works on political economy with current policy debates. We study how political systems and markets are organized in a wide range of different national settings, looking at both history and contemporary issues. Topics include: 1) Early industrialization in Britain and the United States, 2) Late industrialization in continental Europe and Japan, 3) The varieties of capitalism in contemporary industrialized countries, 4) The newly industrializing economics of Latin America and East Asia, 5) The problems of development, and 6) The transition from communism to a market economy in Eastern Europe and China.
    </course>
    <course name="Immigrants, Citizenship, and the State" number="138F" units="4">
        This course will examine international migration from a historical and comparative perspective, looking at why people migrate, how citizens respond to the migration, and how states respond to migration. The first part of the course looks at the changing relationship between the state, immigrants, and citizenship. Turning to case studies, we will examine five different types of receiving states, each confronted with a different form of migration: a traditional immigrant state, a post-colonial state, a non-traditional immigrant state that imports migrant workers, a highly industrialized latecomer state, and a newly industrialized state.
    </course>
    <course name="National Success and Failure in the Age of a Global Economy: from Pleats to Cleats" number="138G" units="4">
        In the present era political, economic, and social organization powerfully influence national capacity to assure economic success, real and rising incomes for the population, and political success, basic survival, and the projection of its purposes and values. This course looks at the continual process of international competition and transformation, and examines which factors separate the winners from the losers. We will gain leverage into these questions by examining critical moments in the 20th and 21st centuries and analyze according to national responses. What choices signal success? Can the failures be avoided? The course will discuss whether globalization is shunting aside national political choice, or whether globalization is in fact a sequence of national and regional stories played out on a larger stage. We will consider how economic constraint structures political choice and national response to the global economy. But we will also examine how political developments shape market dynamics and national innovations. We will learn about all sorts of things from the politics of French fashion to why Japanese make good cars.
    </course>
    <course name="Development Politics" number="139B" units="4">
        Politics of economic development in developing countries. Comparative analysis of the theories and practice of development in the light of contemporary experience. Political strategies of agrarian, industrial, educational, and regional development and their impact on autonomy, welfare, justice, and human development.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Issues of Development Politics" number="139C" units="4">
        See departmental announcements. Topics will vary with instructor.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140C" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140D" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140E" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140F" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140G" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140H" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140I" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140J" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140K" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140L" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140M" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140N" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140O" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140P" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140Q" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140R" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140S" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140T" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140U" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140V" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140W" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140X" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140Y" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="140Z" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Politics and Government in Eastern Europe" number="141C" units="4">
        Modern politics and government in the states of Eastern Europe presented within a broader cultural, historical, and sociological framework. Problems of economic underdevelopment and national fragmentation. Comparisons of the pre-Communist, Communist, and post-Communist periods.
    </course>
    <course name="Middle East Politics" number="142A" units="4">
        The Middle East in world affairs, international relations and domestic policies of contemporary states in the Middle East; policies and strategy of major powers; supranational movements, regional political and security organizations. The area comprises Turkey, Iran, Afghanistan, Israel, and the Arab countries.
    </course>
    <course name="Northeast Asian Politics" number="143A" units="4">
        The structure and evolution of political institutions in China, Japan, and Korea. Emphasis upon such topics as nationalism, political modernization, and ideology.
    </course>
    <course name="Northeast Asian Politics" number="143B" units="4">
        The structure and evolution of political institutions in China, Japan, and Korea. Emphasis upon such topics as nationalism, political modernization, and ideology.
    </course>
    <course name="Chinese Politics" number="143C" units="4">
        An overview of Chinese politics since the fall of the Qing Dynasty. Emphasis on the People's Republic of China and post-Mao reforms.
    </course>
    <course name="The Political Economy of China" number="143E" units="4">
        China's extraordinary growth has in some respects confirmed the power of free markets, but at the same time, it has challenged social scientists to think more deeply about the foundations and limits of the market economy. Furthermore, China's ever-increasing economic freedom and prosperity has been accompanied by only limited steps toward greater political freedom, running counter to one of the most consistent patterns of comparative politics and history. This class will cross conventional boundaries between political and economic analysis in order to address these issues.
    </course>
    <course name="Politics of Divided Korea" number="144B" units="4">
        An overview of modern Korea divided into the Republic of Korea and the Democratic People's Republic of Korea. The course will compare the two Koreas in terms of political, social and economic institutions, culture, political elites and modernization strategy.
    </course>
    <course name="South Asian Politics" number="145A" units="4">
        A comparative analysis of development and change in the political systems of contemporary South Asia.
    </course>
    <course name="South Asian Politics" number="145B" units="4">
        A comparative analysis of development and change in the political systems of contemporary South Asia.
    </course>
    <course name="African Politics" number="146A" units="4">
        Introduction to politics in the states of contemporary sub-Saharan Africa. Comparative study of political institutions and regime transitions; economic crisis and development; political violence and civil conflict.
    </course>
    <course name="African Politics" number="146B" units="4">
        In-depth analysis of several African states, focusing on the formation of their contemporary state structures and political systems, and the nature of current political processes and problems. Cases are chosen so as to highlight contrasting political strategies for the pursuit of economic development and social change. For details consult departmental announcements.
    </course>
    <course name="Western European Politics" number="147B" units="4">
        The political development of Western Europe from feudalism to the 20th century.Topics include absolutism, commericalization of agriculture, English and French revolutions, industrialization, national unification, working class incorporation, democratic and authoritarian regime outcomes, comtemporary politics and policy. Focus on Britain, France, Germany, and Italy.
    </course>
    <course name="Contemporary French Politics: The Republican Model in Transition" number="147F" units="4">
        French political life has long gravitated around a &quot;Republican model&quot; marked by an unmediated relationship between the citizen and the state, socialization into French values through secular public education, a special vocation for France on the international stage, and an activist state. Recent developments have called the Republican model into question. This course will examine the transformation of France's Republican model - its origins, operations, and responses to contemporary challenges.
    </course>
    <course name="The Welfare State in Comparative Perspective" number="147G" units="4">
        Comparision of welfare states in Western Europe and North America. Origins of welfare states. Varieties of welfare states. Relationship between welfare states and the economy. Impact of changing social, economic, and family structure states. Contemporary welfare reform.
    </course>
    <course name="The Domestic Politics of Postwar Western Europe" number="147H" units="4">
        This course examines the different ways in which the leading nations of Western Europe--Britain, France, Germany, and to a lesser extent, Italy and Sweden--have confronted common problems in the postwar period.
    </course>
    <course name="Latin American Politics" number="148A" units="4">
        Political institutions, groups and parties in Latin American countries. Basic characteristics of political processes in Latin America; problems of political development and modernization and political change. Comparative study of political systems, institutions, groups and political culture.
    </course>
    <course name="Latin American Politics" number="148B" units="4">
        Political institutions, groups and parties in Latin American countries. Basic characteristics of political processes in Latin America; problems of political development and modernization and political change. Comparative study of political systems, institutions, groups and political culture.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149C" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149D" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149E" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149F" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149G" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149H" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149I" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149J" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149K" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149L" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149M" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149N" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149O" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149P" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149Q" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149R" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149S" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149T" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149U" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149V" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149W" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149X" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149Y" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="149Z" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="The American Legal System" number="150" units="4">
        The nature of the American legal system; the interrelationships of judges, lawyers, police, political officials, bureaucrats, press, and general public; the political and social aspects of the legal process.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152C" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152D" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152E" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152F" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152G" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152H" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152I" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152J" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152K" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152L" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152M" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152N" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152O" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152P" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152Q" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152R" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152S" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152T" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152U" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152V" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152W" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152X" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152Y" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="152Z" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Constitutional Law of the United States" number="157A" units="4">
        Fundamental principles of constitutional law, leading cases, causes, and consequences of legal decisions and their role in influencing, shaping, and constraining the American political system.
    </course>
    <course name="Constitutional Law of the United States" number="157B" units="4">
        Fundamental principles of constitutional law, leading cases, causes, and consequences of legal decisions and their role in influencing, shaping, and constraining the American political system.
    </course>
    <course name="Public Opinion, Voting and Participation" number="161" units="4">
        The nature of public opinion, attitude formation, electoral turnout and choice; political cleavages; the role of the mass public.
    </course>
    <course name="Political Psychology and Involvement" number="164A" units="4">
        Personality factors in political behavior; psychological roots of decision-making; leadership; psychological sources of political belief; conflict theory.
    </course>
    <course name="Racial and Ethnic Politics in the New American Century" number="167" units="4">
        Some of the most enduring and violent conflicts in America center on race. The goal of this course is to explore, discuss, and better understand the relationship between perceptions of racial identity, attributions of racial difference, and politics, broadly defined. We focus on the recent and persistent debates about racism, identity, rights, representation, citizenship, conflict, and coalitions. A repeated theme of this course is the question whether racial order and inequality are essential to, or an exception from, the liberal democracy in the U.S. This is a lecture course with intensive readings, written assignments, and in-class discussion.
    </course>
    <course name="Racial and Ethnic Politics in the New American Century" number="167AC" units="4">
        Some of the most enduring and violent conflicts in America center on race. The goal of this course is to explore, discuss, and better understand the relationship between perceptions of racial identity, attributions of racial difference, and politics, broadly defined. We focus on the recent and persistent debates about racism, identity, rights, representation, citizenship, conflict, and coalitions. A repeated theme of this course is the question whether racial order and inequality are essential to, or an exception from, the liberal democracy in the U.S. This is a lecture course with intensive readings, written assignments, and in-class discussion.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in Political Behavior" number="169" units="4">
        See departmental announcements.
    </course>
    <course name="California Politics" number="171" units="4">
        An inquiry into the political environment of the state--historical, economic, geographic, and social; its political institutions--government, parties, interest groups, and citizens; and the policies resulting from the interaction of environment and institutions.
    </course>
    <course name="Political Economy of the California Crisis" number="173S" units="4">
        This course examines the emergence and crisis of California's political economy. An analytical framework is developed that encompasses the secular growth and cyclical variability of California's income, expenditure, and revenue levels. California's economic growth and political development since 1875 will be analyzed. Specific topics covered include the Edmund G. (Pat) Brown era; Proposition 13 and the Ronald Reagan governorship; California's demographic transformation; challenges of minority economic development and political representation; the 2003 gubernatorial recall and the 2002-04 fiscal crisis. Course is part of the University of California Center Sacramento Program and is located in Sacramento.
    </course>
    <course name="The Unseen America" number="176" units="4">
        Social science methods and philosophies; on-site observation of &quot;unseen&quot; parts of local community: war veterans, elderly, alcoholics, prisoners, military personnel, factory workers, et al. Frequent field trips led by undergraduate student coordinators. Classroom discussions also directed by undergraduate student coordinators under the direction of the sponsoring faculty.
    </course>
    <course name="Undergraduate Colloquium on Political Science" number="179" units="1">
        Political issues facing the state of California, the United States, or the international community.
    </course>
    <course name="Public Organization and Administration" number="181" units="4">
        The methods used to manage the power of the bureaucracy in the American political system. An introduction to theories of organizational behavior. The effects of administrative structure upon the creation and distribution of public benefits.
    </course>
    <course name="Administrative Behavior" number="183" units="4">
        The dynamics of public policy formulation within bureaucratic organizations; the influence upon public organizations of the legislature and pressure groups; patterns of conflict within public organizations.
    </course>
    <course name="Public Problems" number="186" units="4">
        Homelessness, global warming, corruption, bankrupt pension systems, educational inequality: the list of intractable public problems seems to grow every year. This course explores the way societies try to address and solve difficult and seemingly intractable public problems. Can we attribute success or failure to institutions and their capacity to solve problems? Are problems difficult to solve because they are complex or because of a failure of political will? What are the characteristics of organizations or communities that are able to solve problems? How are public problems framed and how are they used to mobilize constituencies? The course draws on literature in public administration, public policy studies, and democratic theory to try to better understand some of the major social, political, environmental, and economic problems of our contemporary world.
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar: Technology and Politics" number="187C" units="4">
        The relationship of technology to social/political change, scope of challenges of democratic governance of technical developments, the bases for technological dissent, roots and promises of technology assessment in the congressional setting, and alerts for the future in the development of public policy.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in Public Organization and Policy" number="189" units="4">
        See departmental announcements for topics.
    </course>
    <course name="Honors Seminar" number="H190A" units="4">
        Eligible students must have taken at least two letter-graded upper division Political Science courses at Berkeley. H190A is the first of a two-semester research seminar designed to provide support and structure to political science seniors writing an honors thesis. To receive department honors, students must maintain the minimum GPA for honors and complete H190B with a B+ or better. For additional details, please consult the Undergraduate Advising Office or http://www.polisci.berkeley.edu.
    </course>
    <course name="Honors Seminar" number="H190B" units="4">
        Eligible students must have taken at least two letter-graded upper division Political Science courses at Berkeley. H190B is the second of a two-semester research seminar designed to provide support and structure to political science seniors writing an honors thesis. To receive department honors, students must maintain the minimum GPA for honors and complete H190B with a B+ or better. For additional details, please consult the Undergraduate Advising Office or http://www.polisci.berkeley.edu.
    </course>
    <course name="Junior Seminar" number="191" units="4">
        The seminars will be led by ladder-rank faculty members in the subfields of American Politics, International Relations, and Comparative Politics. These intense writing seminars will focus on the research area of the faculty member teaching the course. The seminars will provide an opportunity for students to have direct intellectual interactions with faculty members while also giving the students an understanding of faculty research.
    </course>
    <course name="Senior Honors Thesis" number="H195A" units="4">
        Independent research and thesis. Satisfies thesis requirement for honors candidates. Both semesters must be taken and completed with a final grade of B+ or better in order for departmental honors to be awarded. Applications and details through the Undergraduate Office.
    </course>
    <course name="Senior Honors Thesis" number="H195B" units="4">
        Independent research and thesis. Satisfies thesis requirement for honors candidates. Both semesters must be taken and completed with a final grade of B+ or better in order for departmental honors to be awarded. Applications and details through the Undergraduate Office.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Research Project" number="196" units="1-4">
        Independent study of an advanced topic resulting in a substantial research paper.
    </course>
    <course name="UC Sacramento Internship and Research Seminar" number="196S" units="9-13">
        This seminar will introduce students to the theory and practice of policy analysis and development as it relates to legislative action at the state level to maximize students' internship experience. The internship component of the course will provide students with a challenging opportunity to engage in experiential learning in some aspect of the political, policy-making, or governmental processes in California's state capital. This course will permit students to develop a systematic understanding of the public policy and political process in California and to develop analytical writing skills to produce a 25-30 page research paper developing and reflecting on this understanding. This course is part of the University of California Center Sacramento Program and is located in Sacramento.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Field Research" number="C196W" units="10.5">
        Students work in selected internship programs approved in advance by the faculty coordinator and for which written contracts have been established between the sponsoring organization and the student. Students will be expected to produce two progress reports for their faculty coordinator during the course of the internship, as well as a final paper for the course consisting of at least 35 pages. Other restrictions apply; see faculty adviser. Also listed as Gender and Women's Studies C196W, History of Art C196W, Undergrad Interdisciplinary Studies C196W, Mass Communications C196W, History C196W, Political Economy of Industrial Soc C196W, and Sociology C196W.
    </course>
    <course name="Field Study in Political Science" number="197" units="1-3">
        Supervised experience relevant to specific aspects of Political Science in off-campus organizations. Regular individual meetings with faculty sponsor and written reports required.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study for Undergraduates" number="198" units="1-4">
        Submission of study proposal by faculty sponsor to the department chairman one month in advance of the semester to be offered. Group studies of selected topics which vary from year to year.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study and Research for Undergraduates" number="199" units="1-4">
        Enrollment is restricted by departmental regulation.
    </course>
    <course name="Major Themes in Comparative Analysis" number="200" units="4">
        Subject and texts to be studied vary with instructor. See departmental announcements.
    </course>
    <course name="Comparative Analysis of Industrial Democracies" number="201B" units="4">
        The comparative study of politics in Western societies. The place of parties, political structures, interest groups, and economic institutions. The relation between domestic political developments and the international system. The effect of economic development on political change. The effect of labor politics on national politics.
    </course>
    <course name="Governance of the E-conomy" number="201D" units="4">
        New digital technologies, changing market structures, and innovative business organizations are transforming the economic and social landscape of the advanced industrial countries. The policy issues associated with this transformation pose fundamental philosophical and political questions of how to organize our markets, polity, and society. The means of making and implementing these choices is politics. The necessarily global scope of the E-conomy extends the political and policy challenges to the international arena. This course will explore the literature on the political economy of the Internet to determine what policy choices -- hence which political debates -- are and will be most important. We also will examine our conceptual understanding of the burgeoning digital economy and its impact on politics, law, and socio-economic relations.
    </course>
    <course name="Institutions for Economic and Political Competition" number="201E" units="4">
        This seminar compares alternative approaches to the institutional arrangements that are shaping competition in the advanced countries. Debates in political economy, sociology, and the economics of organization show that industrial democracies are experimenting with new rules and frameworks by which they grovern themselves and coordinate economic activity. Comparative analysis shows that a range of governance mechanisms -- networks, associations, regions, and federal systems of coordination -- are evolving alongside markets as practical forms of forms for organizing economic and political competition. Collective choices among these different arrangements are complex and contested, because different groups place different value on the goals of economic efficiency and growth on the one hand, political accountability and autonomy on the other.
    </course>
    <course name="Theories of Development and Political Change." number="202A" units="4">
        Issues of social organization and political change. Theories of progress, development, modernization and dependence.
    </course>
    <course name="Political Leadership" number="204" units="4">
        Graduate seminar. Open to students from all disciplines and colleges who are interested in the disciplined study of political leadership. The course examines contending definitions of political leadership and then delves into literature on agency versus structure (&quot;what difference does leadership make?&quot;). It examines the ways in which leaders typically make decisions, the resources on which they draw for getting their decisions promulgated and implemented, the strategies they employ for building and maintaining their authority, and the criteria employed by scholars for evaluating leaders' effectiveness. Students will read and discuss case studies of leaders of politics, public and private organizations, and social movements.
    </course>
    <course name="Authoritarianism" number="208" units="4">
        This seminar explores the characteristics and dynamics of non-democratic regimes: how and why they come about, what sustains them, why some people resist and others do not, and how and why they decline and fall. While there are no formal methodological prerequisites for this course, we will encounter a variety of approaches, including formal, large-N statistical, small-N qualitative, narrative, and literary. Our discussions will weave theoretical and methodological ideas with detailed analysis of historical and contemporary dictatorial regimes.
    </course>
    <course name="Comparative Political Economy" number="209A" units="4">
        Emphasis on three models of modern society--&quot;post industrial,&quot; &quot;mass,&quot; and &quot;corporatist&quot;--as they apply to countries labelled capitalist and socialist, pluralist and totalitarian. The aim: to evaluate convergence theory and explore divergent paths of development among rich countries. Special attention to stratification, the welfare state, mass media, role of intellectuals.
    </course>
    <course name="Post Fordism: New Patterns of Production, Time, and Meaning in Contemporary Capitalism" number="209B" units="4">
        With changes in technology, the internationalization of production and the massive increase in trans-border transactions of all kinds, it has been argued that we live and work in an era of substantively different capitalism. Were this true, it has deep implications for politics and for political economy. This graduate seminar explores the validity of this claim of a &quot;new capitalism&quot; through a variety of materials, starting with the question of whether &quot;Fordism&quot; ever existed, moving on to the question of whether &quot;Post-Fordism&quot; exists and ending with a variety of ethnographic studies that show how global production chains shape culture, gender, and hieraarchy/power.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in Comparative Politics" number="210" units="4">
        See departmental announcements. Topic will vary with instructor.
    </course>
    <course name="History of Political Thought: Ancient and Medieval" number="212A" units="4">
        A weekly seminar on political thought from the ancient Greeks to the Renaissance. Ancient and medieval political theorist, typically including Plato, Aristotle, St. Augustine, and Aquinas.
    </course>
    <course name="History of Political Thought: Early Modern (Renaissance to French Revolution)" number="212B" units="4">
        A weekly seminar on political thought from the Renaissance to the French Revolution. Early modern political theorists, typically including Machiavelli, Hobbes, Locke, Rousseau, and Burke.
    </course>
    <course name="History of Political Thought: Modern (French Revolution through World War II)" number="212C" units="4">
        A weekly seminar on political thought in the 19th and early 20th centuries. Modern political theorists, typically including Tocqueville, Hegel, Marx, Mill, Nietzsche, and Weber.
    </course>
    <course name="Methodological Topics in the History of Political Thought" number="213" units="4">
        A weekly seminar on political thought in the 19th and early 20th centuries. Modern political theorists, typically including Tocqueville, Hegel, Marx, Mill, Nietzsche, and Weber.
    </course>
    <course name="Themes in Western Political Theory" number="214" units="4">
        Themes to be specified by instructor.
    </course>
    <course name="Approaches to Contemporary Political Theory" number="215A" units="4">
        A weekly seminar on contemporary approaches to political theory.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics to Contemporary Political Theory" number="215B" units="4">
        A weekly seminar on leading topics in contemporary political theory.
    </course>
    <course name="Symposium in Contemporary Political Theory" number="216" units="4">
        An intensive examination of a contemporary theorist, debate, or issue.
    </course>
    <course name="Theories of International Relations" number="220A" units="4">
        Origin, application and utility of major concepts featured in the study of international relations. Relation of various strands of political and social theory to international relations.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in International Relations" number="223" units="4">
        See departmental announcements. Topic will vary with instructor.
    </course>
    <course name="Sociological Traditions in International Relations" number="224" units="4">
        This seminar traces the development of the constructivist program in international relations in order to better understand its elements, assumptions, and methods and apply those to current issues. We start by uncovering the roots of constructivism in sociology and philosophy and examine structuation theory, the English School, world systems theory, regime theory, and sociological institutionalism. The second part of this course focuses on the constructivist agenda in international relations, its boundaries and its critics. In the last part of the course we examine current research in IR that draws on sociological methods, including work on the role of norms, epistemic communities, transnational civil society, and the origins of the state.
    </course>
    <course name="International Security" number="224A" units="4">
        The goal of this course is to introduce advanced political science graduate students to current debates in the field of international security and to prepare these students for conducting dissertation research in their own areas of interest within this field. This course is designed for advanced political science graduate students preparing to commence their dissertation research. Its orientation is theoretical rather than empirical and it is both reading and research.
    </course>
    <course name="The Empirical Analysis of International Security" number="225A" units="4">
        This course offers an introduction to the empirical analysis of International Security. The primary goals are 1) to acquaint students with the empirical knowledge in the field of International Security that has been produced with quantitative approaches and 2) to help students develop and hone their skills in empirical analysis. Therefore, particular emphasis will be given on how to go beyond being &quot;consumers&quot; of empirical research and how to become &quot;producers&quot; of novel empirical knowledge.
    </course>
    <course name="International Political Economy" number="226A" units="4">
        The creation, maintenance, transformation, and decay of international arrangements designed to manage or regulate interstate activities relating to trade, money, resource use, technology, and physical environment.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantitative Analysis in Political Research" number="231A" units="4">
        Introductory course in the analysis of political data.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantitative Analysis in Political Research" number="231B" units="4">
        Topics from multi-equation causal modeling and introductory econometrics, with special emphasis on procedures appropriate for political data, including survey data.
    </course>
    <course name="Formal Models of Political Science" number="232A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Formal Models of Political Science" number="232B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Psychometric and Econometric Methods" number="233" units="4">
        Most political science data suffer from two major problems: the measures of theoretical constructs contain substantial amounts of error and the processes generating the data involve reciprocal causation (&quot;simultaneity&quot;) or selection effects. In addition, political scientists often only have nominal or ordinal measures for their concepts. This course explores methods for correcting these problems through careful statistical modelling.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Research Methods" number="235" units="4">
        Overview of methods of political research. Theories, concepts, variables, hypotheses. Research design, quantitative and qualitative methodology. Basic data collection techniques. Approaches to data analysis. Provides an overview of different statistical techniques, but does not teach statistics per se.
    </course>
    <course name="The Statistics of Causal Inference in the Social Sciences" number="236" units="4">
        Approaches to causal inference using the potential outcomes framework. Covers observational studies with and without ignorable treatment assignment, randomized experiments with and without noncompliance, instrumental variables, regression discontinuity, sensitivity analysis, and random inference. Applications are drawn from a variety of fields including political science, economics, sociology, public health, and medicine.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in Methodology" number="239" units="4">
        See departmental announcements. Topic will vary with instructor.
    </course>
    <course name="Politics in the Post-Communist World" number="241D" units="4">
        Reading and discussion seminar for graduate students. Comparative analysis of divergent paths of development among the almost 30 new states that formerly comprised the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe. Focus on changes in politics, economics, social stratification, culture, and international relations. Discussions of competing explanations for the observed patterns, and of their implications for theories of development, modernization, and international relations.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Middle East Politics" number="242" units="4">
        An advanced seminar, designed to encourage synthesis of empirical research and theoretical reflection. Focused each year on a specific dimension of Middle East politics (state formation, local politics, sectarianism, Islamic political thought, etc.). A seminar paper and class presentations are required.
    </course>
    <course name="International Relations in East Asia" number="243A" units="4">
        This reading seminar will focus on dynamic interactions of four major powers--the United States, former Soviet Union, China, and Japan, which are also global powers--and two minor actors--South and North Korea--from bilateral, regional, and global perspectives.
    </course>
    <course name="Political Authority and Economic Exchange in East Asia" number="243B" units="4">
        This course will compare how authority and exchange relations are combined to regulate political and economic activities in China, Taiwan, South Korea, North Korea, and Japan. The course will examine theoretical literature on state-society relations, market, world system, late development, as well as empirical case studies dealing with each nation covered.
    </course>
    <course name="Japanese Politics" number="243C" units="4">
        Japanese domestic politics--issues in historical development; political bureaucratic and legal structures; studies in economic policymaking.
    </course>
    <course name="Analysis of Contemporary China" number="244A" units="4">
        This is the first in a two-semester sequence designed to provide the incoming graduate student with a basic grounding in the politics of contemporary China. The focus will be on wide reading and comprehension of the available analytical literature; its sequel will be devoted to integrating that reading with primary source research materials. There are no prerequisites, though undergraduate course work in Chinese politics and/or some acquaintance with the Chinese language would be useful.
    </course>
    <course name="Analysis of Contemporary China" number="244B" units="4">
        This second semester concentrates on the acquistion of bibliographical mastery of primary sources and the application research skills. The seminar is chronologically divided into three sections: 1. Two weeks on the problems of conceptualization and methodology; 2. Four weeks on reading and analyzing primary materials from the recent period of &quot;socialist reform&quot;; and 3. A final period of oral reports on student research topics.
    </course>
    <course name="Approaches to Chinese Politics" number="244C" units="4">
        This course has three main objectives: to expose students to debates in the study of post-1949 Chinese politics; to consider how research on contemporary China both draws from and informs political science; and to explore characterizations of the Chinese state and state-society relations. Emphasis on questions such as: What can we learn by examining Chinese culture and institutions? Do concepts such as fragmented authoritarianism, neotraditionalism, state &quot;reach,&quot; civil society, and corporatism produce insights into the structure and dynamics of Chinese politics?
    </course>
    <course name="Collective Action in China" number="244D" units="4">
        This course will explore contentious politics in the People's Republic of China. Special attention to the current era and dissent by peasants, migrants, workers, religious groups, women, students, artists, and dissidents. How do concepts drawn from social movement theory help us understand popular activism? What are the consequences of protest for regime stability and the development of a more complete citizenship?
    </course>
    <course name="The Political Economy of China" number="244E" units="4">
        This course will examine the interrelationships between politics and the economy in contemporary China. How has China achieved rapid economic growth when basic market institutions are missing or deeply corrupted? How have China's leaders managed to keep economic development from leading to democratization? Does China's experience hold lessons for other developing countries?
    </course>
    <course name="South Asian Politics" number="245A" units="4">
        Major themes of politics and international relations in India, Pakistan, Burma and the mountain kingdoms.
    </course>
    <course name="Comparative Politics in Asia" number="245C" units="4">
        Comparative politics has tended to neglect Asia, the most economically vital region of the globe, while Asian studies has tended to be based fundamentally on an area studies approach cum single-country monographic analyses. This seminar attempts to look at Asian politics from a comparative perspective. Course requirements focus on intensive and extensive reading, as indicated by a series of brief comparative review-essays and lively class discussions. No formal course prerequisites.
    </course>
    <course name="African Politics" number="246" units="4">
        Politics of Sub-Saharan Africa; relations of state and society in the context of weak states; state building; societal pluralism; the political role of ethnicity; crisis states and proto-national states; ethnic states; oppression and restratification; conflict and class formation; political order and development; modernization and equity; and interstate conflict and international order.
    </course>
    <course name="Western European Politics" number="247B" units="4">
        Major themes of politics and international relations of Western Europe.
    </course>
    <course name="German Politics" number="247C" units="4">
        The seminar provides a general overview of modern German political development in the context of Central European history, and detailed analyses of selected topics.
    </course>
    <course name="The Comparative Politics of the Welfare State" number="247G" units="4">
        This course analyzes the politics of social protection in Western Europe and the United States. After describing different national welfare regimes, we turn to contemporary challenges, notably globalization, persistent poverty, and changes in family forms and gender roles. We also look at the politics of welfare retrenchment and adjustment, paying particular attention to the prospects for progressive social policy. Must reform inevitably scale back protections for the weak and vulnerable, or can equity be safeguarded while promoting efficiency?
    </course>
    <course name="Latin American Politics" number="248A" units="4">
        Explores different analytical approaches to Latin American politics, focusing both on major concepts (clientelism, corporatism, the state, legitimacy, nationalism) and different explanatory approaches (focusing on factors such as dependency and imperialism, internal social order and economic change, political structure and institutions and political culture).
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249A" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249B" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249C" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249D" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249E" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249F" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249G" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249H" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249I" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249J" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249K" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249L" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249M" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249N" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249O" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249P" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249Q" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249R" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249S" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249T" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249U" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249V" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249W" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249X" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249Y" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="249Z" units="4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Legal Theory and Institutions" number="252" units="4">
        The organization and behavior of legal institutions, with particular reference to American courts and administrative agencies. Institutional responses to problems of legality, authority, policy choice, and the organization of enforcement and decision-making processes. Readings include empirical studies, judicial opinions, jurisprudential writings and organization theory.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in Public law" number="259" units="4">
        See departmental announcements. Topic will vary with instructor.
    </course>
    <course name="Political Behavior" number="261" units="4">
        A comprehensive review of the major topics in political behavior through intensive examination of the theories, findings, and proceedings of the most significant studies in the field.
    </course>
    <course name="Voting Behavior and Public Opinion" number="262" units="4">
        Examination of the basic literature on American voting behavior, public opinion and student research on individually selected topics in this field.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in Political Behavior" number="269" units="4">
        See departmental announcements. Topic will vary with instructor.
    </course>
    <course name="American Government" number="271A" units="4">
        The principal topics in American national politics, including public opinion, elections, parties, interest groups, Congress, the presidency, the bureaucracy, and policy information.
    </course>
    <course name="American Government" number="271B" units="4">
        The principal topics in American national politics, including public opinion, elections, parties, interest groups, Congress, the presidency, the bureaucracy, and policy information.
    </course>
    <course name="National Policy Making" number="272A" units="4">
        National policy-making processes, concentration on congress, the Presidency, and interactions among policy-making institutions.
    </course>
    <course name="National Policy Making" number="272B" units="4">
        National policy-making processes, concentration on congress, the Presidency, and interactions among policy-making institutions.
    </course>
    <course name="Urban Politics" number="273" units="4">
        Politics and policy-making in American cities. Historical, economic and social context of cities. Major urban political institutions, other levels of government in urban affairs.
    </course>
    <course name="American Political Development" number="274" units="4">
        This course will consider several broad themes in American political development. The objective is to extract the central conditions, processes, and controversies that scholars have found running through American political development and try to come to terms with possible relations among them.
    </course>
    <course name="Principles of Policy Analysis" number="275" units="4">
        The study of American public policy doctrines, policy formulation, evaluation, and implementation, including the role of social science research in policy-making.
    </course>
    <course name="Race, Immigration and Identity in United States Politics" number="276" units="4">
        The goal of this course is to explore, discuss, and better understand the relationship between perceptions of racial identity, attributions of racial difference, and politics, broadly defined. It focuses on recent and contemporaneous intersections of race, immigration, and identity politics in the U.S. While much of the readings come from quantitative studies of political behavior, students are expected to grapple enthusiastically with parallel debates in philosophy, psychology, sociology, economics, and history.
    </course>
    <course name="Political Regulation" number="277" units="4">
        This course looks at political regulation and reform issues from both empirical and normative perspectives. Topics include campaign finance reform, lobbying regulations, bribery, voting franchise restrictions, redistricting, term limitations, direct democracy, political fairness, and the design of electoral institutions.
    </course>
    <course name="Selected Topics in American Government" number="279" units="4">
        See departmental announcements. Topic will vary with instructor.
    </course>
    <course name="Public Organization Theory" number="280A" units="4">
        A survey of the literature of organization and management theory, emphasizing the major writers and distinctive contributions of various disciplines.
    </course>
    <course name="Comparative Administration" number="280B" units="4">
        A comparative analysis of the structures and processes which are used to control public bureaucracies in selected political systems and the effects of those controls on the character of administrative performance.
    </course>
    <course name="Politics and Organization" number="280C" units="4">
        The process of public policy formulation, governmental planning and programming, and administrative decision-making.
    </course>
    <course name="Strategies of Contemporary Governance" number="284" units="4">
        This course explores the implications of new strategies for coping with social problems and managing public programs. In response to growing criticism of government bureaucracy, public skepticism of expert authority, and an explosion of advocacy groups, a variety of new governance strategies have been developed. These new strategies are characterized by five broad themes: the use of markets or market mechanisms to increase efficiency; an emphasis on holding public agencies accountable and making them more transparent; the development of coordinating networks to link public agencies with each other and with stakeholders; the extensive involvement of non-state organizations in all aspects of governing; and renewed attention to the civic role of individuals and communities. The course investigates the extent to which these new strategies succeed in making the governance process more efficient, accountable, effective, representative, and civic.
    </course>
    <course name="Development Administration" number="287" units="4">
        The problems of administering economic development programs in poor countries. Particular emphasis is placed on rural development, the problems of relating bureaucratic structures to peasant communities, and the relevance of organization theory to non-Western administration.
    </course>
    <course name="Research Topics in Public Organization" number="289" units="4">
        See departmental announcements.
    </course>
    <course name="Dissertation Research" number="290" units="4">
        Seminar to aid students in initiating, carrying out, and completing dissertation research. Problems of planning dissertation research, the preparation of research designs and proposals for outside funding, field work, and writing and presenting the results of completed research. Presentations by graduate students working on their dissertations.
    </course>
    <course name="Research Workshop in American Politics" number="291" units="1,2">
        A forum for the presentation and discussion of research in progress by graduate students. To receive two units of credit, a student must make at least one presentation of work in progress and serve as a discussant for another student's presentation. To receive one unit of credit a student must regularly attend class and participate in discussion, but will not be required to make a presentation. Appropriate works in progress include (but are not limited to) a paper in preparation for submission to a journal, a dissertation prospectus (including early drafts), a dissertation chapter, or a job market paper. Anyone working on American politics, political behavior, public law, or public administration is welcome.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Advanced Study" number="292" units="2-12">
        Open to qualified graduate students wishing to pursue special study and research under direction of a member of the staff.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Dissertation Research" number="296" units="4-12">
        Open to qualified students advanced to candidacy for the Ph.D. degree.
    </course>
    <course name="Independent Study in Preparation for the M.A. Essay" number="299" units="4-8">
        Open only to qualified first-year graduate students working toward the M.A. degree.
    </course>
    <course name="Graduate Student Instructor Training Seminar" number="301" units="2">
        This course is intended for all new graduate student instructors (GSI) in the Department of Political Science, and is meant to be taken simultaneously with the first semester of teaching as a GSI. The course functions as a participatory workshop. Although the course is intended for first-time GSIs, it is not a course in &quot;how to be a GSI,&quot; but rather, how to be an effective political science teacher, now and at later steps in professional careers. Workshop time will be divided among presentations by the instructor, discussion of required readings, and discussion of weekly assignments in relation to challenges encountered by GSIs in the course of their teaching.
    </course>
    <course name="Professional Preparation for Graduate Student Instructors." number="398" units="4">
        Special study under the direction of a staff member with emphasis on the teaching of undergraduate courses in political science.
    </course>
    <course name="Research Skills" number="404" units="1-4">
        Individual research work under supervision of faculty members. Open to students engaged in supervised research projects in Political Science.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study for Doctoral Students" number="602" units="4-12">
        Individual study in consultation with the major field adviser, intended to provide opportunity for qualified students to prepare themselves for the various examinations required of candidates for the Ph.D. May not be used for unit or residence requirements for the doctoral degree.
    </course>
</department>
