<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="UGBA" name="Undergraduate Business Administration">
    <course name="Principles of Business" number="10" units="3">
        This course provides an introduction to the study of the modern business enterprise. The course is taught in five modules, the order of which may vary from semester to semester. The first examines the role and governance of business enterprise in a market economy. The second concentrates on financial issues, while the third looks at the problems of managing people in organizations. The fourth examines product pricing, marketing, and distribution issues and the last concentrates on the international business environment.
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman Seminars" number="24" units="1">
        The Berkeley Seminar Program has been designed to provide new students with the opportunity to explore an intellectual topic with a faculty member in a small-seminar setting. Berkeley Seminars are offered in all campus departments, and topics vary from department to department and semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Philanthropy: A Cross-Cultural Perspective" number="39AC" units="3">
        This class will compare and contrast the variety of gift giving and sharing traditions that make up American philanthropy. Both the cultural antecedents and their expression in this country will be explored from five ethnic and racial groups: Native American, European American, African American, Hispanic American, and Asian American. The goal is to gain a greater understanding of the many dimensions of philanthropy as it is practiced in the United States today.
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman/Sophomore Seminar" number="39D" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Sophomore Seminar" number="84" units="1,2">
        Sophomore seminars are small interactive courses offered by faculty members in departments all across the campus. Sophomore seminars offer opportunity for close, regular intellectual contact between faculty members and students in the crucial second year. The topics vary from department to department and semester to semester. Enrollment limited to 15 sophomores.
    </course>
    <course name="Lower Division Special Topics in Business Administration" number="96" units="1-4">
        Study in various fields of business administration for lower division students. Topics will vary from year to year and will be announced at the beginning of each semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study" number="98" units="1-4">
        Organized group study on topics selected by lower division students under the sponsorship and direction of a member of the Haas School of Business faculty.
    </course>
    <course name="Business Communication" number="100" units="2">
        Theory and practice of effective communication in a business environment. Students practice what they learn with oral presentations and written assignments that model real-life business situations.
    </course>
    <course name="Microeconomic Analysis for Business Decisions" number="101A" units="3">
        Economic analysis applicable to the problems of business enterprises with emphasis on the determination of the level of prices, outputs, and inputs; effects of the state of the competitive environment on business and government policies.
    </course>
    <course name="Macroeconomic Analysis for Business Decisions" number="101B" units="3">
        Analysis of the operation of the market system with emphasis on the factors responsible for economic instability; analysis of public and business policies which are necessary as a result of business fluctuations.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Financial Accounting" number="102A" units="3">
        The identification, measurement, and reporting of financial effects of events on enterprises, with a particular emphasis on business organization. Preparation and interpretation of balance sheets, income statements, and statements of cash flows.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Managerial Accounting" number="102B" units="3">
        The uses of accounting systems and their outputs in the process of management of an enterprise. Classification of costs and revenue on several bases for various uses; budgeting and standard cost accounting; analyses of relevant costs and other data for decision making.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Finance" number="103" units="4">
        Analysis and management of the flow of funds through an enterprise. Cash management, source and application of funds, term loans, types and sources of long-term capital. Capital budgeting, cost of capital, and financial structure. Introduction to capital markets.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Organizational Behavior" number="105" units="3">
        A general descriptive and analytical study of organizations from the behavioral science point of view. Problems of motivation, leadership, morale, social structure, groups, communications, hierarchy, and control in complex organizations are addressed. The interaction among technology, environment, and human behavior are considered. Alternate theoretical models are discussed.
    </course>
    <course name="Marketing" number="106" units="3">
        The evolution of markets and marketing; market structure; marketing cost and efficiency; public and private regulation; the development of marketing programs including decisions involving products, price, promotional distribution.
    </course>
    <course name="The Social, Political, and Ethical Environment of Business" number="107" units="3">
        Study and analysis of American business in a changing social and political environment. Interaction between business and other institutions. Role of business in the development of social values, goals, and national priorities. The expanding role of the corporation in dealing with social problems and issues.
    </course>
    <course name="Economics of Regulated Industries" number="112" units="3">
        Survey of industry structures and regulations in the transportation, energy, communications, and financial sectors of the American economy. Application of economic analysis to the administrative regulation of prices, investment, service quality, and other managerial decisions. Analysis of regulatory policies and alternatives to economic regulation, including market competition and public ownership.
    </course>
    <course name="Managerial Economics" number="113" units="3">
        Analysis of the theory and practice of decision-making in business firms, utilizing the concepts and techniques of managerial economics. The business decisions to be investigated include pricing policies, internal transfer pricing, and various choices under uncertainty.
    </course>
    <course name="Forecasting for Managerial Decisions" number="114" units="3">
        Theory and analysis of the long-run and short-run forecasts of economic activity.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Economic Analysis and Policy" number="117" units="1-4">
        A variety of topics in economic analysis and policy with emphasis on current problems and research.
    </course>
    <course name="International Trade" number="118" units="3">
        This course will develop models for understanding the economic causes and effects of international trade, will investigate the effects of economic policies that inhibit trade, and will examine the political economy of trade. By integrating the findings of the latest theoretical and empirical research in international economics, this course help students learn how to explore the current political debates in the U.S. and elsewhere regarding the benefits and costs of international trade.
    </course>
    <course name="Strategic Planning" number="119" units="3">
        Class format consists of online instruction, student presentations, and case discussion. This course will cover the study of the concepts and techniques required to design and implement business strategies for private, public, and/or not-for-profit organizations. Students work in teams with a client organization and present their strategic recommendations.
    </course>
    <course name="Intermediate Financial Accounting" number="120A" units="4">
        An intermediate-level course in the theory and practice of financial accounting. The measurement and reporting of the economic effect of events involving working capital and long-term plant assets, investment in securities, intangible assets.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Financial Accounting" number="120B" units="4">
        Continuation of 120A. Sources of long term capital; funds statements, financial analysis, accounting for partnerships, consolidated financial statements, adjustments of accounting data using price indexes; accounting for the financial effects of pension plans; other advanced accounting problems.
    </course>
    <course name="Federal Income Tax Accounting" number="121" units="4">
        Determination of individual and corporation tax liability; influence of federal taxation on economic activity; tax considerations in business and investment decisions.
    </course>
    <course name="Financial Information Analysis" number="122" units="3">
        This course is designed to: 1) develop basic skills in financial statement analysis; 2) teach students to identify the relevant financial data used in a variety of decision contexts, such as equity valuation, forecasting firm-level economic variables, distress prediction and credit analysis; 3) help students appreciate the factors that influence the outcome of the financial reporting process, such as the incentives of reporting parties, regulatory rules, and a firm's competitive environment.
    </course>
    <course name="Auditing" number="126" units="4">
        Concepts and problems in the field of professional verification of financial and related information, including ethical, legal and other professional issues, historical developments, and current concerns.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Accounting" number="127" units="1-4">
        A variety of topics in accounting with emphasis on current problems and research.
    </course>
    <course name="Corporate Finance and Financial Statement Analysis" number="131" units="3">
        This course will cover the principles and practice of business finance. It will focus on project evaluation, capital structure, and corporate governance. Firms' policies toward debt, equity, and dividends are explored. The incentives and conflicts facing managers and owners are also discussed.
    </course>
    <course name="Financial Institutions and Markets" number="132" units="3">
        Organization, behavior, and management of financial institutions. Markets for financial assets and the structure of yields, influence of Federal Reserve System and monetary policy on financial assets and institutions.
    </course>
    <course name="Investments" number="133" units="3">
        Sources of and demand for investment capital, operations of security markets, determination of investment policy, and procedures for analysis of securities.
    </course>
    <course name="Behavioral Finance" number="136F" units="3">
        This course looks at the influence of decision heuristics and biases on investor welfare, financial markets, and corporate decisions. Topics include overconfidence, attribution theory, representative heuristic, availability heuristic, anchoring and adjustment, prospect theory, &quot;Winner's Curse,&quot; speculative bubbles, IPOs, market efficiency, limits of arbitrage, relative mis-pricing of common stocks, the tendency to trade in a highly correlated fashion, investor welfare, and market anomalies.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Finance" number="137" units="1-4">
        A variety of topics in finance with emphasis on current problems and research.
    </course>
    <course name="Production and Operations Management" number="141" units="3">
        A survey of the concepts and methodologies for management control of production and operations systems. Topics include inventory control, material requirements planning for multistage production systems, aggregate planning, scheduling, and production distribution.
    </course>
    <course name="Game Theory and Business Decisions" number="143" units="3">
        This course provides an introduction to game theory and decision analysis. Game theory is concerned with strategic interactions among players (multi-player games), and decision analysis is concerned with making choices under uncertainty (single-player games). Emphasis is placed on applications.
    </course>
    <course name="Planning and Design of E-Business Systems" number="146" units="4">
        Study of principles and procedures of management information systems (MIS) planning, design, and analysis in various organizations. Topics relate to successful and efficient implementation strategies of business systems. &quot;Real-world&quot; projects encompassing all phases of systems analysis, feasibility study, systems design, development, prototyping, testing, documentation, and evaluation. Both technical and managerial issues will be emphasized.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Manufacturing and Information Technology" number="147" units="1-4">
        A variety of topics in manufacturing and information technology with emphasis on current problems and research.
    </course>
    <course name="Information Technology Strategy" number="149A" units="3">
        This course focuses on the use of IT by traditional firms and startups, rather than the details of the technology, with the goals of understanding how IT enables new strategies and how existing strategies adapt to IT innovations. Covers IT technologies used throughout the organization, including mobile communications, systems for online payment, business-to-consumer and business-to-business transactions, customer relationship management, and supply chain management.
    </course>
    <course name="Management of Human Resources" number="151" units="3">
        The designs of systems of rewards, assessment, and manpower development. The interaction of selection, placement, training, personnel evaluation, and career ladders within an on-going organization. Role of the staff manager. Introduction of change. Implications of behavioral research for management problems and policies.
    </course>
    <course name="Negotiation and Conflict Resolution" number="152" units="3">
        The purpose of this course is to understand the theory and processes of negotiation as practiced in a variety of settings. It is designed to be relevant to the broad spectrum of negotiation problems faced by managers and professionals. By focusing on the hehavior of individuals, groups, and organizations in the context of competitive situations, the course will allow students the opportunity to develop negotiation skills experientially in useful analytical frameworks (e.g.- simulations, cases).
    </course>
    <course name="Industrial Relations" number="153" units="3">
        An analysis of manual, white collar, and professional employee relations. Background and functioning of employer and employee organizations. Functioning of labor markets and wage and income security issues. Questions of public policy in labor economics and industrial relations.
    </course>
    <course name="Leadership" number="155" units="3">
        The purpose of this course is for the students to develop understanding of the theory and practice of leadership in various organizational settings. It is designed to allow students the opportunity to develop leadership skills through experiential exercises, behavorial and self-assessments, case studies, class disscussions, and lectures.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Organizational Behavior" number="157" units="1-4">
        A variety of topics in organizational behavior and industrial relations with emphasis on current problems and research.
    </course>
    <course name="Consumer Behavior" number="160" units="3">
        Consumer behavior is the study of how consumers process information, form attitudes and judgments, and make decisions. Its study is critical to understand how consumers think and behave, which is critical for a company wishing to develop a customer focus. Given how different people are, it is amazing how similarly their minds work. Consumer psychology is the systematic study of how consumers perceive information, how they encode it in memory, integrate it with other sources of information, retrieve it from memory, and utilize it to make decisions. It is one of the building blocks of the study of marketing and provides the student with a set of tools with diverse applications.
    </course>
    <course name="Marketing Research: Tools and Techniques for Data Collection and Analysis" number="161" units="3">
        Marketing research objectives; qualitative research, surveys, experiments, sampling, data analysis.
    </course>
    <course name="Brand Management and Strategy" number="162" units="3">
        This course is an introduction to product management in marketing consumer and industrial goods and services. The course will cover analysis of market information, development of product strategy, programming strategy, and implementation.
    </course>
    <course name="Information- and Technology-Based Marketing" number="163" units="3">
        Information technology has allowed firms to gather and process large quantities of information about consumers' choices and reactions to marketing campaigns. However, few firms have the expertise to intelligently act on such information. This course addresses this shortcoming by teaching students how to use customer information to better market to consumers. In addition, the course addresses how information technology affects marketing strategy.
    </course>
    <course name="Integrated Marketing Communication" number="165" units="3">
        Basic concepts and functions of advertising in the economy; consumer motivation; problems in utilizing advertising and measuring its effectiveness.
    </course>
    <course name="Retailing" number="166" units="3">
        History and development of retail management types; geographical structure of retail trade; assortments of goods and services; store management; government regulations.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Marketing" number="167" units="1-4">
        A variety of topics in marketing with emphasis on current problems and research.
    </course>
    <course name="Business Ethics for the 21st Century" number="170" units="2">
        The purpose of this class is to enhance the ability of students to anticipate, critically analyze, and appropriately respond to the wide-range social and ethical issues that challenge managers as well as individuals in their roles as citizens, consumers, investors, and employees. Instruction is based on lectures and case analysis, supplemented by topical and philosophical articles and essays.
    </course>
    <course name="Business in Its Historical Environment" number="C172" units="3">
        This course will examine selected aspects of the history of American business. Included will be discussions of the evolution of the large corporation, the development of modern managerial techniques, and the changing relationship of business, government, and labor. Also listed as American Studies C172.
    </course>
    <course name="Legal Aspects of Management" number="175" units="3">
        An analysis of the law and the legal process, emphasizing the nature and functions of law within the U.S. federal system, followed by a discussion of the legal problems pertaining to contracts and related topics, business association, and the impact of law on economic enterprise.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Business and Public Policy" number="177" units="1-4">
        A variety of topics in business and public policy with emphasis on current problems and research.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to International Business" number="178" units="3">
        A survey involving environmental, economic, political, and social constraints on doing business abroad; effects of overseas business investments on domestic and foreign economies; foreign market analysis and operational strategy of a firm; management problems and development potential of international operations.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Real Estate and Urban Land Economics" number="180" units="3">
        The nature of real property; market analysis; construction cycles; mortgage lending; equity investment; metropolitan growth; urban land use; real property valuation; public policies.
    </course>
    <course name="Valuation of Real Property" number="181" units="3">
        Critical examination of appraisal concepts and methods; the role of value estimates in private land-use and real estate investment decisions and in the implementation of public policies affecting urban development.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Real Estate Finance" number="183" units="3">
        Real estate debt and equity financing; mortgage market structure; effects of credit on demand; equity investment criteria; public policies in real estate finance and urban development.
    </course>
    <course name="Legal Aspects of Real Estate" number="185" units="3">
        The law affecting ownership and use of real property; transfers, titles, development rights, and the regulation thereof in the public interest.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Real Estate Economics and Finance" number="187" units="1-4">
        A variety of topics in real estate economics and finance with emphasis on current problems and research.
    </course>
    <course name="Management in the Public and Not-for-Profit Sectors" number="192A" units="3">
        Economic basis of the public and not-for-profit sectors. Institutional arrangements as they impinge on operations in the public sectors. Emphasis on managerial approaches and tools to use in a nonprofit environment.
    </course>
    <course name="Strategic Corporate Social Responsibility and Consulting Projects" number="192P" units="3">
        Discuss the field of strategic CSR through a series of lectures, guest speakers, and projects. The course will examine best practices used by companies to engage in socially responsible business practices. It will provide students with a flavor of the complex dilemmas one can face in business in trying to do both &quot;good for society&quot; and &quot;well for shareholders.&quot; It looks at CSR from a corporation perspective, and how this supports core business objectives, core competencies, and bottom-line profits.
    </course>
    <course name="Entrepreneurship" number="195A" units="2">
        Principles, theories, and practical aspects of entrepreneurship. Building on functional subject knowledge, explores successes and failures of entrepreneurship. Includes starting new ventures, writing business plans, acquiring other businesses, and making existing enterprises profitable.
    </course>
    <course name="Perspectives on Entrepreneurship" number="195P" units="3">
        This course explores and examines key issues facing entrepreneurs and their businesses. It is intended to provide a broad spectrum of topics across many business disciplines including accounting, finance, marketing, organizational behavior, production/quality, technology, etc. Students will acquire a keen understanding of both the theoretical and real world tools used by today's entrepreneurial business leaders in achieving success in today's global business environment.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Business Administration" number="196" units="1-4">
        Study in various fields of business administration. Topics will vary from year to year and will be announced at the beginning of each semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Study" number="198" units="1-4">
        Organized group study on topics selected by upper division students under the sponsorship and direction of a member of the Haas School of Business faculty.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study and Research" number="199" units="1-4">
        Enrollment restrictions apply.
    </course>
</department>
