<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="BIO ENG" name="Bioengineering">
    <course name="Introduction to Biomedicine for Engineers" number="10" units="4">
        This course is intended for lower division students interested in acquiring a foundation in biomedicine with topics ranging from evolutionary biology to human physiology. The emphasis is on the integration of engineering applications to biology and health. The goal is for undergraduate engineering students to gain sufficient biology and human physiology fundamentals so that they are better prepared to study specialized topics, e.g., biomechanics, imaging, computational biology, tissue engineering, biomonitoring, drug development, robotics, and other topics covered by upper division and graduate courses in UC Berkeley departments of Molecular and Cell Biology, Integrative Biology, Bioengineering, Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Mechanical Engineering, and courses in the UC San Francisco Division of Bioengineering. The specific lecture topics and exercises will include the key aspects of genomics and proteomics as well as topics on plant and animal evolution, stem cell biomedicine, and tissue regeneration and replacement. Medical physiology topics include relevant engineering aspects of human brain, heart, musculoskeletal, and other systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Biotechnology" number="22" units="3">
        This course is intended to introduce students to a variety of fields that fall under the biotechnology umbrella. In general, these fields include medical, microbial, agricultural, animal, and forensic biotechnology. Students in this course will learn the types of biotechnology projects currently being worked on, as well as the techniques and assays used within these projects.
    </course>
    <course name="Biotechnology Laboratory" number="22L" units="2">
        This course is intended to introduce students to a variety of laboratory techniques that are used in current day biotechnology projects. During this course, students will get hands-on molecular and cellular biotechnology experience working with E. coli, Yeast, Human and Mouse Cell Lines, DNA, RNA, and proteins. This is a bioengineering course; the focus of these exercises will be on the critical understanding of biological, biochemical, or physical mechanisms, and theories of different experiemental methods, techniques, and instrumentation used. Second, students leaving this class should understand how to address a critical biological question and design experiments in a quantitative manner.
    </course>
    <course name="Aspects of Bioengineering" number="24" units="1">
        This introductory seminar is designed to give freshmen and sophomores a glimpse of a broad selection of bioengineering research that is currently underway at Berkeley and UCSF. The goal is to help students gain a feeling for the breadth of interesting problems in bioengineering and also the variety of ways that engineering principles can be applied to biological and medical problems. A series of one-hour seminars will be presented by researchers, professors, and doctors on their particular research areas.
    </course>
    <course name="Careers in Biotechnology" number="25" units="1">
        This introductory seminar is designed to give freshmen and sophomores an opportunity to explore specialties related to engineering in the pharmaceutical/biotech field. A series of one-hour seminars will be presented by industry professionals, professors, and researchers. Topics may include biotechnology and pharmaceutical manufacturing; process and control engineering; drug inspection process; research and development; compliance and validation; construction process for a GMP facility; project management; and engineered solutions to environmental challenges. This course is of interest to students in all areas of engineering and biology, including industrial engineering and manufacturing, chemical engineering, and bioengineering.
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman and Sophomore Seminar" number="39" units="2-4">
        Freshman and sophomore seminars offer lower division students the opportunity to explore an intellectual topic with a faculty member and a group of peers in a small seminar setting. These seminars are offered in all campus departments; topics vary from department to department and from semester to semester. Enrollment limits are set by the faculty, but the suggested limit is 25.
    </course>
    <course name="Sophomore Seminar" number="84" units="1,2">
        Sophomore seminars are small interactive courses offered by faculty members in departments all across the campus. Sophomore seminars offer opportunity for close, regular intellectual contact between faculty members and students in the crucial second year. The topics vary from department to department and semester to semester. Enrollment limited to 15 sophomores.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Group Studies" number="98" units="1-4">
        Organized group study on various topics under the sponsorship of a member of the Bioengineering faculty.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study and Research" number="99" units="1-4">
        Supervised independent study for lower division students.
    </course>
    <course name="Ethics in Science and Engineering" number="100" units="3">
        The goal of this semester course is to present the issues of professional conduct in the practice of engineering, research, publication, public and private disclosures, and in managing professional and financial conflicts. The method is through historical didactic presentations, case studies, presentations of methods for problem solving in ethical matters, and classroom debates on contemporary ethical issues. The faculty will be drawn from national experts and faculty from religious studies, journalism, and law from the UC Berkeley campus.
    </course>
    <course name="Instrumentation in Biology and Medicine" number="101" units="4">
        This course teaches the fundamental principles underlying modern instrumentation used in biology and medicine. Organized around three classes of instruments--bioelectronics, optical microscopy, and medical imaging--the course takes an integrative approach to measurement theory and practice by presenting and analyzing example instruments currently used for biological and medical research. For each instrument, students will learn the fundamentals of operation, methods of control, mechanisms of contrast, devices for detection, and methods for signal processing and error estimation. Current biological questions and medical problems investigated with each type of instrument will be discussed.
    </course>
    <course name="Biomechanics" number="102" units="4">
        This course introduces, develops, and applies scaling laws and the methods of continuum mechanics to tissue-level biomechanical phenomena. It is intended for upper level undergraduate students who have been exposed to vectors and tensors, differential equations, and undergraduate courses in either fluids or transport, and molecular biology. Topics include biosolid and biofluid mechanics; elastic (time-independent), viscoelastic, and poroelastic (time-dependent) behavior of tissues; continuum and microstructural models; constitutive laws; material properties of tissues; experimental methods--macroscopic rheology.
    </course>
    <course name="Biological Transport Phenomena" number="104" units="4">
        The transport of mass, momentum, and energy is critical to the function of living systems. Changes in such transport processes often lead to pathological conditions. Transport phenomena are also crucial to the viability of biomedical devices that are invented as a replacement or assist for biological tissues or organs. Biological transport phenomena are present in a wide range of scales from molecular to cellular to whole organ and organism. Similarly they span a wide range of time scales from minutes to the lifetime of living organisms. This course develops and applies scaling laws and the methods of continuum mechanics to biological transport phenomena over a range of length and time scales. The course is intended for undergraduate students who have taken a course in differential equations and an introductory course in physics. Background in biology and physiology is useful but not assumed. Example application areas include biomolecular transport in biological tissues, living organs, and in microfabricated biomedical microdevices.
    </course>
    <course name="Thermodynamics and Biothermodynamics" number="C105B" units="3">
        This course introduces the basic principles of thermodynamics and their application to a variety of biological processes and systems. Some coverage of conventional engineering applications is also included. Also listed as Mechanical Engineering C105B.
    </course>
    <course name="Biomedical Physiology for Engineers" number="110" units="4">
        This course introduces students to the physiology of human organ systems, with an emphasis on quantitative problem solving, engineering-style modeling, and applications to clinical medicine. The course will begin with a review of basic principles of cellular physiology, including membrane transport and electrophysiology, and then take a system-by-system approach to the physiology of various organ systems, including the cardiovascular, pulmonary, renal, and endocrine systems. Throughout, the course will feature extensive discussions of clinical conditions associated with dysfunction in specific physiological processes as well as the role of medical devices and prostheses. This course is geared towards upper-division bioengineering students who wish to solidify their foundation in physiology, especially in preparation for a career in clinical medicine or the biomedical device industry.
    </course>
    <course name="Molecular Cell Biomechanics" number="112" units="4">
        This course develops and applies scaling laws and the methods of continuum and statistical mechanics to biomechanical phenomena over a range of length scales, from molecular to cellular levels. It is intended for senior undergraduate students who have been exposed to differential equations, mechanics, and certain aspects of modern biology.
    </course>
    <course name="Cell Biology Laboratory for Engineers" number="115" units="4">
        The structural and functional characteristics of musculoskeletal tissues (e.g., bone, tendon, cartilage) are altered by cells in response to loading, injury, nutrition, and other factors. A contemporary understanding of the structural form, function and longevity includes knowledge of tissue ultra structure, composition of matrix, and cell function. Students will be introduced to cellular and molecular biology and biochemistry techniques as applied to musculoskeletal tissues including histology, image analysis, protein quantification, gene analysis and expression, and cell culture. By applying these techniques to structural tissues in the laboratory, students can learn the reliability and limitations of these tools.
    </course>
    <course name="Cell and Tissue Engineering" number="116" units="4">
        Introduction to tissue engineering, analysis of cellular process, and cell engineering. Topics include bioreactor and mass transport, transplantation, artifical tissues, cell-matrix interaction, cell migration and cell mechanics, cell proliferation, stem cells, and cell manipulation.
    </course>
    <course name="Structural Aspects of Biomaterials" number="C117" units="4">
        This course covers the structure and mechanical functions of load bearing tissues and their replacements. Natural and synthetic load-bearing biomaterials for clinical applications are reviewed. Biocompatibility of biomaterials and host response to structural implants are examined. Quantitative treatment of biomechanical issues and constitutive relationships of tissues are covered in order to design biomaterial replacements for structural function. Material selection for load bearing applications including reconstructive surgery, orthopedics, dentistry, and cardiology are addressed. Mechanical design for longevity including topics of fatigue, wear, and fracture are reviewed. Case studies that examine failures of devices are presented. This course includes a teaching/design laboratory component that involves design analysis of medical devices and outreach teaching to the public community. Several problem-based projects are utilized throughout the semester for design analysis. In addition to technical content, this course involves rigorous technical writing assignments, oral communication skill development and teamwork. Also listed as Mechanical Engineering C117.
    </course>
    <course name="Biological Performance of Materials" number="C118" units="4">
        This course is intended to give students the opportunity to expand their knowledge of topics related to biomedical materials selection and design. Structure-property relationships of biomedical materials and their interaction with biological systems will be addressed. Applications of the concepts developed include blood-materials compatibility, biomimetic materials, hard and soft tissue-materials interactions, drug delivery, tissue engineering, and biotechnology. Also listed as Materials Science and Engineering C118.
    </course>
    <course name="Orthopedic Biomechanics" number="C119" units="4">
        Students will learn the application of engineering concepts including statics, dynamics, optimization theory, composite beam theory, beam-on-elastic foundation theory, Hertz contact theory and materials behavior. Topics will include forces and moments acting on human joints; composition and mechanical behavior of orthopedic biomaterials; design/analysis of artificial joint, spine, and fracture fixation prostheses; musculoskeletal tissues including bone, cartilage, tendon, ligament, and muscle; osteoporosis and fracture-risk predication of bones; and bone adaptation. Students will be challenged in a MATLAB-based project to integrate the course material in an attempt to gain insight into contemporary design/analysis/problems. Also listed as Mechanical Engineering C176.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Micro and Nanobiotechnology: BioMEMS" number="121" units="3">
        Biophysical and chemical principles of biomedical microelectromechanical systems (bioMEMS) for the measurement of biological phenomena and clinical applications. Micro- and nano-scale devices for the manipulation of cells and biomolecules. Topics include solid-state transducers, optical transducers, electrochemical transducers, biomedical microelectronics, microfluidics, and hybrid integration of microfabrication technology.
    </course>
    <course name="BioMems and BioNanotechnology Laboratory" number="121L" units="4">
        Hands-on project experience in applying microfabrication techniques to problems in biotechnology using the latest micro- and nano-technological tools. Experimental design and analysis of micro- and nano-scale device interfaces. Students will give poster sessions and oral presentations on their results.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Robotics" number="C125" units="4">
        An introduction to the kinematics, dynamics, and control of robot manipulators, robotic vision, and sensing. The course covers forward and inverse kinematics of serial chain manipulators, the manipulator Jacobian, force relations, dynamics, and control. It presents elementary principles on proximity, tactile, and force sensing, vision sensors, camera calibration, stereo construction, and motion detection. The course concludes with current applications of robotics in active perception, medical robotics, and other areas. Also listed as Electrical Engineering C125.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Computational Molecular and Cell Biology" number="131" units="4">
        Topics include computational approaches and techniques to gene structure and finding, sequence alignment using dynamic programming, protein folding and structure prediction, protein-drug interactions, genetic and biochemical pathways and networks, and microarray analysis. Various case studies in these areas are reviewed and web-based computational biology tools will be used by students. Computational biology research connections to biotechnology will be explored.
    </course>
    <course name="Statistics for Bioinformatics" number="C141" units="4">
        Study of bioinformatics problems such as DNA pattern finding, gene expression data analysis, molecular evolution models, and biomolecular sequence database searching. Introduction of the necessary probability and statistics: events, (conditional) probability, random variables, estimation, testing, and linear regression. Also listed as Statistics C141.
    </course>
    <course name="Programming and Algorithm Design for Computational Biology and Genomics Applications" number="142" units="4">
        This course will introduce students to structured software development and select principles of computer science with applications in computational biology and allied disciplines. The principle language used for instruction will be Java with a course module on Perl. Examples and tutorials will draw from problems in computational biology. The course will require one significant programming project, preferably biologically oriented.
    </course>
    <course name="Computational Methods in Biology" number="143" units="4">
        An introduction to biophysical simulation methods and algorithms, including molecular dynamics, Monte Carlo, mathematical optimization, and &quot;non-algorithmic&quot; computation such as neural networks. Various case studies in applying these areas in the areas of protein folding, protein structure prediction, drug docking, and enzymatics will be covered. Core Specialization: Core B (Informatics and Genomics); Core D (Computational Biology); BioE Content: Biological.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Protein Informatics" number="144" units="4">
        This course will introduce students to the fundamentals of molecular biology and to the bioinformatics tools and databases used for the prediction of protein function and structure. It is designed to impart both a theoretical understanding of popular computational methods and practical hands-on experience with protein sequence analysis methods applied to real data.
    </course>
    <course name="Protein Informatics Laboratory" number="144L" units="2">
        This course is intended to introduce students to a variety of bioinformatics techniques that are used to predict protein function and structure. It is designed to be taken concurrently with 144 (which provides the theoretical foundations for the methods used in the laboratory class), although students can petition to take this laboratory course separately. No programming is performed in this class, and no prior programming experience is required.
    </course>
    <course name="Introductory Electronic Transducers Laboratory" number="C145L" units="3">
        Laboratory exercises exploring a variety of electronic transducers for measuring physical quantities such as temperature, force, displacement, sound, light, ionic potential; the use of circuits for low-level differential amplification and analog signal processing; and the use of microcomputers for digital sampling and display. Lectures cover principles explored in the laboratory exercises; construction, response and signal to noise of electronic transducers and actuators; and design of circuits for sensing and controlling physical quantities. Also listed as Electrical Engineering C145L.
    </course>
    <course name="Introductory Microcomputer Interfacing Laboratory" number="C145M" units="3">
        Laboratory exercises constructing basic interfacing circuits and writing 20-100 line C programs for data acquisition, storage, analysis, display, and control. Use of the IBM PC with microprogrammable digital counter/timer, parallel I/O port. Circuit components include anti-aliasing filters, the S/H amplifier, A/D and D/A converters. Exercises include effects of aliasing in periodic sampling, fast Fourier transforms of basic waveforms, the use of the Hanning filter for leakage reduction, Fourier analysis of the human voice, digital filters, and control using Fourier deconvolution. Lectures cover principles explored in the lab exercises and design of microcomputer-based systems for data acquisitions, analysis and control. Also listed as Electrical Engineering C145M.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Computational Biology and Genomics" number="C146" units="4">
        Instruction and discussion of topics in genomics and computational biology. Working from evolutionary concepts, the course will cover principles and application of molecular sequence comparison, genome sequencing and functional annotation, and phylogenetic analysis. Also listed as Molecular and Cell Biology C146 and Plant and Microbial Biology C146.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction of Bionanoscience and Bionanotechnology" number="150" units="4">
        This course is intended for the bioengineering or engineering undergraduate students interested in acquiring a background in recent development of bio-nanomaterials and bio-nanotechnology. The emphasis of the class is to understand the properties of biological basis building blocks, their assembly principles in nature, and their application to build functional materials and devices. The goal is for the bioengineering students to gain sufficient chemical and physical aspects of biological materials through the case study of spider webs, silks, sea shells, diatoms, bones, and teeth, as well as recently developed self-assembled nanostructures inspired by nature. The course covers the structures and properties of amino acids, DNAs, sugars, lipids, and their natural and artifical assembly structures. It also covers nanoscale inorganic materials used to develop nano medicines, bio-imaging, bio-sensors, bioelectronics, and machinery.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Bioastronautics" number="155" units="4">
        This course aims to bring undergraduate students into the world of space science related research including bioastronautics and high altitude human physiology. Students will gain a strong knowledge base of specific topics in bioastronautics, an introduction to research methods, and will learn how to structure a research team. Additionally, students will develop leadership, management, teamwork, and communication skills. The topics to be covered include history of manned space flight, the space environment, Mars and lunar environments, space flight and life support systems, space suit technology, human physiological responses to space flight, countermeasures to space deconditioning, and space medicine.
    </course>
    <course name="Optics and Microscopy" number="164" units="4">
        This course teaches fundamental principles of optics and examines contemporary methods of optical microscopy for cells and molecules. Students will learn how to design simple optical systems, calculate system performance, and apply imaging techniques including transmission, reflection, phase, and fluorescence microscopy to investigate biological samples. The capabilities of optical microscopy will be compared with complementary techniques including electron microscopy, coherence tomography, and atomic force microscopy. Students will also be responsible for researching their final project outside of class and presenting a specific application of modern microscopy to biological research as part of an end-of-semester project.
    </course>
    <course name="Image Processing and Reconstruction Tomography" number="C165" units="4">
        Linear systems and Fourier transforms in two and three dimensions. Basic image processing. Theory and algorithms for image reconstruction from projections. Physics of imaging systems including magnetic resonance, X-ray tomography, positron emission tomography, ultrasound, and biomagnetic imaging. Data analysis including hypothesis testing, parameter estimation by least squares, and compartmental kinetic modelling. Field trips to medical imaging laboratories. Also listed as Electrical Engineering C145B.
    </course>
    <course name="Practical Light Microscopy" number="168L" units="3">
        This laboratory course is designed for students interested in obtaining practical hands-on training in optical imaging and instrumentation. Using a combination of lenses, cameras, and data acquisition equipment, students will construct simple light microscopes that introduce basic concepts and limitations important in biomedical optical imaging. Topics include compound microscopes, Kohler illumination, Rayleigh two-point resolution, image contrast including dark-field and fluorescence microscopy, and specialized techniques such as fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP). Intended for students in both engineering and the sciences, this course will emphasize applied aspects of optical imaging and provide a base of practical skill and reference material that students can leverage in their own research or in industry.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Biomechanics and Tissue Engineering" number="190A" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Bioinformatics and Genomics" number="190B" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Micromachines and Robotics" number="190C" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Computational Bioengineering" number="190D" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Neural and Sensory Systems Bioengineering" number="190E" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Biomedical Imaging and Signal Processing" number="190F" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Radiological Bioengineering" number="190G" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Biomedical Systems Engineering" number="190H" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Junior and Senior Seminar" number="191" units="1-3">
        Junior and senior seminars are small interactive courses offered by faculty members in Bioengineering. These seminars offer opportunity for close, regular intellectual contact between faculty members and students. The topics vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Honors Undergraduate Research" number="H194" units="3,4">
        Supervised research. Students who have completed 3 or more upper division courses may pursue original research under the direction of one of the members of the staff. May be taken a second time for credit only. A final report or presentation is required. A maximum of 4 units of this course may be used to fulfill the research or technical elective requirement or in the Bioengineering program.
    </course>
    <course name="Undergraduate Design Research" number="196" units="4">
        Supervised research. This course will satisfy the Senior Bioengineering Design project requirement. Students with junior or senior status may pursue research under the direction of one of the members of the staff. May be taken a second time for credit only. A final report or presentation is required.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study for Advanced Undergraduates" number="198" units="1-4">
        Group study of a selected topic or topics in bioengineering, usually relating to new developments.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study" number="199" units="1-4">
        Supervised independent study.
    </course>
    <course name="The Graduate Group Introductory Seminar" number="200" units="1">
        An introduction to research in bioengineering including specific case studies and organization of this rapidly expanding and diverse field.
    </course>
    <course name="Cell Mechanics and the Cytoskeleton" number="210" units="3">
        This course explores emerging biophysical descriptions of the cell based on molecular details of the cytoskeleton and its interactions with the cellular microenvironment. Through lectures, discussions, and reading of the research literature, students will learn about current questions facing the field of cell mechanics and its connections with health and disease. Fundamental biology of the cytoskeleton and associated molecular motors will be discussed in the context of cell motility, shape change, and mechanotransduction. Modern techniques for quantifying mechanical properties of the cell and its structural components, including optical trapping, magnetic tweezers, atomic force microscopy, and traction-force microscopy will be presented, and recent models of cell mechanics and their predictions will be discussed and debated.
    </course>
    <course name="Cell and Tissue Mechanotransduction" number="211" units="3">
        This course will focus on biophysical and bioengineering aspects of mechanotransduction, the process through which living cells sense and respond to their mechanical environment. Students will learn how mechanical inputs to cells influence both subcellular biochemistry and whole-cell behavior. They will also study newly-engineered technologies for force manipulation and measurement in living cells, and synthetic strategies to control the mechanics and chemistry of the extracellular matrix. Finally, students will learn about the role of mechanotransduction in selected human organ systems and how these mechanisms may go awry in the setting of the disease. Instruction will feature lectures, discussions, analysis of relevant research papers, assembly of a literature review and a research proposal, and an oral presentation.
    </course>
    <course name="Heat and Mass Transport in Biomedical Engineering" number="C212" units="3">
        Fundamental processes of heat and mass transport in biological systems; organic molecules, cells, biological organs, whole animals. Derivation of mathematical models and discussion of experimental procedures. Applications to biomedical engineering. Also listed as Mechanical Engineering C212.
    </course>
    <course name="Fluid Mechanics of Biological Systems" number="C213" units="3">
        Fluid mechanical aspects of various physiological systems, the circulatory, respiratory, and renal systems. Motion in large and small blood vessels. Pulsatile and peristaltic flows. Other biofluidmechanical flows: the ear, eye, etc. Instrumentation for fluid measurements in biological systems and for medical diagnosis and applications. Artifical devices for replacement of organs and/or functions, e.g. blood oxygenators, kidney dialysis machines, artifical hearts/circulatory assist devices. Also listed as Mechanical Engineering C213.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Tissue Mechanics" number="C214" units="3">
        The goal of this course is to provide a foundation for characterizing and understanding the mechanical behavior of load-bearing tissues. A variety of mechanics topics will be introduced, including anisotropic elasticity and failure, cellular solid theory, biphasic theory, and quasi-linear viscoelasticity (QLV) theory. Building from this theoretical basis, we will explore the constitutive behavior of a wide variety of biological tissues. After taking this course, students should have sufficient background to independently study the mechanical behavior of most biological tissues. Formal discussion section will include a seminar series with external speakers. Also listed as Mechanical Engineering C214.
    </course>
    <course name="Models of Cell Mechanics: Dynamics of the Cytoskeleton and Nucleus" number="215" units="3">
        The field of cell mechanics has recently undergone rapid development with particular attention to the dynamics of the cytoskeleton as well as its interactions with the extracellular matrix and how this interaction may cause changes in cell architecture, consequently leading to functional adaptation or pathological conditions. A wide range of models exist for cytoskeletal mechanics, ranging from continuum models for cell deformation to actin filament-based models for cell mobility. Numerous experimental techniques have also been established to quantify the cytoskeletal mechanics via perturbing the cell by exerting some sort of deformation and examining the static and dynamic response of the cell. These experimental observations along with theoretical approaches to the cell have given rise to several theories for describing the mechanics of living cells, modeling the cytoskeleton as a simple mechanical elastic, viscoelastic, or poroviscoelastic continuum, porous gel or soft glassy material, tensegrity network incorporating discrete structural elements that bear compression.
    </course>
    <course name="Macromolecular Science in Biotechnology and Medicine" number="C216" units="4">
        Overview of the problems associated with the selection and function of polymers used in biotechnology and medicine. Principles of polymer science, polymer synthesis, and structure-property-performance relationships of polymers. Particular emphasis is placed on the performance of polymers in biological environments. Interactions between macromolecular and biological systems for therapy and diagnosis. Specific applications will include drug delivery, gene therapy, tissue engineering, and surface engineering. Also listed as Materials Science and Engineering C216.
    </course>
    <course name="Biomimetic Engineering -- Engineering from Biology" number="C217" units="3">
        Study of nature's solutions to specific problems with the aim of determining appropriate engineering analogs. Morphology, scaling, and design in organisms applied to engineering structures. Mechanical principles in nature and their application to engineering devices. Mechanical behavior of biological materials as governed by underlying microstructure, with the potential for synthesis into engineered materials. Trade-offs between redundancy and efficiency. Students will work in teams on projects where they will take examples of designs, concepts, and models from biology and determine their potential in specific engineering applications. Also listed as Integrative Biology C217 and Mechanical Engineering C217.
    </course>
    <course name="Stem Cells and Directed Organogenesis" number="C218" units="3">
        This course will provide an overview of basic and applied embryonic stem cell (ESC) biology. Topics will include early embryonic development, ESC laboratory methods, biomaterials for directed differentiation and other stem cell manipulations, and clinical uses of stem cells. Also listed as Molecular and Cell Biology C237.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Micro and Nanobiotechnology: BioMEMS" number="221" units="3">
        Biophysical and chemical principles of biomedical microelectromechanical systems (bioMEMS) for the measurement of biological phenomena and clinical applications. Micro- and nano-scale devices for the manipulation of cells and biomolecules. Topics include solid-state transducers, optical transducers, electrochemical transducers, biomedical microelectronics, microfluidics, and hybrid integration of microfabrication technology.
    </course>
    <course name="Polymer Engineering" number="C223" units="3">
        A survey of the structure and mechanical properties of advanced engineering polymers. Topics include rubber elasticity, viscoelasticity, mechanical properties, yielding, deformation, and fracture mechanisms of various classes of polymers. The course will discuss degradation schemes of polymers and long-term performance issues. The class will include polymer applications in bioengineering and medicine. Also listed as Mechanical Engineering C223.
    </course>
    <course name="Implications and Applications of Synthetic Biology" number="C230" units="3">
        Explore strategies for maximizing the economic and societal benefits of synthetic biology and minimizing the risks; create &quot;seedlings&quot; for future research projects in synthetic biology at UC Berkeley; increase multidisciplinary collaborations at UC Berkeley on synthetic biology; and introduce students to a wide perspective of SB projects and innovators as well as policy, legal, and ethical experts. Also listed as Chemical Engineering C295L.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Computational Molecular and Cellular Biology" number="231" units="4">
        Topics include computational approaches and techniques to gene structure and finding, sequence alignment using dynamic programming, protein folding and structure prediction, protein-drug interactions, genetic and biochemical pathways and networks, and microarray analysis. Various case studies in these areas are reviewed and web-based computational biology tools will be used by students. Computational biology research connections to biotechnology will be explored. Bioengineering content: fulfills biological and statistical requirement. Bioengineering Breadth, Core B (Informatics and Genomics) and Core D (Computational Biology).
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Computational Biology and Evolution" number="240" units="3">
        This class is aimed at graduate students from both the life sciences and engineering/mathematics. In addition to learning about bioinformatics methods in computational biology and evolution, we will focus on research and (oral and written) presentation skills and on the development of critical and analytical skills. Readings for the class will be selected from the best papers in the field over the past 20 years, with a focus on review papers and papers presenting important methods.
    </course>
    <course name="Probabilistic Modeling in Computational Biology" number="241" units="3">
        The course is designed to be a self-contained, advanced introduction to the techniques used in designing and implementing probabilistic models for bioinformatics, genomics, and other applications in computational biology and sequence analysis. A high mathematical facility is assumed: this is a course for graduate students (and advanced undergraduates) who are interested in designing their own, novel probabilistic models and approaches, rather than for the casual user of bioinformatics software.
    </course>
    <course name="Computational Methods in Biology" number="243" units="4">
        An introduction to biophysical simulation methods and algorithms, including molecular dynamics, Monte Carlo, mathematical optimization, and &quot;non-algorithmic&quot; computation such as neural networks. Various case studies in applying these areas in the areas of protein folding, protein structure prediction, drug docking, and enzymatics will be covered. Core Specialization: Core B (Informatics and Genomics); Core D (Computational Biology); Bioengineering Content: Biological.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Protein Informatics" number="244" units="4">
        This course will introduce students to the fundamentals of molecular biology and to the bioinformatics tools and databases used for the prediction of protein function and structure. It is designed to impart both a theoretical understanding of popular computational methods and practical hands-on experience with protein sequence analysis methods applied to real data.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Computational Biology and Genomics" number="C246" units="4">
        Instruction and discussion of topics in genomics and computational biology. Working from evolutionary concepts, the course will cover principles and application of molecular sequence comparison, genome sequencing and functional annotation, and phylogenetic analysis. Also listed as Plant and Microbial Biology C246.
    </course>
    <course name="Principles of Magnetic Resonance Imaging" number="265" units="3">
        Fundamentals of MRI including signal-to-noise ratio, resolution, and contrast as dictated by physics, pulse sequences, and instrumentation. Image reconstruction via 2D FFT methods. Fast imaging reconstruction via convolution-back projection and gridding methods and FFTs. Hardware for modern MRI scanners including main field, gradient fields, RF coils, and shim supplies. Software for MRI including imaging methods such as 2D FT, RARE, SSFP, spiral and echo planar imaging methods. Fundamental tradeoffs of tailoring hardware and pulse sequences to specific applications. The modern MRI &quot;toolbox&quot; will be introduced, including selecting a slice or volume, fast imaging methods to avoid image artifacts due to physiologic motion, and methods for functional imaging. The fundamentals of MRI image artifacts (motion, magnetic susceptibility variations, RF field variations) will also be covered. The last part of the class will present emerging research opportunities and concomitant engineering research challenges including high-field MRI, hyperpolarization methods, small animal MRI, cardiac MRI, stem cell tracking with MRI, and fMRI.
    </course>
    <course name="Occupational Biomechanics" number="C279" units="4">
        Overview of ergonomics and occupational biomechanics. Course covers pathophysiology and risk factors of upper extremity and back loading at work, measurement of force and posture, models for risk assessment, anthropometry applied to task and workstation design, tool design, and structure of successful ergonomics programs. Students will conduct a detailed job analysis and design a workplace intervention. Also listed as Public Health C269C.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Bioengineering" number="290" units="1-3">
        This course covers current topics of research interest in bioengineering. The course content may vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Biomechanics and Tissue Engineering" number="290A" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Bioinformatics and Genomics" number="290B" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Fluid Mechanics" number="C290C" units="1,2">
        Lectures on special topics which will be announced at the beginning of each semester that the course is offered. Topics may include transport and mixing, geophysical fluid dynamics, bio-fluid dynamics, oceanography, free surface flows, non Newtonian fluid mechanics, among other possibilities. Also listed as Environ Sci, Policy, and Management C291, Physics C290I, Mathematics C290C, Chemical Engineering C295M, Nuclear Engineering C290F, Civil and Environmental Engineering C290K, and Mechanical Engineering C298A.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Computational Bioengineering" number="290D" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Biomedical Imaging and Signal Processing" number="290F" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Biomedical Systems Engineering" number="290H" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Special Topics in Bioengineering" number="290I" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Group Studies, Seminars, or Group Research" number="298" units="1-8">
        Advanced studies in various subjects through special seminars on topics to be selected each year. Informal group studies of special problems, group participation in comprehensive design problems, or group research on complete problems for analysis and experimentation.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study or Research" number="299" units="1-12">
        Investigations of advanced problems in bioengineering.
    </course>
    <course name="Teaching Techniques for Bioengineering" number="301" units="1">
        Weekly seminars and discussions of effective teaching techniques. Use of educational objectives, alternative forms of instruction, and special techniques for teaching key concepts and techniques in bioengineering. Course is intended to orient new graduate student instructors to teaching in the Bioengineering department at Berkeley.
    </course>
</department>
