<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="EL ENG" name="Electrical Engineering">
    <course name="Structure and Interpretation of Systems and Signals" number="20N" units="4">
        Mathematical modeling of signals and systems. Continous and discrete signals, with applications to audio, images, video, communications, and control. State-based models, beginning with automata and evolving to LTI systems. Frequency domain models for signals and frequency response for systems, and sampling of continuous-time signals. A Matlab-based laboratory is an integral part of the course.
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman Seminar" number="24" units="1">
        The Freshman Seminar Program has been designed to provide new students with the opportunity to explore an intellectual topic with a faculty member in a small seminar setting. Freshman seminars are offered in all campus departments, and topics may vary from department to department and semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Microelectronic Circuits" number="40" units="4">
        Fundamental circuit concepts and analysis techniques in the context of digital electronic circuits. Transient analysis of CMOS logic gates; basic integrated-circuit technology and layout.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Digital Electronics" number="42" units="3">
        This course serves as an introduction to the principles of electrical engineering, starting from the basic concepts of voltage and current and circuit elements of resistors, capacitors, and inductors. Circuit analysis is taught using Kirchhoff's voltage and current laws with Thevenin and Norton equivalents. Operational amplifiers with feedback are introduced as basic building blocks for amplication and filtering. Semiconductor devices including diodes and MOSFETS and their IV characteristics are covered. Applications of diodes for rectification, and design of MOSFETs in common source amplifiers are taught. Digital logic gates and design using CMOS as well as simple flip-flops are introduced. Speed and scaling issues for CMOS are considered. The course includes as motivating examples designs of high level applications including logic circuits, amplifiers, power supplies, and communication links.
    </course>
    <course name="Introductory Electronics Laboratory" number="43" units="1">
        Using and understanding electronics laboratory equipment such as oscilloscope, power supplies, function generator, multimeter, curve-tracer, and RLC-meter. Includes a term project of constructing and testing a robot or other appropriate electromechanical device.
    </course>
    <course name="Sophomore Seminar" number="84" units="1,2">
        Sophomore seminars are small interactive courses offered by faculty members in departments all across the campus. Sophomore seminars offer opportunity for close, regular intellectual contact between faculty members and students in the crucial second year. The topics vary from department to department and semester to semester. Enrollment limited to 15 sophomores.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study for Undergraduates" number="98" units="1-4">
        Group study of selected topics in electrical engineering, usually relating to new developments.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study and Research for Undergraduates" number="99" units="1-4">
        Supervised independent study and research for students with fewer than 60 units completed.
    </course>
    <course name="Electronic Techniques for Engineering" number="100" units="4">
        This course serves as an introduction to the principles of electrical engineering, starting from the basic concepts of voltage and current and circuit elements of resistors, capacitors, and inductors. Circuit analysis is taught using Kirchhoff's voltage and current laws with Thevenin and Norton equivalents. Operational amplifiers with feedback are introduced as basic building blocks for amplication and filtering. Semiconductor devices including diodes and MOSFETS and their IV characteristics are covered. Applications of diodes for rectification, and design of MOSFETs in common source amplifiers are taught. Digital logic gates and design using CMOS as well as simple flip-flops are introduced. Speed and scaling issues for CMOS are considered. The course includes as motivating examples designs of high level applications including logic circuits, amplifiers, power supplies, and communication links.
    </course>
    <course name="Microelectronic Devices and Circuits" number="105" units="4">
        This course covers the fundamental circuit and device concepts needed to understand analog integrated circuits. After an overview of the basic properties of semiconductors, the p-n junction and MOS capacitors are described and the MOSFET is modeled as a large-signal device. Two port small-signal amplifiers and their realization using single stage and multistage CMOS building blocks are discussed. Sinusoidal steady-state signals are introduced and the techniques of phasor analysis are developed, including impedance and the magnitude and phase response of linear circuits. The frequency responses of single and multi-stage amplifiers are analyzed. Differential amplifiers are introduced.
    </course>
    <course name="Electromagnetic Fields and Waves" number="117" units="4">
        Review of static electric and magnetic fields and applications; Maxwell's equations; transmission lines; propagation and reflection of plane waves; introduction to guided waves, microwave networks, and radiation and antennas. Minilabs on statics, transmission lines, and waves.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Optical Communication Systems and Networks" number="118" units="3">
        Basic principles of digital and analog optical communications and optical networks. Emphasis is on principles of optical links, including channel capacity, basic limitations due to noise processes, and bit error rate requirements. Optical amplification, the detector-receiver, optical fiber and free-space propagation, the transmitter, and modulation schemes. Coherent and incoherent communications and network systems. Basic optical Fourier transform signal processing techniques.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Optical Engineering" number="119" units="3">
        Fundamental principles of optical systems. Geometrical optics and aberration theory. Stops and apertures, prisms, and mirrors. Diffraction and interference. Optical materials and coatings. Radiometry and photometry. Basic optical devices and the human eye. The design of optical systems. Lasers, fiber optics, and holography.
    </course>
    <course name="Signals and Systems" number="120" units="4">
        Continuous and discrete-time transform analysis techniques with illustrative applications. Linear and time-invariant systems, transfer functions. Fourier series, Fourier transform, Laplace and Z-transforms. Sampling and reconstruction. Solution of differential and difference equations using transforms. Frequency response, Bode plots, stability analysis. Illustrated by analysis of communication systems and feedback control systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Digital Communication Systems" number="121" units="4">
        Introduction to the basic principles of the design and analysis of modern digital communication systems. Topics include source coding, channel coding, baseband and passband modulation techniques, receiver design, and channel equalization. Applications to design of digital telephone modems, compact disks, and digital wireless communication systems. Concepts illustrated by a sequence of MATLAB exercises.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Communication Networks" number="122" units="4">
        This course is an introduction to the design and implementation of computer networks. We will focus on the concepts and fundamental design principles that have contributed to the Internet's scalability and robustness and survey the underlying technologies--e.g., Ethernet, 802.11, DSL, optical links--that have led to the Internet's phenomenal success. Topics include layering, congestion/flow/error control, routing, addressing, multicast, packet scheduling, switching, internetworking, network security, and networking/programming interfaces.
    </course>
    <course name="Digital Signal Processing" number="123" units="4">
        Discrete time signals and systems: Fourier and Z transforms, DFT, 2-dimensional versions. Digital signal processing topics: flow graphs, realizations, FFT, chirp-Z algorithms, Hilbert transform relations, quantization effects, linear prediction. Digital filter design methods: windowing, frequency sampling, S-to-Z methods, frequency-transformation methods, optimization methods, 2-dimensional filter design.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Embedded Systems" number="124" units="4">
        This course introduces students to the basics of models, analysis tools, and control for embedded systems operating in real time. Students learn how to combine physical processes with computation. Topics include models of computation, control, analysis and verification, interfacing with the physical world, mapping to platforms, and distributed embedded systems. The course has a strong laboratory component, with emphasis on a semester-long sequence of projects.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Robotics" number="C125" units="4">
        An introduction to the kinematics, dynamics, and control of robot manipulators, robotic vision, and sensing. The course covers forward and inverse kinematics of serial chain manipulators, the manipulator Jacobian, force relations, dynamics, and control. It presents elementary principles on proximity, tactile, and force sensing, vision sensors, camera calibration, stereo construction, and motion detection. The course concludes with current applications of robotics in active perception, medical robotics, and other areas. Also listed as Bioengineering C125.
    </course>
    <course name="Probability and Random Processes" number="126" units="4">
        This course covers the fundamentals of probability and random processes useful in fields such as networks, communication, signal processing, and control. Sample space, events, probability law. Conditional probability. Independence. Random variables. Distribution, density functions. Random vectors. Law of large numbers. Central limit theorem. Estimation and detection. Markov chains.
    </course>
    <course name="Feedback Control" number="128" units="4">
        Analysis and synthesis of continuous and sampled-data linear feedback control systems. Advantages of feedback. Design by root locus, frequency response, and state space methods, with a comparison of techniques. Case studies.
    </course>
    <course name="Neural and Nonlinear Information Processing" number="129" units="3">
        Principles of massively parallel real-time computation, optimization, and information processing via nonlinear dynamics and analog VLSI neural networks, applications selected from image processing, pattern recognition, feature extraction, motion detection, data compression, secure communication, bionic eye, auto waves, and Turing patterns.
    </course>
    <course name="Integrated-Circuit Devices" number="130" units="4">
        Overview of electronic properties of semiconductor. Metal-semiconductor contacts, pn junctions, bipolar transistors, and MOS field-effect transistors. Properties that are significant to device operation for integrated circuits. Silicon device fabrication technology.
    </course>
    <course name="Linear Integrated Circuits" number="140" units="4">
        Single and multiple stage transistor amplifiers. Operational amplifiers. Feedback amplifiers, 2-port formulation, source, load, and feedback network loading. Frequency response of cascaded amplifiers, gain-bandwidth exchange, compensation, dominant pole techniques, root locus. Supply and temperature independent biasing and references. Selected applications of analog circuits such as analog-to-digital converters, switched capacitor filters, and comparators. The laboratory builds on the concepts presented in the lectures and provides hands-on design experience and help with the use of computer aided design tools such as SPICE.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Digital Integrated Circuits" number="141" units="4">
        CMOS devices and deep sub-micron manufacturing technology. CMOS inverters and complex gates. Modeling of interconnect wires. Optimization of designs with respect to a number of metrics: cost, reliability, performance, and power dissipation. Sequential circuits, timing considerations, and clocking approaches. Design of large system blocks, including arithmetic, interconnect, memories, and programmable logic arrays. Introduction to design methodologies, including hands-on experience.
    </course>
    <course name="Integrated Circuits for Communications" number="142" units="4">
        Analysis and design of electronic circuits for communication systems, with an emphasis on integrated circuits for wireless communication systems. Analysis of noise and distortion in amplifiers with application to radio receiver design. Power amplifier design with application to wireless radio transmitters. Radio-frequency mixers, oscillators, phase-locked loops, modulators, and demodulators.
    </course>
    <course name="Microfabrication Technology" number="143" units="4">
        Integrated circuit device fabrication and surface micromachining technology. Thermal oxidation, ion implantation, impurity diffusion, film deposition, expitaxy, lithography, etching, contacts and interconnections, and process integration issues. Device design and mask layout, relation between physical structure and electrical/mechanical performance. MOS transistors and poly-Si surface microstructures will be fabricated in the laboratory and evaluated.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits" number="144" units="4">
        This course covers a wide variety of algorithmic techniques to aid in the design and analysis of integrated circuits and systems. Topics to be covered include placement, routing, timing analysis, synthesis, verification, testing, and current research topics. Software-based laboratory assignments will expose students to state-of-the-art tools and techniques.
    </course>
    <course name="Image Processing and Reconstruction Tomography" number="C145B" units="4">
        Linear systems and Fourier transforms in two and three dimensions. Basic image processing. Theory and algorithms for image reconstruction from projections. Physics of imaging systems including magnetic resonance, X-ray tomography, positron emission tomography, ultrasound, and biomagnetic imaging. Data analysis including hypothesis testing, parameter estimation by least squares, and compartmental kinetic modelling. Field trips to medical imaging laboratories. Also listed as Bioengineering C165.
    </course>
    <course name="Introductory Electronic Transducer Laboratory" number="145L" units="3">
        Laboratory exercises exploring a variety of electronic transducers for measuring physical quantities such as temperature, force, displacement, sound, light, ionic potential; the use of circuits for low-level differential amplification and analog signal processing; and the use of microcomputers for digital sampling and display. Lectures cover principles explored in the laboratory exercises; construction, response and signal to noise of electronic transducers and actuators; and design of circuits for sensing and controlling physical quantities.
    </course>
    <course name="Introductory Electronic Transducers Laboratory" number="C145L" units="3">
        Laboratory exercises exploring a variety of electronic transducers for measuring physical quantities such as temperature, force, displacement, sound, light, ionic potential; the use of circuits for low-level differential amplification and analog signal processing; and the use of microcomputers for digital sampling and display. Lectures cover principles explored in the laboratory exercises; construction, response and signal to noise of electronic transducers and actuators; and design of circuits for sensing and controlling physical quantities. Also listed as Bioengineering C145L.
    </course>
    <course name="Introductory Microcomputer Interfacing Laboratory" number="145M" units="3">
        Laboratory exercises constructing basic interfacing circuits and writing 20-100 line C programs for data acquisition, storage, analysis, display, and control. Use of the IBM PC with microprogrammable digital counter/timer, parallel I/O port, and analog I/O port. Circuit components include anti-aliasing filters, the S/H amplifier, A/D and D/A converters. Exercises include effects of aliasing in periodic sampling, fast Fourier transforms of basic waveforms, the use of the Hanning filter for leakage reduction, Fourier analysis of the human voice, digital filters, and control using Fourier deconvolution. Lectures cover principles explored in the laboratory exercises and design of microcomputer-based systems for data acquisition, analysis, and control.
    </course>
    <course name="Introductory Microcomputer Interfacing Laboratory" number="C145M" units="3">
        Laboratory exercises constructing basic interfacing circuits and writing 20-100 line C programs for data acquisition, storage, analysis, display, and control. Use of the IBM PC with microprogrammable digital counter/timer, parallel I/O port. Circuit components include anti-aliasing filters, the S/H amplifier, A/D and D/A converters. Exercises include effects of aliasing in periodic sampling, fast Fourier transforms of basic waveforms, the use of the Hanning filter for leakage reduction, Fourier analysis of the human voice, digital filters, and control using Fourier deconvolution. Lectures cover principles explored in the lab exercises and design of microcomputer-based systems for data acquisitions, analysis and control. Also listed as Bioengineering C145M.
    </course>
    <course name="Mechatronic Design Laboratory" number="192" units="4">
        Design project course, focusing on application of theoretical principles in electrical engineering to control of a small-scale system, such as a mobile robot. Small teams of students will design and construct a mechatronic system incorporating sensors, actuators, and intelligence.
    </course>
    <course name="Senior Honors Thesis Research" number="H196A" units="4">
        Thesis work under the supervision of a faculty member. To obtain credit the student must, at the end of two semesters, submit a satisfactory thesis to the Electrical Engineering and Computer Science department archive. A total of four units must be taken. The units may be distributed between one or two semesters in any way. H196A-H196B count as graded technical elective units, but may not be used to satisfy the requirement for 20 upper division technical units in EECS.
    </course>
    <course name="Senior Honors Thesis Research" number="H196B" units="4">
        Thesis work under the supervision of a faculty member. To obtain credit the student must, at the end of two semesters, submit a satisfactory thesis to the Electrical Engineering and Computer Science department archive. A total of four units must be taken. The units may be distributed between one or two semesters in any way. H196A-H196B count as graded technical elective units, but may not be used to satisfy the requirement for 20 upper division technical units in EECS.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study for Advanced Undergraduates" number="198" units="1-4">
        Group study of selected topics in electrical engineering, usually relating to new developments.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study" number="199" units="1-4">
        Supervised independent study. Enrollment restrications apply.
    </course>
    <course name="Strategic Computing and Communications Technology" number="C201" units="3">
        Factors strongly impacting the success of new computing and communications products and services (based on underlying technologies such as electronics and software) in commercial applications. Technology trends and limits, economics, standardization, intellectual property, government policy, and industrial organization. Strategies to manage the design and marketing of successful products and services. Also listed as Information C224.
    </course>
    <course name="Applied Electromagnetic Theory" number="210" units="3">
        Advanced treatment of classical electromagnetic theory with engineering applications. Boundary value problems in electrostatics. Applications of Maxwell's Equations to the study of waveguides, resonant cavities, optical fiber guides, Gaussian optics, diffraction, scattering, and antennas.
    </course>
    <course name="Soft X-rays and Extreme Ultraviolet Radiation" number="C213" units="3">
        This course will explore modern developments in the physics and applications of soft x-rays. It begins with a review of electromagnetic radiation at short wavelengths including dipole radiation, scattering and refractive index, using a semi-classical atomic model. Subject matter will include the generation of x-rays with laboratory tubes, synchrotron radiation, laser-plasma sources, x-ray lasers, and black body radiation. Concepts of spatial and temporal coherence will be discussed. Also listed as Applied Science and Technology C210.
    </course>
    <course name="Antennas and Propagation" number="216" units="3">
        Application of Maxwell's Equations to the study of antennas and the propagation of electromagnetic waves. Basic concepts of antennas as devices in communication systems. Analysis of wire antennas, arrays of elements, horns, reflector and lens systems, frequency independent antennas. The propagation of waves over the earth and in inhomogeneous and random media.
    </course>
    <course name="Microwave Circuits" number="217" units="3">
        Techniques of analog circuit technology in the high-frequency regime above 1 GHz. Transmission lines and distributed circuit elements; S-parameter design of high-frequency active circuits; computer-aided analysis and design. Emphasis on design of planar high-frequency integrated circuits employing CMOS and SiGe technology. Circuit building blocks for broadband wired and wireless communication will be emphasized including oscillators, low-noise amplifiers, and power amplifiers.
    </course>
    <course name="Computer-Aided Verification of Electronic Circuits and Systems" number="219A" units="3">
        This course deals with techniques for the verification of correct behavior of complex electronic circuits and systems including algorithms and systems for the detailed simulation of integrated circuits at the transistor level in the time and frequency domain, discrete-event logic simulation, cycle-based logic simulation, RTL and behavorial simulation, equivalence checking, timing analysis, and power estimation.
    </course>
    <course name="Logic Synthesis" number="219B" units="4">
        The course covers the fundamental techniques for the design and analysis of digital circuits. The goal is to provide a detailed understanding of basic logic synthesis and analysis algorithms, and to enable students to apply this knowledge in the design of digital systems and EDA tools. The course will present combinational circuit optimization (two-level and multi-level synthesis), sequential circuit optimization (state encoding, retiming), timing analysis, testing, and logic verification.
    </course>
    <course name="Computer-Aided Verification" number="219C" units="3">
        Introduction to the theory and practice of formal methods for the design and analysis of systems, with a focus on automated algorithmic techniques. Covers selected topics in computational logic and automata theory including formal models of reactive systems, temporal logic, model checking, and automated theorem proving. Applications in hardware and software verification, analysis of embedded, real-time, and hybrid systems, computer security, synthesis, planning, constraint solving, and other areas will be explored as time permits.
    </course>
    <course name="Nonlinear Circuits" number="220" units="3">
        Algebraic and dynamic n-ports. Potential and state functions. Volterra series. Frequency-power formulas. Qualitative properties: equilibrium states, stability, oscillations, subharmonic, almost-periodic, and chaotic phenomenon. Frequency entrainment. Harmonic balance, describing function and bifurcation. Applications to oscillators, multivibrators, mixers, modulators and harmonic generators.
    </course>
    <course name="Linear System Theory" number="221A" units="4">
        Basic system concepts; state-space and I/O representation. Properties of linear systems. Controllability, observability, minimality, state and output-feedback. Stability. Observers. Characteristic polynomial. Nyquist test.
    </course>
    <course name="Nonlinear Systems--Analysis, Stability and Control" number="222" units="3">
        Basic graduate course in non-linear systems. Second Order systems. Numerical solution methods, the describing function method, linearization. Stability - direct and indirect methods of Lyapunov. Applications to the Lure problem - Popov, circle criterion. Input-Output stability. Additional topics include: bifurcations of dynamical systems, introduction to the &quot;geometric&quot; theory of control for nonlinear systems, passivity concepts and dissipative dynamical systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Stochastic Systems: Estimation and Control" number="223" units="3">
        Parameter and state estimation. System identification. Nonlinear filtering. Stochastic control. Adaptive control.
    </course>
    <course name="Digital Communications" number="224A" units="4">
        Introduction to the basic principles of the design and analysis of modern digital communication systems. Topics include source coding; channel coding; baseband and passband modulation techniques; receiver design; channel equalization; information theoretic techniques; block, convolutional, and trellis coding techniques; multiuser communications and spread spectrum; multi-carrier techniques and FDM; carrier and symbol synchronization. Applications to design of digital telephone modems, compact disks, and digital wireless communication systems are illustrated. The concepts are illustrated by a sequence of MATLAB exercises.
    </course>
    <course name="Fundamentals of Wireless Communication" number="224B" units="3">
        Introduction of the fundamentals of wireless communication. Modeling of the wireless multipath fading channel and its basic physical parameters. Coherent and noncoherent reception. Diversity techniques over time, frequency, and space. Spread spectrum communication. Multiple access and interference management in wireless networks. Frequency re-use, sectorization. Multiple access techniques: TDMA, CDMA, OFDM. Capacity of wireless channels. Opportunistic communication. Multiple antenna systems: spatial multiplexing, space-time codes. Examples from existing wireless standards.
    </course>
    <course name="Digital Signal Processing" number="225A" units="3">
        Advanced techniques in signal processing. Stochastic signal processing, parametric statistical signal models, and adaptive filterings. Application to spectral estimation, speech and audio coding, adaptive equalization, noise cancellation, echo cancellation, and linear prediction.
    </course>
    <course name="Digital Image Processing" number="225B" units="3">
        2-D sequences and systems, separable systems, projection slice thm, reconstruction from projections and partial Fourier information, Z transform, different equations, recursive computability, 2D DFT and FFT, 2D FIR filter design; human eye, perception, psychophysical vision properties, photometry and colorimetry, optics and image systems; image enhancement, image restoration, geometrical image modification, morphological image processing, halftoning, edge detection, image compression: scalar quantization, lossless coding, huffman coding, arithmetic coding dictionary techniques, waveform and transform coding DCT, KLT, Hadammard, multiresolution coding pyramid, subband coding, Fractal coding, vector quantization, motion estimation and compensation, standards: JPEG, MPEG, H.xxx, pre- and post-processing, scalable image and video coding, image and video communication over noisy channels.
    </course>
    <course name="VLSI Signal Processing" number="225C" units="3">
        Formerly 290M. Design of signal processing systems. Building blocks and design styles. Simulation and specification. Architectural trade-offs. Synthesis techniques.
    </course>
    <course name="Audio Signal Processing in Humans and Machines" number="225D" units="3">
        Introduction to relevant signal processing and basics of pattern recognition. Introduction to coding, synthesis, and recognition. Models of speech and music production and perception. Signal processing for speech analysis. Pitch perception and auditory spectral analysis with applications to speech and music. Vocoders and music synthesizers. Statistical speech recognition, including introduction to Hidden Markov Model and Neural Network approaches.
    </course>
    <course name="Random Processes in Systems" number="226A" units="4">
        Probability, random variables and their convergence, random processes. Filtering of wide sense stationary processes, spectral density, Wiener and Kalman filters. Markov processes and Markov chains. Gaussian, birth and death, poisson and shot noise processes. Elementary queueing analysis. Detection of signals in Gaussian and shot noise, elementary parameter estimation.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Convex Optimization" number="227A" units="3">
        Convex optimization is a class of nonlinear optimization problems where the objective to be minimized, and the constraints, are both convex. Contrarily to the more classical linear programming framework, convex programs often go unrecognized, and this is a pity since a large class of convex optimization problems can now be efficiently solved. In addition, it is possible to address hard, nonconvex problems (such as &quot;combinatorial optimization&quot; problems) using convex approximations that are more efficient than classical linear ones. The 3-unit course covers some convex optimization theory and algorithms, and describes various applications arising in engineering design, modelling and estimation, finance, and operations research.
    </course>
    <course name="Convex Optimization and Approximation" number="227B" units="3">
        Convex optimization as a systematic approximation tool for hard decision problems. Approximations of combinatorial optimization problems, of stochastic programming problems, of robust optimization problems (i.e., with optimization problems with unknown but bounded data), of optimal control problems. Quality estimates of the resulting approximation. Applications in robust engineering design, statistics, control, finance, data mining, operations research.
    </course>
    <course name="High Speed Communications Networks" number="228A" units="3">
        Descriptions, models, and approaches to the design and management of networks. Optical transmission and switching technologies are described and analyzed using deterministic, stochastic, and simulation models. FDDI, DQDB, SMDS, Frame Relay, ATM, networks, and SONET. Applications demanding high-speed communication.
    </course>
    <course name="Information Theory and Coding" number="229" units="3">
        Formerly EECS 229B Fundamental bounds of Shannon theory and their application. Source and channel coding theorems. Galois field theory, algebraic error-correction codes. Private and public-key cryptographic systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Information Theory and Coding" number="229A" units="3">
        Fundamental bounds of Shannon theory and their application. Source and channel coding theorems. Galois field theory, algebraic error-correction codes. Private and public-key cryptographic systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Error Control Coding" number="229B" units="3">
        Error control codes are an integral part of most communication and recording systems where they are primarily used to provide resiliency to noise. In this course, we will cover the basics of error control coding for reliable digital transmission and storage. We will discuss the major classes of codes that are important in practice, including Reed Muller codes, cyclic codes, Reed Solomon codes, convolutional codes, concatenated codes, turbo codes, and low density parity check codes. The relevant background material from finite field and polynomial algebra will be developed as part of the course. Overview of topics: binary linear block codes; Reed Muller codes; Galois fields; linear block codes over a finite field; cyclic codes; BCH and Reed Solomon codes; convolutional codes and trellis based decoding, message passing decoding algorithms; trellis based soft decision decoding of block codes; turbo codes; low density parity check codes.
    </course>
    <course name="Solid State Electronics" number="230" units="3">
        Crystal structure and symmetries. Energy-band theory. Cyclotron resonance. Tensor effective mass. Statistics of electronic state population. Recombination theory. Carrier transport theory. Interface properties. Optical processes and properties.
    </course>
    <course name="Solid State Devices" number="231" units="4">
        Physical principles and operational characteristics of semiconductor devices. Emphasis is on MOS field-effect transistors and their behaviors dictated by present and probable future technologies. Metal-oxide-semiconductor systems, short-channel and high field effects, device modeling, and impact on analog, digital circuits.
    </course>
    <course name="Lightwave Devices" number="232" units="3">
        Principle of semiconductor lasers. Modulation dynamics. Single frequency lasers. Fundamental AM and FM noise properties, linewidth. Tunable semiconductor lasers. Quantum well lasers. Electrooptic modulators and switches. Detectors. Integrated optoelectronic circuits. Optical amplifiers-semiconductor and Erbium fiber. Low coherence sources-superluminescent diodes. Tunable optical filters.
    </course>
    <course name="Lightwave Systems" number="233" units="3">
        Transmission properties of optical fibers - dispersion, attenuation, nonlinear effects (solitons). Direct-detection systems: analog and digital modulation, transmitter design, receiver design, noise properties of single and multimode fiber links, dependence on source coherence, subcarrier and multichannel CATV analog transmission issues the role of optical fiber amplifiers. Coherent communication: FM noise and modulation properties of laser diodes, quantum limited detection, homodyne and heterodyne detection of various formats, laser linewidth requirements, diversity issues. Lightwave networks - WDMA, FDMA, subcarrier, TDMA, and CDMA, relative merits. Topological issues - multihop (sore-and-forward) and hot-potato routing, the role of optical switching. Optical network access protocols. Optical interconnection in high speed circuit modules and computers.
    </course>
    <course name="Nanoscale Fabrication" number="C235" units="4">
        This course discusses various top-down and bottom-up approaches to synthesizing and processing nanostructured materials. The topics include fundamentals of self assembly, nano-imprint lithography, electron beam lithography, nanowire and nanotube synthesis, quantum dot synthesis (strain patterned and colloidal), postsynthesis modification (oxidation, doping, diffusion, surface interactions, and etching techniques). In addition, techniques to bridging length scales such as heterogeneous integration will be discussed. We will discuss new electronic, optical, thermal, mechanical, and chemical properties brought forth by the very small sizes. Also listed as Nanoscale Science and Engineering C203.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantum and Optical Electronics" number="236A" units="3">
        Interaction of radiation with atomic and semiconductor systems, density matrix treatment, semiclassical laser theory (Lamb's), laser resonators, specific laser systems, laser dynamics, Q-switching and mode-locking, noise in lasers and optical amplifiers. Nonlinear optics, phase-conjugation, electrooptics, acoustooptics and magnetooptics, coherent optics, stimulated Raman and Brillouin scattering.
    </course>
    <course name="Superconductive Devices and Circuits" number="238" units="3">
        Introduction to superconductivity. Electron pairing. BCS and Ginzburg-Landau theories. Single-particle and Josephson tunneling. Electrodynamics of superconductors and Josephson junctions. Proximity effect. Mixed state in type II superconductors. Thin films. Applications in analog and digital circuits. Fabrication technology.
    </course>
    <course name="Partially Ionized Plasmas" number="C239" units="3">
        Introduction to partially ionized, chemically reactive plasmas, including collisional processes, diffusion, sources, sheaths, boundaries, and diagnostics. DC, RF, and microwave discharges. Applications to plasma-assisted materials processing and to plasma wall interactions. Also listed as Applied Science and Technology C239.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Analog Integrated Circuits" number="240" units="3">
        Analysis and optimized design of monolithic operational amplifiers and wide-band amplifiers; methods of achieving wide-band amplification, gain-bandwidth considerations; analysis of noise in integrated circuits and low noise design. Precision passive elements, analog switches, amplifiers and comparators, voltage reference in NMOS and CMOS circuits, Serial, successive-approximation, and parallel analog-to-digital converters. Switched-capacitor and CCD filters. Applications to codecs, modems.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Digital Integrated Circuits" number="241" units="3">
        Analysis and design of MOS and bipolar large-scale integrated circuits at the circuit level. Fabrication processes, device characteristics, parasitic effects static and dynamic digital circuits for logic and memory functions. Calculation of speed and power consumption from layout and fabrication parameters. ROM, RAM, EEPROM circuit design. Use of SPICE and other computer aids.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Integrated Circuits for Communications" number="242" units="3">
        Analysis, evaluation and design of present-day integrated circuits for communications application, particularly those for which nonlinear response must be included. MOS, bipolar and BICMOS circuits, audio and video power amplifiers, optimum performance of near-sinusoidal oscillators and frequency-translation circuits. Phase-locked loop ICs, analog multipliers and voltage-controlled oscillators; advanced components for telecommunication circuits. Use of new CAD tools and systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced IC Processing and Layout" number="243" units="3">
        The key processes for the fabrication of integrated circuits. Optical, X-ray, and e-beam lithography, ion implantation, oxidation and diffusion. Thin film deposition. Wet and dry etching and ion milling. Effect of phase and defect equilibria on process control.
    </course>
    <course name="Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits" number="244" units="3">
        This course will cover a wide variety of topics relating to the development of computer aids for integrated circuit design. The course will emphasize state-of-the-art techniques and both the theoretical basis for the methods as well as the application of results to practical problems, including details of implementation. Topics to be covered include simulation, layout techniques, synthesis, verification, testing, and integrated design systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to MEMS Design" number="C245" units="4">
        Physics, fabrication, and design of micro-electromechanical systems (MEMS). Micro- and nano-fabrication processes, including silicon surface and bulk micromachining and non-silicon micromachining. Integration strategies and assembly processes. Microsensor and microactuator devices: electrostatic, piezoresistive, piezoelectric, thermal, magnetic transduction. Electronic position-sensing circuits and electrical and mechanical noise. CAD for MEMS. Design project is required. Also listed as Mechanical Engineering C218.
    </course>
    <course name="Microelectromechanical Systems (MEMS)" number="C246" units="3">
        This course is aimed to provide basic understanding of integrated circuit (IC) processes and microelectromechanical system (MEMS). Technologies including analyses, design, and manufacturing processes of MEMS will be introduced. The first part of the course emphasizes IC processes including thin film deposition, lithography, and etching. The second part of the course deals with micromachining processes including surface-, bulk-micromachining, LIGA and other processes. Also listed as Mechanical Engineering C219.
    </course>
    <course name="Analysis and Design of VLSI Analog-Digital Interface Integrated Circuits" number="247" units="3">
        Architectural and circuit level design and analysis of integrated analog-to-digital and digital-to-analog interfaces in CMOS and BiCMOS VLSI technology. Analog-digital converters, digital-analog converters, sample/hold amplifiers, continuous and switched-capacitor filters. RF integrated electronics including synthesizers, LNA's, and baseband processing. Low power mixed signal design. Data communications functions including clock recovery. CAD tools for analog design including simulation and synthesis.
    </course>
    <course name="Embedded System Design: Models, Validation, and Synthesis" number="249" units="4">
        Principles of embedded system design. Focus on design methodologies and foundations. Platform-based design and communication-based design and their relationship with design time, re-use, and performance. Models of computation and their use in design capture, manipulation, verification, and synthesis. Mapping into architecture and system platforms. Performance estimation. Scheduling and real-time requirements. Synchronous languages and time-triggered protocols to simplify the design process. Simulation techniques for highly programmable platforms. Synthesis and successive refinement: meta-model of computation. Use of design tools and analysis of their capabilities and limitations: Ptolemy, POLIS, Metropolis, VCC, Co-ware.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Computer-Aided Design" number="290A" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Solid State Devices" number="290B" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Circuit Design" number="290C" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Semiconductor Technology" number="290D" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Electromagnetics and Plasmas" number="290E" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Photonics" number="290F" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Semiconductor Manufacturing" number="290H" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Optimization" number="290K" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in System Theory" number="290N" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Control" number="290O" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Bioelectronics" number="290P" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Communication Networks" number="290Q" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Communications and Information Theory" number="290S" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Topics in Signal Processing" number="290T" units="1-3">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Organic Materials in Electronics" number="290Y" units="3">
        Organic materials are seeing increasing application in electronics applications. This course will provide an overview of the properties of the major classes of organic materials with relevance to electronics. Students will study the technology, physics, and chemistry of their use in the three most rapidly growing major applications--energy conversion/generation devices (fuel cells and photovoltaics), organic light-emitting diodes, and organic transistors.
    </course>
    <course name="Control and Optimization of Distributed Parameters Systems" number="C291" units="3">
        Distributed systems and PDE models of physical phenomena (propagation of waves, network traffic, water distribution, fluid mechanics, electromagnetism, blood vessels, beams, road pavement, structures, etc.). Fundamental solution methods for PDEs: separation of variables, self-similar solutions, characteristics, numerical methods, spectral methods. Stability analysis. Adjoint-based optimization. Lyapunov stabilization. Differential flatness. Viability control. Hamilton-Jacobi-based control. Also listed as Civil and Environmental Engineering C291F and Mechanical Engineering C236.
    </course>
    <course name="Hybrid Systems and Intelligent Control" number="C291E" units="3">
        Analysis of hybrid systems formed by the interaction of continuous time dynamics and discrete-event controllers. Discrete-event systems models and language descriptions. Finite-state machines and automata. Model verification and control of hybrid systems. Signal-to-symbol conversion and logic controllers. Adaptive, neural, and fuzzy-control systems. Applications to robotics and Intelligent Vehicle and Highway Systems (IVHS). Also listed as Mechanical Engineering C290S.
    </course>
    <course name="Field Studies in Electrical Engineering" number="297" units="1-12">
        Supervised experience in off-campus companies relevant to specific aspects and applications of electrical engineering. Written report required at the end of the semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Group Studies, Seminars, or Group Research" number="298" units="1-4">
        Advanced study in various subjects through special seminars on topics to be selected each year, informal group studies of special problems, group participation in comprehensive design problems, or group research on complete problems for analysis and experimentation.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Research" number="299" units="1-12">
        Investigation of problems in electrical engineering.
    </course>
    <course name="Teaching Techniques for Electrical Engineering" number="301" units="1">
        Weekly seminars and discussions of effective teaching techniques. Use of educational objectives, alternative forms of instruction, and special techniques for teaching key concepts and techniques in electrical engineering. Student and self-evaluation. Course is intended to orient new graduate student instructors to teaching in the Electrical Engineering Department at Berkeley.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study for Doctoral Students" number="602" units="1-8">
        Individual study in consultation with the major field adviser, intended to provide an opportunity for qualified students to prepare themselves for the various examinations required of candidates for the Ph.D. (and other doctoral degrees).
    </course>
</department>
