<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="IND ENG" name="Industrial Engineering">
    <course name="Freshman Seminars" number="24" units="1">
        The Berkeley Seminar Program has been designed to provide new students with the opportunity to explore an intellectual topic with a faculty member in a small-seminar setting. Berkeley Seminars are offered in all campus departments, and topics vary from department to department and semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39B" units="2-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Sophomore Seminar" number="84" units="1,2">
        Sophomore seminars are small interactive courses offered by faculty members in departments all across the campus. Sophomore seminars offer opportunity for close, regular intellectual contact between faculty members and students in the crucial second year. The topics vary from department to department and semester to semester. Enrollment limited to 15 sophomores.
    </course>
    <course name="Industrial and Commercial Data Systems" number="115" units="3">
        Design and implementation of databases, with an emphasis on industrial and commercial applications. Relational algebra, SQL, normalization. Students work in teams with local companies on a database design project. WWW design and queries.
    </course>
    <course name="Methods of Manufacturing Improvement" number="130" units="3">
        Analytical techniques for the improvement of manufacturing performance along the dimensions of productivity, quality, customer service, and throughput. Techniques for yield analysis, process control, inspection sampling, equipment efficiency analysis, cycle time reduction, and on-time delivery improvement. Applications on semiconductor manufacturing or other industrial settings.
    </course>
    <course name="Discrete Event Simulation" number="131" units="3">
        Introductory course on design, programming, and statistical analysis of a simulation study. Topics include the types of problems that can be solved by such methods. Programming material includes the theory behind random variable generation for a variety of common variables. Techniques to reduce the variance of the resultant estimator and statistical analysis are considered. Final project required.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Mobile Industrial Robots" number="140" units="4">
        Introductory course in the hardware and software design of autonomous vehicles. Basic concepts of sensors, actuators, navigation, exploration, feedback control, and communications. Object-oriented software design principles. Programming for real-time control using Java. Laboratory project teams will design, build, program, and test small prototype vehicles for material handling systems and other applications.
    </course>
    <course name="Production Systems Analysis" number="150" units="3">
        Quantitative models for operational and tactical decision making in production systems, including production planning, inventory control, forecasting, and scheduling.
    </course>
    <course name="Service Operations Design and Analysis" number="151" units="3">
        This course is concerned with improving processes and designing facilities for service businesses such as banks, health care organizations, telephone call centers, restaurants, and transportation providers. Major topics in the course include design of service processes, layout and location of service facilities, demand forecasting, demand management, employee scheduling, service quality management, and capacity planning.
    </course>
    <course name="Logistics Network Design and Supply Chain Management" number="153" units="3">
        We will focus primarily on both quantitative and qualitative issues which arise in the integrated design and management of the entire logistics network. Models and solution techniques for facility location and logistics network design will be considered. In addition, qualitative issues in distribution network structuring, centralized versus decentralized network control, variability in the supply chain, strategic partnerships, and product design for logistics will be considered through discussions and cases.
    </course>
    <course name="Operations Research I" number="160" units="3">
        Deterministic methods and models in operations research. Unconstrained and constrained optimization. Equality, inequality, and integer constraints. Sequential decisions; dynamic programming. Resource allocation, equipment replacement, inventory control, production planning.
    </course>
    <course name="Operations Research II" number="161" units="3">
        Probability review. Conditional expectation. The exponential distribution and poisson process. Markovian Queueing Systems. Component reliability systems. Applications to replacement, repair, transportation and inventory models.
    </course>
    <course name="Linear Programming" number="162" units="3">
        Formulation to linear programs. Optimal allocation and control problems in industry and environmental studies. Convex sets; properties of optimal solutions. The simplex method; theorems of duality; complementary slackness. Problems of post-optimization. Special structures; network problems. Digital computation.
    </course>
    <course name="Engineering Statistics, Quality Control, and Forcasting" number="165" units="3">
        This course will introduce students to basic statistical techniques such as parameter estimation, hypothesis testing, regression analysis, analysis of variance, design of experiments, and non parametric statistics. Applications of these statistical techniques to data analysis problems in engineering and manufacturing systems will be the main foci of this course. Specific applications in forecasting and quality control will be considered in detail. Forecasts based on moving average, exponential smoothing, and regression analysis will be studied. Quality and process control using x-bar, moving average, cumulative sum, and range charts will be discussed.
    </course>
    <course name="Decision Analysis" number="166" units="3">
        Introductory course on the theory and applications of decision analysis. Elective course that provides a systematic evaluation of decision-making problems under uncertainty. Emphasis on the formulation, analysis, and use of decision-making techniques in engineering, operations research and systems analysis. Includes formulation of risk problems and probabilistic risk assessments. Graphical methods and computer software using event trees, decision trees, and influence diagrams that focus on model design.
    </course>
    <course name="Industrial Design and Human Factors" number="170" units="3">
        This course surveys topics related to the design of products and interfaces ranging from alarm clocks, cell phones, and dashboards to logos, presentations, and web sites. Design of such systems requires familiarity with human factors and ergonomics, including the physics and perception of color, sound, and touch, as well as familiarity with case studies and contemporary practices in interface design and usability testing. Students will solve a series of design problems individually and in teams.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Design of Human Work Systems and Organizations" number="171" units="3">
        Qualitative management principles and techniques used to maximize labor productivity, employee satisfaction, and organizational performance in work settings. Topics covered include job attitudes, person-job fit, worker motivation, leadership, organizational culture, technology and innovation management, communication, groups and teams, decision-making, and power and influence.
    </course>
    <course name="Probability and Risk Analysis for Engineers" number="172" units="3">
        This is an introductory probability course for students in engineering. It focuses mostly on random variables and their applications. Applications will be given in such areas as reliability theory, risk theory, inventory theory, failure models, stress models, computer science, and others.
    </course>
    <course name="Senior Project" number="180" units="4">
        Application of systems analysis and industrial engineering to the analysis, planning, and/or design of industrial, service, and government systems. Consideration of technical and economic aspects of equipment and process design. Students work in teams under faculty supervision. Topics vary yearly.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="190A" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Entrepreneurial Marketing and Finance" number="190B" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="190C" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="190D" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Entrepreneurship &amp; Innovation: Life Sciences" number="190E" units="1">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="190F" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="" number="190G" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Operations Research and Management Science Honors Thesis" number="H196A" units="3">
        Individual study and research for at least one academic year on a special problem approved by a member of the faculty; preparation of the thesis on broader aspects of this work.
    </course>
    <course name="Operations Research and Management Science Honors Thesis" number="H196B" units="3">
        Individual study and research for at least one academic year on a special problem approved by a member of the faculty; preparation of the thesis on broader aspects of this work.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Studies for Advanced Undergraduates" number="198" units="1-4">
        Group studies of selected topics. Semester course unit value and contact hours will have a one-to-one ratio.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study" number="199" units="1-4">
        Supervised independent study. Enrollment restrictions apply.
    </course>
    <course name="Analysis and Design of Databases" number="215" units="3">
        Advanced topics in information management, focusing on design of relational databases, querying, and normalization. New issues raised by the World Wide Web. Research projects on current topics in information technology.
    </course>
    <course name="Analysis and Design of Databases" number="C215" units="3">
        Advanced topics in information management, focusing on design of relational databases, querying, and normalization. New issues raised by the World Wide Web. Research projects on current topics in information technology. Also listed as Information C258.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Financial Engineering" number="221" units="3">
        A course on financial concepts useful for engineers that will cover, among other topics, those of interest rates, present values, arbitrage, geometric Brownian motion, options pricing, and portfolio optimization. The Black-Scholes option-pricing formula will be derived and studied. Stochastic simulation ideas will be introduced and used to obtain the risk-neutral geometric Brownian motion values for certain types of Asian, barrier, and lookback options. Portfolio optimization problems will be considered both from a mean-variance and from a utility function point of view. Methods for evaluating real options will be presented. The use of mathematical optimization models as a framework for analyzing financial engineering problems will be shown.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Production Planning and Logistics Models" number="250" units="3">
        This will be an introductory first-year graduate course covering fundamental models in production planning and logistics. Models, algorithms, and analytical techniques for inventory control, production scheduling, production planning, facility location and logistics network design, vehicle routing, and demand forecasting will be discussed.
    </course>
    <course name="Facilities Design and Logistics" number="251" units="3">
        Design and analysis of models and algorithms for facility location, vehicle routing, and facility layout problems. Emphasis will be placed on both the use of computers and the theoretical analysis of models and algorithms.
    </course>
    <course name="Supply Chain Operation and Management" number="253" units="3">
        Supply chain analysis is the study of quantitative models that characterize various economic trade-offs in the supply chain. The field has made significant strides on both theoretical and practical fronts. On the theoretical front, supply chain analysis inspires new research ventures that blend operations research, game theory, and microeconomics. These ventures result in an unprecedented amalgamation of prescriptive, descriptive, and predictive models characteristic of each subfield. On the practical front, supply chain analysis offers solid foundations for strategic positioning, policy setting, and decision making.
    </course>
    <course name="Production and Inventory Systems" number="254" units="3">
        Mathematical and computer methods for design, planning, scheduling, and control in manufacturing and distribution systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Experimenting with Simulated Systems" number="261" units="3">
        This course will introduce graduate and upper division undergraduate students to modern methods for simulating discrete event models of complex stochastic systems. About a third of the course will be devoted to system modeling, with the remaining two-thirds concentrating on simulation experimental design and analysis.
    </course>
    <course name="Mathematical Programming I" number="262A" units="4">
        Basic graduate course in linear programming and introduction to network flows and non-linear programming. Formulation and model building. The simplex method and its variants. Duality theory. Sensitivity analysis, parametric programming, convergence (theoretical and practical). Polynomial time algorithms. Introduction to network flows models. Optimality conditions for non linear optimization problems.
    </course>
    <course name="Mathematical Programming II" number="262B" units="3">
        Basic first year graduate course in optimization of non-linear programs. Formulation and model building. Theory of optimization for constrained and unconstrained problems. Study of algorithms for non-linear optimization with emphasis on design considerations and performance evaluation.
    </course>
    <course name="Applied Stochastic Process I" number="263A" units="4">
        Conditional Expectation. Poisson and renewal processes. Renewal reward processes with application to inventory, congestion, and replacement models. Discrete and continuous time Markov chains; with applications to various stochastic systems--such as exponential queueing systems, inventory models and reliability systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Applied Stochastic Process II" number="263B" units="3">
        Continuous time Markov chains. The reversed chain concept in continuous time Markov chains with applications of queueing theory. Semi-Markov processes with emphasis on application. Brownian Motion. Random walks with applications. Introduction to Martinjales.
    </course>
    <course name="Computational Optimization" number="264" units="3">
        This course is on computational methods for the solution of large-scale optimization problems. The focus is on converting the theory of optimization into effective computational techniques. Course topics include an introduction to polyhedral theory, cutting plane methods, relaxation, decomposition and heuristic approaches for large-scale optimization problems.
    </course>
    <course name="Network Flows and Graphs" number="266" units="3">
        Survey of solution techniques and problems that have formulations in terms of flows in networks. Max-flow min-cut theorem. Minimum cost flows. Multiterminal and multicommodity flows. Relationship with linear programming, transportation problems, electrical networks and critical path scheduling.
    </course>
    <course name="Queueing Theory" number="267" units="3">
        The result &quot;L = (lambda) w&quot; and other conservation laws. Elementary queueing models; comparing single- and multiple-server queues. PASTA. Work. Markovian queues; product form results. Overflow models. Embedded Markov chains. Random walks and the GI/G/l queues. Work conservation; priorities. Bounds and approximations.
    </course>
    <course name="Applied Dynamic Programming" number="268" units="3">
        Dynamic programming formulation of deterministic decision process problems, analytical and computational methods of solution, application to problems of equipment replacement, resource allocation, scheduling, search and routing. Brief introduction to decision making under risk and uncertainty.
    </course>
    <course name="Integer Programming and Combinatorial Optimization" number="269" units="3">
        The course deals with discrete optimization problems and their complexity. These topics include complexity analysis of algorithms and its drawbacks; solving a system of linear integer equations and inequalities; strongly polynomial algorithms, network flow problems (including matching and branching); polyhedral optimization; branch and bound and lagrangean relaxation.
    </course>
    <course name="Systems Analysis and Design Project" number="280" units="3">
        A project course for students interested in applications of operations research and engineering methods. One or more systems, which may be public or in the private sector, will be selected for detailed analysis and re-designed by student groups.
    </course>
    <course name="Dynamic Production Theory and Planning Models" number="290A" units="3">
        Development of dynamic activity analysis models for production planning and scheduling. Relationship to theory of production, inventory theory and hierarchical organization of production management.
    </course>
    <course name="Statistical Aspects of Discrete Event Simulation" number="290C" units="2">
        Statistical design and analysis of discrete event simulation of stochastic models. Methods of simulating random variables and stochastic processes. Variance estimation methods including the bootstrap technique. Variance reduction approaches including control variates, stratified sampling, importance sampling, conditional expectations, and the use of hazard variables will be studied.
    </course>
    <course name="Large-Scale Programming" number="290E" units="3">
        Methods for exploiting the structure of large mathematical optimization problems to economize on computer time and/or memory. Representations of the inverse that preserve sparseness. The simplex methods with upper bounded variables. Generalized upper bounding algorithm. Decomposition, Wolfe's generalized linear program and column generation methods for linear and convex problems. Partitioning, relaxation and resource allocation schemes. Applications.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Mathematical Programming" number="290G" units="3">
        Selected topics in mathematical programming. The actual subjects covered may include: Convex analysis, duality theory, complementary pivot theory, fixed point theory, optimization by vector space methods, advanced topics in nonlinear algorithms, complexity of mathematical programming algorithms (including linear programming).
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Risk Theory" number="290R" units="3">
        Seminar on selected topics from financial and technological risk theory, such as risk modeling, attitudes towards risk and utility theory, portfolio management, gambling and speculation, insurance and other risk-sharing arrangements, stochastic models of risk generation and run off, risk reserves, Bayesian forecasting and credibility approximations, influence diagrams, decision trees. Topics will vary from year to year.
    </course>
    <course name="Group Studies, Seminars, or Group Research" number="298" units="1-4">
        Advanced seminars in industrial engineering and operations research.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study or Research" number="299" units="1-12">
        Individual investigation of advanced industrial engineering problems.
    </course>
    <course name="Teaching Industrial Engineering and Operations Research" number="300" units="1">
        For current and future GSIs. Students learn about teaching through practice, research, discussion, etc. Each student leads one class, introducing the topic based on their research, and leading discussion; the student provides reading materials for that class. Industrial Engineering and Operations Research faculty are invited to attend and participate. Students are videotaped giving a lecture, and evaluate the tape with another student. Students observe a student or professor giving a lecture or leading discussion, and write a critique.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study for Master's Students" number="601" units="1-12">
        Individual study for the comprehensive in consultation with the field adviser. Units may not be used to meet either unit or residence requirements for a master's degree.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study for Doctoral Students" number="602" units="1-12">
        Individual study in consultation with the major field adviser, intended to provide an opportunity for qualified students to prepare themselves for the various examinations required of candidates for the Ph.D. (and other doctoral degrees). May not be used for unit or residence requirements for the doctoral degree.
    </course>
</department>
