<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="NUC ENG" name="Nuclear Engineering">
    <course name="Freshman Seminars" number="24" units="1">
        The Berkeley Seminar Program has been designed to provide new students with the opportunity to explore an intellectual topic with a faculty member in a small-seminar setting. Berkeley Seminars are offered in all campus departments, and topics vary from department to department and semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="" number="39A" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Nuclear Reactions and Radiation" number="101" units="4">
        Energetics and kinetics of nuclear reactions and radioactive decay, fission, fusion, and reactions of low-energy neutrons; properties of the fission products and the actinides; nuclear models and transition probabilities; interaction of radiation with matter.
    </course>
    <course name="Radiation Detection and Nuclear Instrumentation Laboratory" number="104" units="3">
        Basic science of radiation measurement, nuclear instrumentation, neutronics, radiation dosimetry. Applications to nuclear and non-nuclear research, medicine, environmental science and technology, and a variety of other technologies.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Imaging" number="107" units="3">
        Introduction to medical imaging physics and systems, including x-ray computed tomography (CT), nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), positron emission tomography (PET), and SPECT; basic principles of tomography and an introduction to unfolding methods; resolution effects of counting statistics, inherent system resolution and human factors.
    </course>
    <course name="Nuclear Materials" number="120" units="4">
        Effects of irradiation on the atomic and mechanical properties of materials in nuclear reactors. Fission product swelling and release; neutron damage to structural alloys; fabrication and properties of uranium dioxide fuel.
    </course>
    <course name="Radioactive Waste Management" number="124" units="3">
        Components and material flowsheets for nuclear fuel cycle, waste characteristics, sources of radioactive wastes, compositions, radioactivity and heat generation; waste treatment technologies; waste disposal technologies; safety assessment of waste disposal.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Nuclear Reactor Theory" number="150" units="3">
        Neutron interactions, nuclear fission, and chain reacting systematics in thermal and fast nuclear reactors. Diffusion and slowing down of neutrons. Criticality calculations. Nuclear reactor dynamics and reactivity feedback. Production of radionuclides in nuclear reactors.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Numerical Simulations in Radiation Transport" number="155" units="3">
        Computational methods used to analyze radiation transport described by various differential, integral, and integro-differential equations. Numerical methods include finite difference, finite elements, discrete ordinates, and Monte Carlo. Examples from neutron and photon transport; numerical solutions of neutron/photon diffusion and transport equations. Monte Carlo simulations of photon and neutron transport. An overview of optimization techniques for solving the resulting discrete equations on vector and parallel computer systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Nuclear Power Engineering" number="161" units="4">
        Energy conversion in nuclear power systems; design of fission reactors; thermal and structural analysis of reactor core and plant components; thermal-hydraulic analysis of accidents in nuclear power plants; safety evaluation and engineered safety systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Radiation Biophysics and Dosimetry" number="162" units="3">
        Interaction of radiation with matter; physical, chemical, and biological effects of radiation on human tissues; dosimetry units and measurements; internal and external radiation fields and dosimetry; radiation exposure regulations; sources of radiation and radioactivity; basic shielding concepts; elements of radiation protection and control; theories and models for cell survival, radiation sensitivity, carcinogenesis, and dose calculation.
    </course>
    <course name="Nuclear Reactor Safety" number="167" units="3">
        Principles and methods used in the safety evaluation of nuclear power plants. Safety philosophies, design criteria, and regulations. Deterministic and probabilistic models, reliability analysis, nuclear and thermal-hydraulic transients, rediological consequences, and risk assessment. Design-basis and severe accident analysis, role of engineered safety systems, siting, and licensing.
    </course>
    <course name="Nuclear Design: Design in Nuclear Power Technology and Instrumentation" number="170A" units="3">
        Design of various fission and fusion power systems and other physically based applications. Each semester a topic will be chosen by the class as a whole. In addition to technology, the design should address issues relating to economics, the environment, and risk assessment.
    </course>
    <course name="Nuclear Design: Design in Bionuclear, Nuclear Medicine, and Radiation Therapy" number="170B" units="3">
        A systems approach to the development of procedures for nuclear medicine and radiation therapy. Each semester a specific procedure will be studied and will entail the development of the biological and physiological basis for a procedure, the chemical and biochemical characteristics of appropriate drugs, dosimetric requirements and limitations, the production and distribution of radionuclides and/or radiation fields to be applied, and the characteristics of the instrumentation to be used.
    </course>
    <course name="Methods of Risk Analysis" number="175" units="3">
        Methodological approaches for the quantification of technological risk and risk based decision making. Probabilistic safety assessment, human health risks, environmental and ecological risk analysis.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Controlled Fusion" number="180" units="4">
        Introduction to energy production by controlled thermonuclear reactions. Nuclear fusion reactions, energy balances for fusion systems, survey of plasma physics; neutral beam injection; RF heating methods; vacuum systems; tritium handling.
    </course>
    <course name="Group Study for Advanced Undergraduates" number="198" units="1-4">
        Group studies of selected topics.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study" number="199" units="1-4">
        Supervised independent study. Enrollment restrictions apply; see the Introduction to Courses and Curricula section of this catalog.
    </course>
    <course name="Nuclear Reactions and Interactions of Radiation with Matter" number="201" units="4">
        Interaction of gamma rays, neutrons, and charged particles with matter; nuclear structure and radioactive decay; cross sections and energetics of nuclear reactions; nuclear fission and the fission products; fission and fusion reactions as energy sources.
    </course>
    <course name="Irradiation Effects in Nuclear Materials" number="220" units="3">
        Physical aspects and computer simulation of radiation damage in metals. Void swelling and irradiation creep. Mechanical analysis of structures under irradiation. Sputtering, blistering, and hydrogen behavior in fusion reactor materials.
    </course>
    <course name="Corrosion in Nuclear Power Systems" number="221" units="3">
        Structural metals in nuclear power plants; properties and fabrication of Zircaloy; aqueous corrosion of reactor components; structural integrity of reactor components under combined mechanical loading, neutron irradiation, and chemical environment.
    </course>
    <course name="Safety Assessment for Geological Disposal of Radioactive Wastes" number="224" units="3">
        Multi-barrier concept; groundwater hydrology, mathematical modeling of mass transport in heterogeneous media, source term for far-field model; near-field chemical environment, radionuclide release from waste solids, modeling of radionuclide transport in the near field, effect of temperature on repository performance, effect of water flow, effect of geochemical conditions, effect of engineered barrier alteration; overall performance assessment, performance index, uncertainty associated with assessment, regulation and standards.
    </course>
    <course name="The Nuclear Fuel Cycle" number="225" units="3">
        This course is intended for graduate students interested in acquiring a foundation in nuclear fuel cycle with topics ranging from nuclear-fuel reprocessing to waste treatment and final disposal. The emphasis is on the relationship between nuclear-power utilization and its environmental impacts. The goal is for graduate engineering students to gain sufficient understanding in how nuclear-power utilization affects the environment, so that they are better prepared to design an advanced system that would result in minimized environmental impact. The lectures will consist of two parts. The first half includes mathematical models for individual processes in a fuel cycle, such as nuclear fuel reprocessing, waste solidification, repository performance, and nuclear transmutation in a nuclear reactor. In the second half, these individual models are integrated, which enables students to evaluate environmental impact of a fuel cycle.
    </course>
    <course name="Analytical Methods for Non-Proliferation" number="230" units="4">
        Use of nuclear measurement techniques to detect clandestine movement and/or possession of nuclear materials by third parties. Nuclear detection, forensics, signatures, and active passive interrogation methodologies will be explored. Techniques currently deployed for arms control and treaty verification will be discussed. Emphasis will be placed on common elements of detection technology from the viewpoint of resolution of threat signatures from false positives due to naturally occurring radioactive material. Laboratory will involve experiments conducted in the Nucleonics Laboratory featuring passive and active neutron signals, gamma ray detection, fission neutron multiplicity, and U and Pu isotopic identification and age determination. Students should be familiar with alpha, beta, gamma, and neutron radiation and basic concepts of nuclear fission.
    </course>
    <course name="Nuclear Reactor Theory" number="250" units="4">
        Fission characteristics; neutron chain reactions, neutron transport and diffusion theory; reactor kinetics; multigroup methods, fast and thermal spectrum calculations, inhomogeneous reactor design, effects of poisons and fuel depletion.
    </course>
    <course name="Numerical Simulation in Radiation Transport" number="255" units="3">
        Computational methods used to analyze nuclear reactor systems described by various differential, integral, and integro-differential equations. Numerical methods include finite difference, finite elements, discrete ordinates, and Monte Carlo. Examples from neutron and photon transport, heat transfer, and thermal hydraulics. An overview of optimization techniques for solving the resulting discrete equations on vector and parallel computer systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Thermal Aspects of Nuclear Reactors" number="260" units="4">
        Fluid dynamics and heat transfer; thermal and hydraulic analysis of nuclear reactors; two-phase flow and boiling; compressible flow; stress analysis; energy conversion methods.
    </course>
    <course name="Design Analysis of Nuclear Reactors" number="265" units="3">
        Principles and techniques of economic analysis to determine capital and operating costs; fuel management and fuel cycle optimization; thermal limits on reactor performance, thermal converters, and fast breeders; control and transient problems; reactor safety and licensing; release of radioactivity from reactors and fuel processing plants.
    </course>
    <course name="Nuclear Reactor Safety" number="267" units="3">
        Principles and methods used in the safety evaluation of nuclear power plants. Safety philosophies, design criteria and regulations. Deterministic and probabilistic models, reliability analysis, nuclear and thermal-hydraulic transients, radiological consequences, and risk assessment. Design-basis and severe accident analysis, role of engineered safety systems, siting, and licensing. Case studies of accidents.
    </course>
    <course name="Principles and Methods of Risk Analysis" number="275" units="4">
        Principles and methodological approaches for the quantification of technological risk and risk-based decision making.
    </course>
    <course name="Fusion Reactor Engineering" number="280" units="3">
        Engineering and design of fusion systems. Introduction to controlled thermonuclear fusion as an energy economy, from the standpoint of the physics and technology involved. Case studies of fusion reactor design. Engineering principles of support technology for fusion systems.
    </course>
    <course name="Fully Ionized Plasmas" number="281" units="3">
        Introduction to warm and hot magnetized plasmas. Single particle motion in electric and magnetic fields. Collective particle oscillations, waves and instabilities. Magnetohydrodynamic equilibria, stability and transport. Magnetically confined plasmas for controlled fusion. Space plasmas.
    </course>
    <course name="Charged Particle Sources and Beam Technology" number="C282" units="3">
        Topics in this course will include the latest technology of various types of ion and electron sources, extraction and formation of charge particle beams, computer simulation of beam propagation, diagnostics of ion sources and beams, and the applications of beams in fusion, synchrotron light source, neutron generation, microelectronics, lithography, and medical therapy. This is a general accelerator technology and engineering course that will be of interest to graduate students in physics, electrical engineering, and nuclear engineering. Also listed as Engineering C282.
    </course>
    <course name="Charged Particle Beam Instrumentation Laboratory" number="C282L" units="1">
        Optional laboratory designed to accompany Nuclear Engineering C282 and Engineering C282. Ion and electron source operation and beam formation will be demonstrated experimentally. Laboratory sessions will be held at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory. Also listed as Engineering C282L.
    </course>
    <course name="Subsurface Nuclear Technology" number="290B" units="3">
        This course will cover the fundamentals of subsurface nuclear technology and its applications to 1) infer the porosity, the density, elemental composition, and fluid saturation of subsurface media; 2) identify fluid movement in reservoirs, 3) determine fluid characteristics in complex fluid regimes, and 4) perform borehole diagnostics, using neutron and photon measurement and simulation techniques. Application of computational methods will also be covered.
    </course>
    <course name="Uncertainty Analysis for Geologic Disposal" number="290E" units="2">
        This course is intended for graduate students interested in acquiring a foundation in uncertainties associated with safety assessment for geologic disposal of high-level radioactive wastes and spent nuclear fuels. The safety assessment for the geologic disposal system for high-level radioactive wastes needs to cover a time period of 10,000 years or longer, and to take into account heterogeneities observed in geologic formations. Understanding the nature of uncertainties in the assessment results is a key to making right decisions in radioactive waste management. The goal is for graduate engineering students to gain sufficient understanding of how the uncertainties can be quantitatively evaluated. Lectures will consist of two parts. The first half includes an overview of uncertainties observed in the safety assessment for geologic disposal, deterministic models for radionuclide mass transfer and transport, and sensitivity and uncertainties analyses. In the second half, applications of sensitivity and uncertainty analyses for repository performance assessment models are discussed. Implications and interpretations for results of sensitivity and uncertainty analyses are discussed.
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Fluid Mechanics" number="C290F" units="1,2">
        Lectures on special topics which will be announced at the beginning of each semester that the course is offered. Topics may include transport and mixing, geophysical fluid dynamics, bio-fluid dynamics, oceanography, free surface flows, non Newtonian fluid mechanics, among other possibilities. Also listed as Environ Sci, Policy, and Management C291, Physics C290I, Mathematics C290C, Chemical Engineering C295M, Civil and Environmental Engineering C290K, Mechanical Engineering C298A, and Bioengineering C290C.
    </course>
    <course name="Group Research Seminars" number="298" units="1">
        Seminars in current research topics in nuclear engineering: Section 1 - Fusion; Section 2 - Nuclear Waste Management; Section 3 - Nuclear Thermal Hydraulics; Section 4 - Nuclear Chemistry; Section 6 - Nuclear Materials; Section 7 - Fusion reaction design; Section 8 - Nuclear Instrumentation.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Research" number="299" units="1-12">
        Investigation of advanced nuclear engineering problems.
    </course>
    <course name="Teaching Techniques in Nuclear Engineering" number="301" units="1-3">
        This course is designed to acquaint new teaching assistants with the nature of graduate student instruction in courses in the department of Nuclear Engineering. Discussion, practice, and review of issues relevant to the teaching of nuclear engineering. Effective teaching methods will be introduced by experienced GSIs and faculty.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study for Doctoral Students" number="602" units="1-8">
        Individual study in consultation with the major field adviser, intended to provide an opportunity for qualified students to prepare themselves for the various examinations required of candidates for the Ph.D.
    </course>
</department>
