<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<department abbr="PHYSICS" name="Physics">
    <course name="Physics for Scientists and Engineers" number="7A" units="4">
        Mechanics and wave motion.
    </course>
    <course name="Physics for Scientists and Engineers" number="H7A" units="4">
        Honors sequence corresponding to 7A-7B-7C, but with a greater emphasis on theory as opposed to problem solving. Recommended for those students who have had advanced Physics on the high school level and who are intending to declare a major in physics. Entrance into H7A is decided on the basis of performance on an examination given during the first week of class or the consent of the instructor, and into H7B-H7C on performance in previous courses in a standard sequence.
    </course>
    <course name="Physics for Scientists and Engineers" number="7B" units="4">
        Heat, electricity, and magnetism.
    </course>
    <course name="Physics for Scientists and Engineers" number="H7B" units="4">
        Honors sequence corresponding to 7A-7B-7C, but with a greater emphasis on theory as opposed to problem solving. Recommended for those students who have had advanced Physics on the high school level and who are intending to declare a major in physics. Entrance into H7A is decided on the basis of performance on an examination given during the first week of class or the consent of the instructor, and into H7B-H7C on performance in previous courses in a standard sequence.
    </course>
    <course name="Physics for Scientists and Engineers" number="7C" units="4">
        Electromagnetic waves, optics, relativity, and quantum physics.
    </course>
    <course name="Physics for Scientists and Engineers" number="H7C" units="4">
        Honors sequence corresponding to 7A-7B-7C, but with a greater emphasis on theory as opposed to problem solving. Recommended for those students who have had advanced Physics on the high school level and who are intending to declare a major in physics. Entrance into H7A is decided on the basis of performance on an examination given during the first week of class or the consent of the instructor, and into H7B-H7C on performance in previous courses in a standard sequence.
    </course>
    <course name="Introductory Physics" number="8A" units="4">
        Introduction to forces, kinetics, equilibria, fluids, waves, and heat. This course presents concepts and methodologies for understanding physical phenomena, and is particularly useful preparation for upper division study in biology and architecture.
    </course>
    <course name="Introductory Physics" number="8B" units="4">
        Introduction to electricity, magnetism, electromagnetic waves, optics, and modern physics. The course presents concepts and methodologies for understanding physical phenomena, and is particularly useful preparation for upper division study in biology and architecture.
    </course>
    <course name="Descriptive Introduction to Physics" number="10" units="3">
        The most interesting and important topics in physics, stressing conceptual understanding rather than math, with applications to current events. Topics covered may vary and may include energy and conservation, radioactivity, nuclear physics, the Theory of Relativity, lasers, explosions, earthquakes, superconductors, and quantum physics.
    </course>
    <course name="Descriptive Introduction to Physics" number="C10" units="3">
        The most interesting and important topics in physics, stressing conceptual understanding rather than math, with applications to current events. Topics covered may vary and may include energy and conservation, radioactivity, nuclear physics, the Theory of Relativity, lasers, explosions, earthquakes, superconductors, and quantum physics. Also listed as Letters and Science C70V.
    </course>
    <course name="Physics of Music" number="21" units="2">
        Physical principles encountered in the study of music. The applicable laws of mechanics, fundamentals of sound, harmonic content, principles of sound production in musical instruments, musical scales. Numerous illustrative lecture demonstrations will be given. Only the basics of high school algebra and geometry will be used.
    </course>
    <course name="Physics and Music" number="C21" units="2">
        What can we learn about the nature of reality and the ways that we humans have invented to discover how the world works? An exploration of these questions through the physical principles encountered in the study of music. The applicable laws of mechanics, fundamentals of sound, harmonic content, principles of sound production in musical instruments, musical scales. Numerous illustrative lecture demonstrations will be given. Only the basics of high school algebra and geometry will be used. Also listed as Letters and Science C70W.
    </course>
    <course name="Freshman Seminars" number="24" units="1">
        The Berkeley Seminar Program has been designed to provide new students with the opportunity to explore an intellectual topic with a faculty member in a small-seminar setting. Berkeley Seminars are offered in all campus departments, and topics vary from department to department and semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Lower Division Physics Seminar" number="39" units="1.5-4">
        Enrollment limited to 20 students per section. Physics seminar course designed for both non major students and students considering a major in physics. Topics vary from semester to semester.
    </course>
    <course name="Supplementary Work in Lower Division Physics" number="49" units="1-3">
        Students with partial credit in lower division physics courses may, with consent of instructor, complete the credit under this heading.
    </course>
    <course name="Sophomore Seminar" number="84" units="1,2">
        Sophomore seminars are small interactive courses offered by faculty members in departments all across the campus. Sophomore seminars offer opportunity for close, regular intellectual contact between faculty members and students in the crucial second year. The topics vary from department to department and semester to semester. Enrollment limited to 15 sophomores.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study" number="98" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study" number="99" units="1-4">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Communicating Physics and Physical Science" number="100" units="2">
        For undergraduate and graduate students interested in improving their ability to communicate scientific knowledge by teaching science in K-12 schools. The course will combine instruction in inquiry-based science teaching methods and learning pedagogy with 10 weeks of supervised teaching experience in a local school. Students will practice, with support and mentoring, communicating scientific knowledge through presentations and hands-on activities. Approximately three hours per week including time spent in school classrooms.
    </course>
    <course name="Analytic Mechanics" number="105" units="4">
        Newtonian mechanics, motion of a particle in one, two, and three dimensions, Larange's equations, Hamilton's equations, central force motion, moving coordinate systems, mechanics of continuous media, oscillations, normal modes, rigid body dynamics, tensor analysis techniques.
    </course>
    <course name="Electromagnetism and Optics" number="110A" units="4">
        A course emphasizing electromagnetic theory and applications; charges and currents; electric and magnetic fields; dielectric, conducting, and magnetic media; relativity, Maxwell equations. Wave propagation in media, radiation and scattering, Fourier optics, interference and diffraction, ray optics and applications.
    </course>
    <course name="Electromagnetism and Optics" number="110B" units="4">
        A course emphasizing electromagnetic theory and applications; charges and currents; electric and magnetic fields; dielectric, conducting, and magnetic media; relativity, Maxwell equations. Wave propagation in media, radiation and scattering, Fourier optics, interference and diffraction, ray optics and applications.
    </course>
    <course name="Modern Physics and Advanced Electrical Laboratory" number="111" units="1-3">
        The first semester (3 units), on Basic Semiconductor Circuits (BSC), covers introductory analog and digital circuits. The class meets for two 4-hour afternoon lab sessions, and a 1-1/2 hour weekly lecture. In the second semester, Advanced Lab (3 units), students complete 4 of 20+ advanced experiments. These include many in atomic, nuclear, classical, and solid-state physics, among others. Students may, with approval, enroll in an optional third semester for variable units.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Statistical and Thermal Physics" number="112" units="4">
        Basic concepts of statistical mechanics, microscopic basis of thermodynamics and applications to macroscopic systems, condensed states, phase transformations, quantum distributions, elementary kinetic theory of transport processes, fluctuation phenomena.
    </course>
    <course name="Particle Physics" number="129" units="4">
        Tools of particle and nuclear physics. Properties, classification, and interaction of particles including the quark-gluon constituents of hadrons. High energy phenomena analyzed by quantum mechanical methods. Course will survey the field including some related topics in nuclear physics.
    </course>
    <course name="Contemporary Physics" number="132" units="3">
        A general descriptive course of selected topics in contemporary physics. Subject matter will vary and may include topics from special and general relativity, atomic and nuclear physics, radiation, fundamental particles and their symmetries, superconductivity and superfluidity, solid state physics, astrophysics, and cosmology.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantum Mechanics" number="137A" units="4">
        Introduction to the methods of quantum mechanics with applications to atomic, molecular, solid state, nuclear and elementary particle physics.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantum Mechanics" number="137B" units="4">
        Introduction to the methods of quantum mechanics with applications to atomic, molecular, solid state, nuclear and elementary particle physics.
    </course>
    <course name="Modern Atomic Physics" number="138" units="3">
        This course has two goals: 1) The description and calculation of the properties of atomic energy levels based on the central field approximation. The ideas developed in this description are widely used in solid state, particle and nuclear physics. 2) The description of modern experimental methods in atomic physics and some of the important physics obtained from them. Examples are magnetic resonance, lasers and masers, ion and neutral atom traps, optical pumping and beam foil spectroscopy.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Relativity and General Relativity" number="139" units="3">
        Historical and experimental foundations of Einstein's special theory of relativity; spatial and temporal measurements, particle dynamics, electrodynamics, Lorentz invariants. Introduction to general relativity. Selected applications. Designed for advanced undergraduates in physics and astronomy.
    </course>
    <course name="Solid State Physics" number="141A" units="4">
        A thorough introductory course in modern solid state physics. Crystal symmetries; classification of solids and their bonding; electromagnetic, elastic, and particle waves in periodic lattices; thermal magnetic and dielectric properties of solids; energy bands of metals and semi-conductors; superconductivity; magnetism; ferroelectricity; magnetic resonances.
    </course>
    <course name="Solid State Physics" number="141B" units="3">
        A thorough introductory course in modern solid state physics. Crystal symmetries; classification of solids and their bonding; electromagnetic, elastic, and particle waves in periodic lattices; thermal magnetic and dielectric properties of solids; energy bands of metals and semi-conductors; superconductivity; magnetism; ferroelectricity; magnetic resonances.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Plasma Physics" number="142" units="4">
        Motion of charged particles in electric and magnetic fields, dynamics of fully ionized plasma from both microscopic and macroscopic point of view, magnetohydrodynamics, small amplitude waves; examples from astrophysics, space sciences and controlled-fusion research.
    </course>
    <course name="Elective Physics: Special Topics" number="151" units="3">
        Topics vary from semester to semester. The subject matter level and scope of the course are such that it is acceptable as the required elective course in the Physics major. See Department of Physics course announcements.
    </course>
    <course name="Relativistic Astrophysics and Cosmology" number="C161" units="4">
        Elements of general relativity. Physics of pulsars, cosmic rays, black holes. The cosmological distance scale, elementary cosmological models, properties of galaxies and quasars. The mass density and age of the universe. Evidence for dark matter and dark energy and concepts of the early universe and of galaxy formation. Reflections on astrophysics as a probe of the extrema of physics. Also listed as Astronomy C161.
    </course>
    <course name="Principles of Molecular Biophysics" number="177" units="3">
        We will review the structure of proteins, nucleic acids, carbohydrates, lipids, and the forces and interactions maintaining their structure in solution. We will describe the thermodynamics and kinetics of protein folding. The principles of polymer chain statistics and of helix-coil transitions in biopolymers will be reviewed next, together with biopolymer dynamics. We will then cover the main structural methods in biology: X-ray crystallography, MNR and fluorescence spectroscopy, electron and probe microscopy, and single molecular methods.
    </course>
    <course name="Physics Honors Course" number="H190" units="2">
        A seminar which includes study and reports on current theoretical and experimental problems. Open to all students.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantum Information Science and Technology" number="C191" units="3">
        This multidisciplinary course provides an introduction to fundamental conceptual aspects of quantum mechanics from a computational and informational theoretic perspective, as well as physical implementations and technological applications of quantum information science. Basic sections of quantum algorithms, complexity, and cryptography, will be touched upon, as well as pertinent physical realizations from nanoscale science and engineering. Also listed as Chemistry C191 and Computer Science C191.
    </course>
    <course name="Senior Honors Thesis Research" number="H195A" units="2">
        Thesis work under the supervision of a faculty member. To obtain credit the student must, at the end of two semesters, submit a satisfactory thesis. A total of four units must be taken. The units may be distributed between one or two semesters in any way.
    </course>
    <course name="Senior Honors Thesis Research" number="H195B" units="2">
        Thesis work under the supervision of a faculty member. To obtain credit the student must, at the end of two semesters, submit a satisfactory thesis. A total of four units must be taken. The units may be distributed between one or two semesters in any way.
    </course>
    <course name="Directed Group Study" number="198" units="1-4">
        Enrollment restrictions apply; see the Introduction to Courses and Curricula section in this catalog.
    </course>
    <course name="Supervised Independent Study" number="199" units="1-3">
        Enrollment restrictions apply; see the Introduction to Courses and Curricula section in this catalog.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Nano-Science and Engineering" number="C201" units="3">
        A three-module introduction to the fundamental topics of Nano-Science and Engineering (NSE) theory and research within chemistry, physics, biology, and engineering. This course includes quantum and solid-state physics; chemical synthesis, growth fabrication, and characterization techniques; structures and properties of semiconductors, polymer, and biomedical materials on nanoscales; and devices based on nanostructures. Students must take this course to satisfy the NSE Designated Emphasis core requirement. Also listed as Materials Science and Engineering C261 and Nanoscale Science and Engineering C201.
    </course>
    <course name="Computational Nanoscience" number="C203" units="2">
        A multidisciplinary overview of computational nanoscience for both theorists and experimentalists. This course teaches the main ideas behind different simulation methods; how to decompose a problem into &quot;simulatable&quot; constituents; how to simulate the same thing two different ways; knowing what you are doing and why thinking is still important; the importance of talking to experimentalists; what to do with your data and how to judge its validity; why multiscale modeling is both important and nonsense. Also listed as Nanoscale Science and Engineering C242.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Dynamics" number="205A" units="4">
        Lagrange and Hamiltonian dynamics, variational methods, symmetry, kinematics and dynamics of rotation, canonical variables and transformations, perturbation theory, non-linear dynamics, KAM theory.
    </course>
    <course name="Advanced Dynamics" number="205B" units="4">
        Continuous systems, dissipative systems. Attractors. Emphasis on recent developments, including turbulence.
    </course>
    <course name="Classical Electromagnetism" number="209" units="5">
        Maxwell's equations, gauge transformations and tensors. Complete development of special relativity, with applications. Plane waves in material media, polarization, Fresnel equations, attenuation, and dispersion. Wave equation with sources, retarded solution for potentials, and fields. Cartesian and spherical multipole expansions, vector spherical harmonics, examples of radiating systems, diffraction, and optical theorem. Fields of charges in arbitrary motion, radiated power, relativistic (synchrotron) radiation, and radiation in collisions.
    </course>
    <course name="Equilibrium Statistical Physics" number="211" units="4">
        Foundations of statistical physics. Ensemble theory. Degenerate systems. Systems of interacting particles.
    </course>
    <course name="Nonequilibrium Statistical Physics" number="212" units="4">
        Time dependent processes. Kinetic equations. Transport processes. Irreversibility. Theory of many-particle systems. Fluctuation phenomena.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Many-Body Physics" number="216" units="4">
        Quantum theory of many-particle systems. Applications of theory and technique to physical systems. Pairing phenomena, superfluidity, equation of state, critical phenomena, phase transitions, nuclear matter.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantum Mechanics" number="221A" units="5">
        Basic assumptions of quantum mechanics; quantum theory of measurement; matrix mechanics; Schroedinger theory; symmetry and invariance principles; theory of angular momentum; stationary state problems; variational principles; time independent perturbation theory; time dependent perturbation theory; theory of scattering.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantum Mechanics" number="221B" units="5">
        Many-body methods, radiation field quantization, relativistic quantum mechanics, applications.
    </course>
    <course name="Particle Physics Phenomenology" number="226" units="4">
        Introduction to particle physics phenomena. Emphasis is placed on experimental tests of particle physics models. Topics include Quark model spectroscopy; weak decays; overview of detectors and accelerators; e+e- annihilation; parton model; electron-proton and neutrino-proton scattering; special topics of current interest.
    </course>
    <course name="Extragalactic Astronomy and Cosmology" number="C228" units="3">
        A survey of physical cosmology - the study of the origin, evolution, and fate of the universe. Topics include the Friedmann-Robertson-Walker model, thermal history and big bang nucleosynthesis, evidence and nature of dark matter and dark energy, the formation and growth of galaxies and large scale structure, the anisotropy of the cosmic microwave radiation, inflation in the early universe, tests of cosmological models, and current research areas. The course complements the material of Astronomy 218. Also listed as Astronomy C228.
    </course>
    <course name="General Relativity" number="231" units="4">
        An introduction to Einstein's theory of gravitation. Tensor analysis, general relativistic models for matter and electromagnetism, Einstein's field equations. Applications, for example, to the solar system, dense stars, black holes, and cosmology.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantum Field Theory I" number="232A" units="4">
        Introduction to quantum field theory: canonical quantization of scalar, electromagnetic, and Dirac fields; derivation of Feynman rules; regularization and renormalization; introduction to the renormalization group; elements of the path integral.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantum Field Theory II" number="232B" units="4">
        Renormalization of Yang-Mills gauge theories: BRST quantization of gauge theories; nonperturbative dynamics; renormalization group; basics of effective field theory; large N; solitons; instantons; dualities. Selected current topics.
    </course>
    <course name="Standard Model and Beyond I" number="233A" units="4">
        Introduction to the standard model of particle physics and its applications: construction of the standard model; Higgs mechanism; phenomenology of weak interctions; chiral Lagrangian; QCD and scaling violation.
    </course>
    <course name="Standard Model and Beyond II" number="233B" units="4">
        Advanced topics in the standard model and beyond: open problems in the standard model; supersymmetric models; grand unification; neutrino physics; theories with flat and warped extra dimensions; models at the TeV scale; low string/gravity scale. Selected current topics.
    </course>
    <course name="String Theory I" number="234A" units="4">
        Perturbative theory of the bosonic strings, superstrings, and heterotic strings: NSR and GS formulations; 2d CFT; strings in background fields; T-duality; effective spacetime supergravity; perturbative description of D-branes; elements of compactifications and string phenomemology; perturbative mirror symmetry.
    </course>
    <course name="String Theory II" number="234B" units="4">
        Nonperturbative apsects of string theory. Topics selected from black holes; black branes; Bekenstein-Hawking entropy; D-branes; string dualities; M-theory; holographic principle and its realizations; AdS/CFT correspondence; gauge theory/gravity dualities; flux compactifications; cosmology in string theory; topological string theories. Selected current topics.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantum Theory of Solids" number="240A" units="4">
        Excitations and interactions in solids; crystal structures, symmetries, Bloch's theorem; energy bands; electron dynamics; impurity states; lattice dynamics, phonons; many-electron interactions; density functional theory; dielectric functions, conductivity and optical properties; excitons; electron-phonon interactions, polarons; Fermi surfaces; magnetoresistance; quantum Hall effect; transport processes, Boltzmann equation; superconductivity, BCS theory; many-body perturbation theory, Green's functions.
    </course>
    <course name="Quantum Theory of Solids" number="240B" units="4">
        Excitations and interactions in solids; crystal structures, symmetries, Bloch's theorem; energy bands; electron dynamics; impurity states; lattice dynamics, phonons; many-electron interactions; density functional theory; dielectric functions, conductivity and optical properties; excitons; electron-phonon interactions, polarons; Fermi surfaces; magnetoresistance; quantum Hall effect; transport processes, Boltzmann equation; superconductivity, BCS theory; many-body perturbation theory, Green's functions.
    </course>
    <course name="Theoretical Plasma Physics" number="242A" units="4">
        Analysis of plasma behavior according to the Vlasov, Fokker-Planck equations, guiding center and hydromagnetic descriptions. Study of equilibria, stability, linear and nonlinear electromagnetic waves, transport, and interaction with radiation. Rigorous kinetic theory.
    </course>
    <course name="Theoretical Plasma Physics" number="242B" units="4">
        Analysis of plasma behavior according to the Vlasov, Fokker-Planck equations, guiding center and hydromagnetic descriptions. Study of equilibria, stability, linear and nonlinear electromagnetic waves, transport, and interaction with radiation. Rigorous kinetic theory.
    </course>
    <course name="Special Topics in Physics" number="250" units="2-4">
        Topics will vary from semester to semester. See Department of Physics announcements.
    </course>
    <course name="Introduction to Graduate Research in Physics" number="251" units="1">
        A survey of experimental and theoretical research in the Department of Physics, designed for first-year graduate students. One regular meeting each week with supplementary visits to experimental laboratories. Meetings include discussions with research staff.
    </course>
    <course name="High Energy Astrophysics" number="C254" units="3">
        Basic physics of high energy radiation processes in an astrophysics environment. Cosmic ray production and propagation. Applications selected from pulsars, x-ray sources, supernovae, interstellar medium, extragalactic radio sources, quasars, and big-bang cosmologies. Also listed as Astronomy C254.
    </course>
    <course name="Theoretical Astrophysics Seminar" number="C285" units="2">
        The study of theoretical astrophysics. Also listed as Astronomy C285.
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290A" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290B" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Cosmology" number="C290C" units="2">
        Astronomy C290C.
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290D" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290E" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290F" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290G" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290H" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290I" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Topics in Fluid Mechanics" number="C290I" units="1,2">
        Lectures on special topics which will be announced at the beginning of each semester that the course is offered. Topics may include transport and mixing, geophysical fluid dynamics, bio-fluid dynamics, oceanography, free surface flows, non Newtonian fluid mechanics, among other possibilities. Also listed as Environ Sci, Policy, and Management C291, Mathematics C290C, Chemical Engineering C295M, Nuclear Engineering C290F, Civil and Environmental Engineering C290K, Mechanical Engineering C298A, and Bioengineering C290C.
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290J" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290K" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290L" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar in Non-Neutral Plasmas" number="290N" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290P" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar in Quantum Optics" number="290Q" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290R" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290S" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290T" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290X" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290Y" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Seminar" number="290Z" units="2">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Special Study for Graduate Students" number="295" units="1-4">
        This course is arranged to allow qualified graduate students to investigate possible research fields or to pursue problems of interest through reading or non-laboratory study under the direction of faculty members who agree to give such supervision.
    </course>
    <course name="Research" number="299" units="1-12">
        
    </course>
    <course name="Professional Preparation: Supervised Teaching of Physics" number="300" units="2">
        Discussion, problem review and development, guidance of physics laboratory experiments, course development, supervised practice teaching.
    </course>
    <course name="Individual Study for Doctoral Students" number="602" units="1-8">
        Individual study in consultation with the major field adviser intended to provide an opportunity for qualified students to prepare themselves for the various examinations required of candidates for the Ph.D.
    </course>
</department>
